send messages to an object called a text editing controller and say hey my text
has changed that is our proxy to a text field in
flutter okay so that's setting up that and what we need to also do is to allow
the user to enter multiple lines of text in this text field because remember text
fields usually in flutter are like one line so for instance you're writing an
email address or you're writing your password so they're not like multi-line
text fields by default unless you make them multi-line so that's what we're
going to do now so we're going to say our keyboard type
you can see it's of type text input type so then say text input type
alt-line all right so that's going to allow you to have a little enter key at
the bottom uh right hand side of your keyboard if you're left to right on like
english language or if you're right to left language like arabic then that
little enter key is going to be at the bottom left so then in here
you will get that keyboard as you'll soon see actually and
you'll get that key on your keyboard to go to the next line
now in flutter as it is also in swift when
you're doing ios development there is a weird habit of
creating text fields that are multi-line with strange parameters and
unfortunately it has leaked to flutter as well in that
um you you don't have like a parameter in
text field that says multiline so if you want to create a text field that
is multi-line and it kind of like expands as you enter more text into it
then unfortunately you have to call and you have to assign null to the max
line's parameter there are some discussions on github
about why that's the case but there's a good reason behind it okay
um and what we're then gonna do is if we if
we do like this and i press command s and we go here
and we press the plus button in here okay you'll see there's a text field in
here that's great okay however it's not so obvious the user
what what am i supposed to do what is this line here am i gonna tap somewhere
here it's not so obvious so what we're gonna do is to add something called a
hint to this text field if you're a designer or a developer from before you
probably already know what a hint is but if you don't know what a hint is a hint
is little um as this name indicates a little text
that usually gets displayed to the user telling telling her or him uh
what is expected to be entered in this uh field so
let's go and add the hint and that is through a property on our text field
called decoration and that's uh
an input decoration inside our input decoration we're going
to add a parameter called hint text and here we're just going to say start
typing your notes like this all right
so command s and
a comma here to prefi the code a little bit
but there we go now we have hints in here and as i bring up as i tap on this
text field you can see i can start typing in here and press this little
button that i was talking about for multi-line and as i start typing more
and more then the text field is gonna increase in size
all right so
that is that is really what we have to do in this chapter i hope i didn't scare
you by saying in the beginning of this chapter that this chapter is gonna be
kind of code heavy but i mean there were there was quite a lot
of code but hopefully you could stick with me throughout the chapter and get
it to this point as is the tradition in all the other
chapters we worked on we're not gonna
lose we don't want to lose the work that we're doing on our code so we need to
make sure that we commit and also we tag our code
okay so let me change the screen layout a little bit
and we've tagged the previous chapter as step 13 so as the caption indicates here
we're going to tag and commit this code as step 14 so
i'm going to say git status two files change and then i'm gonna add
them all to the staging environment and then i'm gonna commit them
as step 14 and push my changes to github
and then i'm gonna tag our code as step 14 as well and then push our tags
okay um so
that was that for tagging um now again as is tradition for other chapters as
well at the end of every chapter we're going to talk about what we are going to
discuss in the chapter that follows so we are now actually creating notes it
may not be immediately visible to you but if you if you for instance have
created some notes then this screen should be able to render those notes
because the new note view is doing everything necessary to not only create
the note and let's see where it is here create the new note
but it also is updating that note for us so here you can see update note so those
notes are in the database it's just that the main ui of the application which is
this node c the dark is not able to render them all it's doing is just
saying waiting for all nodes so it's not so exciting but just know that
you are getting there and we are getting there it's just there are a few steps
left to handle that and uh that's exactly what we're gonna do in the next
chapter so get some tea and coffee if you want to and i'll see you there
hello and welcome to chapter 32 of the slotzer course in the previous chapters
we've been talking quite a lot about our node service and creating stream
controller in order to populate the stream control with the nodes and we
also have a buffer locally called underscore nodes in our node service and
so we're kind of like working with our notes in a really good and organic way
and we also work with the new node view dark file where we created a stateful
widget that had a text editing controller and i also allowed the user
to enter some text we manage even to save that text as a
new note into the database so we've done quite a lot however what wasn't so much
fun was that it was a little bit of an anti-climax in that we we are able to
create notes but we're not able to actually display them so we're
populating the database with new notes but no one is able to show them on the
screen and that's what we're going to take care of in this chapter
so let me bring the code that we've written so far to the screen here
and um i'm going to clear this get status just
to make sure everything's working fine yeah
the visual studio code i'm going to bring scrcpy to the right hand side
and we have to now talk about a little
problem that we have with our nodes service you see if you look at the code
here i'm going to increase the size so you see better
so if you have a look at our note service
and we have this uh shared instance that we've created here okay so whenever
somebody says note service parenthesis then they're actually not creating any
instance they're not creating a new instance of node service but they're
going through this factory initializer which in turn calls this shared
static final which in turn calls this internal or private constructor that
means we've created a singleton so creating a new node service over and
over again is not gonna um create a new instance
he's just gonna get the same shared instance and then whoever then starts
talk reading or you see all notes in here
properly all notes is delegating its responsibility to the node stream
controller or stream however our node stream controller is a broadcast stream
controller and what that means is that a stream controller that
doesn't really hold on to its current value for new listeners so let's say you
have a stream controller that is sitting here and you start listening to events
uh to that stream controller from one place and then an event comes into the
stream controller and stream controller says oh um i have one listener right
here i'm gonna delegate this information to that's uh that listener
all looks fine however however after the propagation of this event into the
stream controller the stream controller is not going to hold on to this value
when a new listener comes in from another side so
any new listener to your broadcast stream controller is not going to be
informed of the current information which is populated in that stream
controller so if you're familiar with for instance uh reactive programming
with rx you may know this as a published subject and the same is true if you're
for instance versus using rx java or rx scotland
rx swift even if you're doing like um combined programming with a swift ui you
will know these as like published subjects so
a stream controller that is broadcast is not gonna hold on in to its current uh
value for new listeners we need to we need to remedy that and the way to do
that is just to move the initialization of node stream
controller to our initializer right here as we'll soon see
so i'm going to do a little bit of a shuffling of
screen sizes in here all right so as the caption indicates
what we need to do and we need to make this notes stream controller
which is let's see where it is it's right here we need to make it a late
final so grab the data type from where it is and just say late final put the
data type in here and then remove the equal all right so now it is our
responsibility to ensure that this node stream controller is actually
initialized upon constructor upon constructing a new instance of our node
service okay so let's go ahead and do that inside
shared instance which is right here so what we need to do now is to say node
stream controller is a stream controller list of
database nodes and then we do the exact same thing as we did before using
broadcast however what we're going to do in here is to
use a property inside the broadcast stream listener called on listen so this
unless and uh callback is going to get called whenever
a new listener subscribes to our note stream controller
note stream controllers stream so upon this happening we need to ensure
that our node stream controllers stream is populated with all the values that
we've currently read from the database so let's go ahead and do that
so we're just going to go ahead and say notes
stream controller sync add notes just like that all right so
this ensures anyone who starts listening to our
to this property all notes which in turn uses the no stream controller if it's a
new subscriber then it's gonna the unlisted um callback is gonna get called
and then we're gonna populate our stream controllers a stream with those notes
that we've already read from the database
okay let's now move to the next note before
we can actually get on with the rest of this chapter as the caption indicates as
we shouldn't close the db upon hot reload after opening db we shouldn't
close it otherwise upon every reload it gets closed
so the problem that i'm referring to is in inside our notes view and it is right
here inside our dispose so upon doing hot reload what we're doing is that
we're saying node service close which in turn is going to actually close the
database but remember node service is and is was and is supposed to be a
singleton where upon creation and upon doing an open one time it should keep
its state so we shouldn't play with closing of the
database inside any of our widgets because that is going to interfere with
the internals and how the node service is actually supposed to work so what
we're going to do as you can see since this pose function in here the
overwriting overwriting of the dispose function the only thing it was actually
doing was to close the node services database we're just going to remove this
function for now because we have nothing else to dispose of at the moment in our
notes view
all right um so what we need to do is actually get to
the meat of this section which i'm so excited about for this chapter
and that is to start working with the list view
and what we need to do is to make sure that we have a list that we can
we can grab the data that comes from our stream here stream builder you can see
it reads all the notes and right now we're just saying waiting for all nodes
so we're going to change that and instead we're actually going to start
using something called a list view now list view in flutter is an amazing
widget which i can actually show you here so if you just type list view and
then command and click control click on linux and windows you
can see it's a box scroll view extends box scroll view which in turn is a
scroll view which in turn is a stateless widget so
a list view has uh some function some really great functionality uh that it
exposes using is builder we can see here it has a builder function and i believe
it's a static function here or it's actually constructor great okay
so it has a builder and inside your builder you will be able to pass two
important parameters to this list view so we're gonna say
we return a list view instead of that little text that we had which right now
says waiting for all notes in here we're gonna say we have two
parameters first we are gonna tell it how many items it has to render on the
screen so we're going to say item count all right
and for the item count we need to actually listen for this snapshots data
so remember the stream builder at the moment is listening for all notes
and so that means the data that comes from snapshot
is actually going to be your um
is going to be the all the notes that we've read from the database so what we
need to do now is just to ensure that upon waiting um in here so
i'm gonna actually remove this and i'm gonna say if
snapshot has data so that's a property on your snapshot that exposes whether
the snapshot has actually pro can actually provide you with some data and
i'm going to put an else in here and upon else we're also going to say return
con circular progress indicator okay and if the
snapshot has any data then let's grab that data so i'm just going to say final
all notes is snapshot that's data as a list of database notes
all right and what we could do we could just say
return const text
got all the notes something like that and we could actually print these notes
to the screen if you want to it's we could say print notes
and i'm going to bring the debug console up
then i'm going to clear the logs and change the screen layout
so you see it better and i'm just gonna do command s
alright and i can see at the moment it's just saying your notes so meaning that
we don't actually have any notes so if i go in here then
you can see all of a sudden we got a new note populated into the database just
because i went here and i said i'm printing some notes so
so i'm gonna say hello okay
see as i'm changing this our snapshot is actually getting updated with new
information and it's constantly printing and it's the note id is the same and you
can see his text is actually changing and if i go out then you can see well
it's just at the moment says got all the notes meaning that you have some notes
so if you're seeing a circular progress indicator instead of like a text at the
moment that we're saying all the notes it's probably because you were like me
and you didn't have any notes in the database all right
okay now we have all the notes so how do we then render these so what we need to
do in here we're going to say return list view i'm going to change the screen
layout let's say list view builder
and you remember i mentioned before we need to populate this listview with two
important parameters one is the item count and at the moment the item count
is all notes count links and then we have our item builder get
some help from your editor to complete this you get a a
build context as the first parameter of type context and then you get an index
okay now inside your item builder your job is
if you look at the at the
signature of item builder it says it's a function
that takes two parameters it build context and an integer for the index and
it has to return a widget you see here so you could return anything in here you
could just say return text item something like that
okay it's not gonna look so pretty though
and actually i can see maybe did we lose our item maybe in here
it is possible that there is something wrong with our note 2 that it's like
deleting the notes it could be so i'm just gonna do a
hot reload here and my scr cpy may actually die no but uh it's it worked
without a problem so we have an item so if that's if that's what you're also
seeing maybe you could do a hot reload because we've changed our nodes service
so it could be the problem that our uh we just needed to do a hot reload for
this unlisten to actually get called all right so that's what we're seeing at the
moment so i can see item in here and i'm gonna press the plus button so and i'm
gonna say hello world in here and i'm gonna go out and all of a sudden
you see two items appearing in here okay but this is not so pretty because
displaying text on the screen is not so nice and you won't have uh
you won't be able to easily add interactions to these items because what
we want ideally is for these items to appear on
the list and then they have like their own sizing so they have a good height so
that they are separated a little bit from each other and as you'll see in the
next chapter we're going to work with um deleting these items so we want the
ability for the user to see some sort of an icon next to each item using which he
or she can click on that icon and delete the item so text in itself is not going
to be able to provide us with all that functionality that we need so
what we need is a little bit more sophisticated widget and it is called
list tile so let's do that let's just say we return at least tile
okay and our list tile is gonna have a um a title so that's the only thing at
the moment we're gonna provide it with and you can see it's a widget
and for the widget of this list and for the title of this list style we're going
to use text um right there okay and i'm going to put
some commas in there so for the text what we're going to say
then is the text in itself is
we want to grab the text that is entered in that note so you see we have all the
notes but we don't have the current note so the current note that we're actually
reading its index is going to be provided to us using this item builders
index so let's go and say final um notes is all nodes at that index so that's the
current node that we're returning a list tile for okay
its text is gonna be the note text as you can see here
uh i can see i've written tile here but it should be title
and in here we have to have a semicolon all right so if i do command s in here
you can see now we have very i mean a lot nicer and prettier versions
of those texts and you can see that they're right here it says hello and
hello world and those are the texts that we entered you can actually test that
and say my new my new notes is entered here
and by pressing the back button you'll see that your note is appearing on the
screen all right but what we want to do here is if you
enter a lot of text in your in your notes so if i go and say here
is a very long text that i've entered and i don't
want it all to be displayed in one tile and then nodes view so we have now a
node that is quite large but this is in it in itself is going to
break a little bit our layout you see in our notes list we don't want to
render the entire note we somehow want to cap
the amount of information that we're displaying to a size that is reasonable
and since our notes don't have titles we
could infer the content of the note by simply rendering just one line of text
and the user should be able to then say oh that's what i've written kind of in
my notes and as you'll see in the latest later chapters we are going to allow the
user to also click on or tap on these existing notes in order to go and see
more information about them so it's not the end of the world if you
don't display like the entire note to the user and as you'll see when users
start to enter more and more information in their notes it's actually not desired
uh desirable to render the entire note because imagine a
note is two pages long or you're gonna have like two very small notes and then
two pages of long of one note it's it's not feasible so actually it is feasible
but it's not a good user interface so i'm going to put a comma here
and i'm just going to use a property in our text called max lines and i'm just
going to say one
and so as you'll see here then what we're going to do is to make
sure that the user kind of understands that there is more information in here
than what we are rendering so we want to put like ellipses at the end of the text
that don't have enough space to render themselves fully so
we're going to say soft wrap and as you can see the information is
whether the text should break at soft line breaks so make sure that it's true
and then we're going to say overflow and we're going to say text overflow
ellipses like that
and now you can see it says here's a very long text blah
blah blah and then dot dot so this is a good indication then to all users to
know that well there's more information to be rendered but there's not enough
space for that information to be rendered on the screen right now
all right so i think i mean we've looked at how that all works we've actually
demoed it so we don't have to do a separate demo for this we've been
looking at it as we've been developing and the application and that's one of
the beauties of flutter so
we don't have to do anything about this demo right now
and you will probably be surprised that this
is all we have to do right now for the notes view there's not much more to work
on we've written
we were able to at the moment create new notes and we're able to display those
notes and one at a time inside this list view builder so you'll learn how to use
the list view builder as well and what we can do as is a tradition
we're gonna go and commit and tag our work so
i'm gonna do some reshuffling on the screen
so you see what i'm doing a little bit better
and i'm gonna go to my built-in terminal here and we're
gonna have a look at the status can see there are two files changed so
let's do git add all
and let's commit this as step 15 and before committing it you can see your
git lock from before the last commit was step 14
so and you can also look at all the tags and we have up to tag 14.
so let's go ahead and say git commit and we do step 15.
now i'm going to push that commit to github or if you're using bitbucket or
any other provider that's fine too and i'm going to tag this as step
15 right and then we're going to push our tags
great that part is now done so we've done what we promised to do in this
chapter the next thing that we have to talk
about as a tradition in all the other chapters is at the end of every chapter
we'll talk about what we're going to talk about in the next chapter and you
can see that we are able to create notes uh we're not able yet to update notes
we're going to get there soon but we also need to allow the user to delete
notes so that's exactly actually what we're gonna
take care of in the next chapter and the next chapter is not gonna be a huge
chapter either just like this one so it's gonna go very smooth but we're
gonna do some quite heavy refactoring on our project as you'll soon see so
grab some refreshments if you want and i'll see you in the next chapter
hello everyone and welcome to chapter 33 of this flutter course
in the previous chapters we've been talking about how to create new notes
and how also to display those notes on the screen
um and now it would make sense for any user of our application to be able to
delete the notes that they've created already
and we are not right now giving that functionality to the user and that's
exactly what we're gonna work on in this chapter
and just a heads up we're gonna work quite a bit with refactoring so things
are gonna get a little bit uncomfortable where the code isn't gonna compile but
we're gonna fix that soon and right after breaking it so we're
going to work a little bit about on our dialogues as well
you see we have a few dialogues at the moment that appear on the screen and for
instance will we display an error to the screen
or to the user where we for instance say oh you couldn't log in or oh your
password was incorrect or we couldn't register this user because it's a a weak
password entered so that's like our error dialogues and
we also have a dialogue that we display to the user when he or she's trying to
log out of the application so we have two dialogues at the moment
and in this chapter what we're going to do is we're going to consolidate how we
also display our dialogues to the user as part of delete
functionality because you see the delete part as well the way we're going to do
it is we're going to let me actually bring the
scrcpy to the screen so how we're going to do it is that we're
going to put a little delete icon next to every item on the list and we're
going to allow the user to tap on those icons in order to display a dialogue
now this is going to be the third dialogue and um a colleague of mine that
i work with which i really admire his way of working he mentions that he makes
things reusable when he gets to the third time of doing the
same thing again so now we've written two dialogues to this point and we also
now need a third dialogue and that's the point that maybe we should actually
consolidate all our dialogue displaying to one
function and then from other functions we're just gonna reuse that okay
so that's what we're gonna do in this chapter
so let's have a look at the code a little bit i'm gonna um
i'm gonna bring the screen to a little bit
um larger display so here
so these this is our application the way we've listed left it at the moment
so like that visual studio code and we have a cr cpy there as well okay
so let's then have a look at our as a caption in case we're going to have a
look at our error dialog so let's go ahead in
our
let's see what we have constant services crowd utilities we have and we have a
function here called show error dialog which in turn says show dialog and then
it says alert dialogue okay then if you have a look at how this is
constructed the only thing it's doing is saying like hey i have um hey i have a
title then i have just one action with a button
and also and that action doesn't return any value and also
we i have some text to display all right great now let's go to our notes view if
you look at our notes view at the end of notes view we have this
logout dialog what does this do it's the same thing it
has show dialog it has an alert dialog inside it it has a title and some text
but it has two actions and these actions they do different things so one action
does uh if it sends a value of false the other
one sends the value of true so every dialogue that appears to the
screen so let's say this one for instance
our logout dialog that's the one we're looking at right now
the cancel button sends a false value and the log out button sends a true
value so the dialogs are all very similar they
have a title they have some contents and they have some actions that the user can
take on those dialogues and these actions then have their own values and
that's what we're going to do in our application right now is that we're
going to consolidate all these into one generic function that is going to kind
of allow us to customize it to our needs all right
so let's have a look at how we can achieve
this so as the caption indicates here we're first going to cut things from the
source and that's like the strategy that i use a lot in software development so
if i'm gonna disrupt things and i'm gonna like change the way things work
i'm not gonna be scared and i'm really not scared of
making things break and i in my opinion you may think differently but in my
opinion it's really good to cut things from the source break the code and then
start fixing things one at a time instead of trying to make sure nothing
breaks while you're refactoring the code so that's what we're going to do here as
the caption indicates we're going to go to short air dialog
let's see if you can find it i like to use command p in visual studio code i'm
going to say the show error dialog in here
and what we're going to do is just we're going to remove all this code that is
there okay so that's that part
and what we're also going to do is um as the cache indicates remove the show log
out the dialog from notes view since we're going to have a generic one so go
into your notes view in here and
remove this show log out dialog all right
we're gonna get errors that's okay and you know this code that we removed also
here show error dialog is used quite a lot so
by removing it if i like search for show air dollar you can see we're actually
using in seven places so all of those places are now gonna have an error
that's okay fine we're gonna fix that soon so don't worry about that
all right so what we need to do in here is before we fix all of that we're gonna
start basically creating our notes list view all right
so at the moment if you look at our notes
view what we have is this beauty in here which is doing quite
a lot of work as you can see it's it has a future builder inside the body of the
notes view and it has a stream builder and a lot of code in here it would be
really great if you could separate this code into its own place and we could
call this widget like a notes list view and that's exactly what we're going to
do in this chapter so let's go ahead in our views inside notes
in here in your
views inside notes let's create a new file and we're going to call it notes
list view dot parts okay like that
and in in notes list view what we're going to do is going to say the notes
list view is a stateless widget so we create a stl which is a stateless widget
and we're going to call it notes list view
as we've seen it before we need to import material so i'm going to do that
right now so all those errors are going to go away
now what we need to do is we need to
actually pass a a list of notes to this notes list
view so that it can render them because you see all the logic for retrieving the
notes can stay still in the notes view but all notes list view is interested in
is a list of notes to display so let's go and expose that
as a parameter in our notes list view so we're going to say final
list of database nodes and you can see database node is not
imported right now but visual studio code is going to be smart enough to
import that so
if you're actually yeah
if your editor like if you're using vim or something on linux or even mac and
windows if you're using that you may have to import these things manually so
um but the import statements i believe i mean if you've gotten to this point in
the course you should be uh
like savvy enough and you should know all these things enough in order to be
able to solve that yourself so um so i'm not going to repeat all that
information again just make sure that your database note is in context in at
this point so that's going to be our notes
and also this notes view as i mentioned in the previous chapter but maybe it's
actually worth mentioning in this chapter because it's very relevant what
we're going to do is beside every note to the right hand side
as the trailing tile widget we're going to display a little like a trashcan icon
that the user can tap on in order to delete a um
notes and what we're going to do then is to
make sure that
that we can basically call a little function to show a delete
dialog to the user so upon you pressing the delete button we're going to display
a dialogue and the delete dialog is going to be very similar to log out like
saying now hey hey you're deleting this note are you sure
and that dialog is going to have two buttons
yes or no or something like that and upon pressing no we're just going to
dismiss the dialogue upon pressing yes then we're going to delete that note
from the database all right so what we need is you can see the notes
list view at the moment isn't like it shouldn't have any connection with the
notes service it should be the notes view that has that connection so this is
how you should also like do your components in flutter in
that you shouldn't leak your services everywhere so if the notes list view
could somehow delegate the deletion task to the notes view that would be ideal so
the notes list view could display the dialogue it could just say hey
are you sure and if the user then says yes the notes list view could then
delegate this information back to its parent and say hey do something with
this information okay
so let's then go and create a little callback definition using typedef
excuse me and we're going to call it delete note
callback okay and this is a void function that takes a database note
oops a database nodes
i'll note like that so we're saying we're defining a function
that we're then going to use in our nodes list view which we call we which
we use as a callback that will be called when the user
presses the yes on this hypothetical dialogue that we're
assuming gonna display that user okay so let's go in here and define that let's
just say um delete node callback and we're just going to say on delete nodes
so this is our callback and you're now getting some errors from a flutter
saying that these parameters aren't defined so i'm going to use visual
studio code and to say define these parameters for me
i'm also going to make them require parameters like this
so that's great we have still some errors in our application so
but we're going to continue building until we can fix all these errors okay
all right that's fantastic so that's the first part that we have to work on so
let's then go ahead and um take our notes view the way it is right here and
you see we already have a list view builder i'm just gonna go and grab this
list view the way it is from there
and i'm i'm actually gonna cut that and bring it into nodes list view inside the
build function alright so inside instead of returning a container i'm just gonna
return that code that i've just pasted that i just cut all right
it looks absolutely horrible at the moment it's because i mean we have so
many errors but i actually like that kind of stuff
to be honest with you some developers get nervous when they have lots of
errors in their code and they just want to patch them up as soon as they can
but we're gonna work just one step at a time as we say in sweden we say
it means one step at a time we're going to fix these errors and at
the end of this chapter everything's going to work i promise you
so let's go in here you can see the first error that we have is all notes
and what all notes is giving us an error for is that it doesn't exist in this
context and that's because we have something called notes all right so
let's go in here and say now we're using notes
and in here we don't have all notes either so we're just going to say notes
notes and that
note is going to be extracted from notes at
that index and the exciting part now is that
we don't just use the title property of our list tile anymore we're going to
start using something called trailing and trailing is a as a property of list
tile that as its name indicates it's going to allow you to
specify a widget that needs to be displayed at the end or the trail of
every list tile and this is where we're going to use an
icon button so to display our little trash can okay so
let's say icon button
and in this icon button what we're going to do then is we're going to define the
uncrest which looks like this and it's icon then
it's going to be icon of icons delete i believe it's called
let's have a look at how delete looks like and you can see it's a little trash
can fantastic and make this cons to make the
analyzer happy as well all right so what do we do i'm pressed so what we
need to do on press is as i mentioned before we need to take care of the
displaying of a dialogue that says let's just call the show delete dialogue
okay so this show delete dialogue we're going to call it and we expect it to
return a true or false remember we haven't implemented the show
delete dialog that's okay we can put some constraints on the
interface of this function yet but it doesn't yet exist so let's just say that
this function show delete dialog takes a build context and it returns true or
false to us so if the user says yes i want to delete some item then it it
returns true if it's if the user says no then this
dialog should return false to us okay so let's go ahead and say final should
uh you should delete is a weight
and when you're using a weight you need to make your own press function async
then we're going to say await show delete dialog we don't have that
function remember but that's okay and when we say
should delete okay if this is boolean then we say if
should delete then what we're going to do is we say
and we call our on deletes notes with the current note okay
so that is just the implementation of this widget
notes list view all right
but don't worry about these errors we're gonna soon fix them so
and just save this file as well
now we need to move to the next item and that's our own generic dialogue you can
see we're going to create a generic dialogue dart
which is so important because pretty much this show generic dialogue and the
variations that we're going to create on it is going to fix all these errors that
we have in our application right now so i'm actually happy to start working on
it i don't know about you so as the caption indicates we're going
to create a file in lib utilities dialogues generic dialogue dart so we
have what folders do we have in here we have lib consonants enums services
utilities all right but inside utilities we don't have at
the moment a dialogues folder and remember that we
removed all the contents of this show error dialog let's just delete the file
now we don't need that so i'm just gonna delete it and move it to trash
so now inside utilities we have nothing so let's go create this new file as the
caption indicates we're gonna say it's gonna be inside a folder called dialogs
and we're going to call it generic dialog.art
all right i'm going to get rid of the sidebar and we now need to start
implementing our generic dialogue
this show generic dialogue is going to be a
little bit complicated and um and i'm saying it a little bit
complicated simply because it's going to use generics
and the reason um i've basically
decided to make it generic is as the name generic indicates this
generic dialogue i mean the file also says generic dialect so you need to kind
of know already what you're getting yourself into
the reason it has to be generic is that it needs to be able to produce
different sorts of values let's go to our notes list view and you see here
we're going to say show delete dialog a function we haven't implemented yet and
show delete dialogue all of a sudden it's going to return true or false okay
that's one thing how about in the case of login view so let's go to login view
how about this case show air dot log remember show error dialog is a is also
a function we're soon gonna develop which we have before we we killed it we
have to develop a new function called show air dialog which in turn is gonna
use our generic dialog but in this case it's not gonna return true or false so
we need to make sure our generic dialogue as its name indicates is a
generic function that can based on what you provide to it is able to return
those values to you and what i mean by what you provide to
it every item every option or every button that is
displayed in our generic dialog is gonna have a value
we're gonna assume that all the buttons that you display in any given dialog is
going to have values of the exact same type so a
dialogue that shows a yes or no button is going to have
two buttons each of which contains a boolean value one true the other one
false or maybe you want to display 10 buttons and two of them have the value
of true and the other one had the others 8 have the value of false but what i
mean is that the buttons inside your generic dialogue are going to have the
same data type all right so we're going to call that data type t
all right so let's go ahead and define this um show
generic dialogue so we're going to say that this dialogue actually returns
um a future of t
and um what we're going to say we're going to say show generic
dialogue and it's
it's a function signature it kind of looks like this
all right so what does it actually mean t optional and that's because remember
on android for instance when you display a dialog to the user the user can
actually press the hardware down button in order to dismiss a dialog without
actually responding to it and ios is actually
not so much like that in is when you display a dialogue it's a modal that the
user has to reply to unless you create your own dialogue or if you're
doing maybe something hacky on the side to say that oh if the user taps outside
the dialogue then it should disappear otherwise dialogues in ios are modal and
have to be responded to however in android it's possible that a user
dismisses a dialogue without actually responding to it and in this case the
show generic dialogue should actually return nil or null depending what
language you're talking about if you're a python developer you'd say none
so so we're going to
define this saying we have a generic dialog that returns some sort of a
optional value all right and the first parameter that we need is
a build context so let's just say build context
and we need a title and content so we're going to say required
also before we do that let's also have a look at this thing that says build
context isn't defined and that's because we have an important material so let's
take care of that and we have to have curly brackets in
these places because required actually requires that okay
so the next parameter that we have to
implement is the title and then the content so both are going to be text or
string so that's the title and now i'm going to
copy paste that i'm going to say content in here content
all right now it's exciting part now what we need is
some sort of ability and some sort of way for the user to be able
to specify like a list of um
a list of buttons to display the to the to the user now every button if we say
every button by default should have for instance
we should we're representing every button as a text button that every text
button needs a string to display all right and then it will have an unpressed
so what we're telling what we're saying is that okay we should be able to render
multiple buttons and every button should have a text
and also we set from before every button should also have some sort of a value
all right which is t optional so we need a way for the user to specify a list of
buttons each of which has a title of type string and also every one of those
buttons should optionally have a value so that's best described with a map of
string as titles and a value of t like this
all right so we're going to type def that we're
going to say we have a definition of a and we have basically a type to finish
and we're going to call the dialog option builder
and we're going to say it has it's a generic
okay and we're going to say that is equal to a function
that returns that value so
let's also see the map all right key expected to find all right and
that's probably because i've misspelled that am all right so now we have an
option builder so we're gonna then use that option builder in our function so
you're you'll see soon how we're going to use it
so i'm going to say that we have a dialog option builder and let's just
call it options builder
okay so we have all those bits and pieces in place now what we need to do
is inside this function actually use the build context to display a dialogue to
the user so before we do that let's grab all the options that the caller
wants us to display so we're going to call it options
is options builder we call that function and now you'll see
options is
it smart enough to understand that yeah it's a map of string dynamic okay it
doesn't understand yet what it is so let's go ahead and say in here in
this function we return a show dialog of t
all right and in here we have two parameters that
we have to pass one is the context the other one is the actual builder
function all right some help from your favorite editor to
complete the builder function which is very simple it just takes to build
context all right and in your builder we are going to return an alert dialogue
this you should already know from before we've worked with alert dialogues and
show dialogue from before so this is nothing revolutionary
so for the title we're going to say we have a text which is equal to
which contains the title string for the content we're going to say also
a text which includes the content
all right and then we're gonna go into our actions
and this is this is the exciting part for me because for the actions what we
need to do you see our actions are defined in here every key inside this
options is the title
which is defined by string of the actions
of our dialogue so we need to start mapping them so we're going to say
options keys
keys and then we map them all right and this let's just call this
a option title
and we're not going to use a shorthand signature in here and we're just going
to do it like this all right so now in here in the option title we're
actually actually gonna return a text button so
let's let's get the value first of this key so i'm just gonna say
um final t value is equal to options
at the option title like that
right and now it's saying that yeah you're not using it that's fine we're
gonna we're gonna fix that soon
and this huge error that we're seeing here is because you see actions it
requires an iterable i believe no it's actually a list of widget but
when you do a map on your keys it's going to return an iterable so to fix
that we're just going to go at the end here and say this is to list all right
all right so let's now fix the rest of the problems i understand i mean this is
quite a lot of errors and you may be a little bit overwhelmed by this but
that's okay we're gonna fix them one at a time so a semi column at the end so to
get rid of that huge er at the end and then what we're going to do in here
where we get the value we're going to create a text button so let's just say
return a text button every
option and what the text button needs as we've
seen before is two parameters unpressed and it also needs the i believe it's
tiled and we're going to say the child is
equal to text of our
option title right
so i mean you may be a little bit confused by all
of this that's okay what we're doing is very simple we have like a list of
titles to display for every button so every button has one title and that
title is inside this map of string and the reason it's inside a map of string
and an optional t is simply because we don't want to have
we don't want to manage two separate lists a list of titles and a list of
values and then we're going to match the titles with the values and map is
already doing that for us furthermore what a map of string with a t does is
ensures that every string or every key in this case of type string is unique so
you can't have two buttons with the same title and different values so
the map is perfect for this case all right and what we're doing in here for
the actions of our alert dialog we're saying that okay
every key inside our map is an option title is a title of a button all right
so we're mapping that what are we mapping it to every one of those titles
of type string is going to be mapped to a text button
whose child is a text of the actual title which is inside this key all right
i understand it could be confusing but please just pause the video have a look
at the code and i'm sure you'll understand it better after we actually
thought about it yourself the values then are going to be
extracted of this type and what we're going to do is we're
going to say let's see final value
and in here if you look at value it's going to be dynamic and what we need to
do is just to make sure that say if value is not null
and we're going to say navigator of
our context it was written already then i'm going to
say pop it with that value otherwise we're just going to pop
off just pop all right so this that is now
you see why we're defining the value as in as an optional because you see some
values some buttons on our dialogs may not
actually have any values just like we have in our
login view if we go back in here this login view is going to have an error
dialog and this error dialog is going to use our generic dialog but this air
dialog is just going to have an ok button it has no value the okay is just
an ok just dismiss the dialog and that's exactly what this is going to do so as
you'll soon see the way we'll implement our new show error dialog is going to
use our generic dialog however it's going to place a little um option in
there that says ok and that ok has a null value all right
perfect a lot of talking a lot of logic but that's fine we sometimes need to do
this okay
wow um we've now written our generic dialogue
what we need to do is we need to start using it and that is inside our error
dialogue that we're going to implement now so
let's go ahead and create an error dialog
so i'm going to bring up my notes and
let's as the caption indicates inside dialogs
let's see where it is inside dialogues we're going to create a new file called
error dialog here
now inside error dialog what we need to do is we need to use our generic dialog
so we need to have an import in here which
we're going to get visual studio code to help us with so
remember error dialog is going to just show an ok button it has no value so
it the short error dialog is going to have the signature exactly as it had
before which is a future void so let's go ahead and do that
and we're going to call it show error dialogue
and the only thing i mean the two things that the shower dialog needs is a build
context and a text so we're saying build context
and we're also going to say a string of text
okay and let's import material to get rid of that error
so that's that and then in here we're actually going to return an instance of
our show err show generic dialogue
and i believe it now should be imported is it not imported automatically in here
it's not yet but somehow it's finding it and i can see we have a show generic
dialogue actually inside in here so this is not the one that
we're actually gonna use so we're gonna use the one with uh
like this and then we're gonna say our air
dialogue avoid so let's import our own uh
show gener um show generic dialogue
so was it a show general dialogue i'm actually curious general dialogue that's
interesting so there's a function called show general dialogue
but that's not what we've created we've called show generic dialects so be
careful a little bit with that because i actually tripped on that right now so
let's go back to our error dialog and say show
generic dialog and it's going to also import
that form you know so that's that's the correct one okay
so put a comma at the end to get formatting also working fine
and now add a comma in here to get the formatting finding there as well
now the title we're going to hard code that
we're going to say an error occurred
like this and the content is just going to be the
text and our options builder now is going to be i remember an options
builder if you go back in here to our generic dialog is a function all
right that returns that so let's go and define an inline function in here and we
say that oops to remove this and we say it's a
function that returns a map and the key in here is just going to be
okay with the value of null all right see how see how generic that
is now so we're actually defining saying that this is a show air dial again it
just doesn't return anything it's just a void all right
and to make it cleaner you could actually specify here that this is a
void all right that's that part so now we've
worked on our error dialogue um and now what we need to do in order to make our
code a little bit less scary with so many errors at the moment that we have
let's go and clean up some of these errors and let's go ahead and use this
show error dialogue everywhere okay so let's go to our views and have a look at
the login view you can see now we have show air dialog
and and now we have our own implementation of uh show air dialog so
let's get help from visual studio code to import our error dialog
and all of a sudden you see all the errors in the login view and disappeared
you can see we're in loginview. so let's save our login view
and we have an error in here from our previous import which was show air
dialog dart so let's remove that as well so
your login view should now look quite clean i'm going to close that and let's
then i'm going to save all of these things that we have in here because we
have so many windows so many tabs open that it's kind of scary so let's then go
inside the register view and clean up this import so let's remove
the old import from utilities show error dialog
and let's go and to these errors that we're getting here
for show air dialing and get visual studio code or your favorite editor or
id to auto import our new function called short error dialogue which
resides inside this utilities dialogues error dialog
okay
now you remember now that we also broke
our notes view
here which at the moment uh let's see
yeah we've broken notes view simply because we're not returning anything in
here because we migrated or moved all the code to the
notes list view so what we need to do now is to go and
basically work on our
show delete dialogue okay so that's not the one that we we need we need to work
on the notes views log out functionality which is here show
log out dialogue you see so we need to create a new logout dialog
as well and this this log out dialog is going to be very similar to how we
created our um error dialog so it's gonna be very similar
okay so let's i'm actually gonna i don't know
if it's worth copying this code i usually don't like copying even if it's
my own code sometimes i do but in this case i think it's actually better that
we write it by hand okay so let's go ahead as the caption
indicates inside dialogues folder create a new file called log out dialog
so in here i'm going to say new file log out dialogue drop down
and in the log out dialog so i'm going to go to my notes as well and log out
that one all right so let's go and say and then we need a function called show
logout dialog all right as we have it here okay so i'm going to just copy that
name so we're going to say it's a future of boolean
and call show logout dialog and the only thing it needs is a build
context okay
we're going to get an error for build content simply because we don't have it
inside our file in here and you see now the only error that
we're getting is saying that the body might complete normally
which means yeah it's not returning any value at the moment and we're going to
fix us so what we need in here we're actually
going to return our show generic dialog and auto import it
a comma at the end and a semicolon just to get the formatting right
the context is there and we're in this case we're actually going to say that
show generic dialogue is going to return a boolean value all right
so the context is there the title we need to specify kind of we're just going
to say log out and for the content we're going to say are you sure you want to
log out the optional remember it's a function
we're going to make an anonymous function in here and returns a map
and for the option of cancel we're going to say false and for the option of
logout we're going to say true all right we're getting a huge error in here
saying that there is a future of boolean you're returning a boolean optional
for a function that is supposed to return a future of bull again remember
on some platforms you're able to dismiss your dialogues without actually
responding to any of the options presented in the dialogue in those
platforms you actually need to guard yourself against that case by returning
a default value so let's go in here and say then
so if we get this value which as you can see is an optional bool then we say
either return that or just return false and that's it we can put a comma at the
end as well just to get the formatting right okay
perfect um now what we need to do is now that we've written our show logout
dialog we have to put it to use so let's go into our notes view
and get help from your favorite editor to
import your new logout dialog in here so that error goes away
okay so we've actually worked on that so what i
want to do is uh
edit my caption a little bit and i'm sorry about and i'm sorry about this
because this caption wasn't completely right so
i need to fix that
that's fine now let's now now that we've worked on the notes list view let's go
and bring notes list view inside notes view all right so you can see here we
have our notes view and but we also have our notes list view
which we have to import in here i'm going to go to my notes and just to
make sure i have everything in place all right so in this case that we have
all notes let's go ahead and say we return an instance of our notes list
view and this is gonna auto import it for me
so like that and for the notes i'm going to say here are all the notes and
upon the user wanting to delete a note i'm
just going to get visual studio code to complete that for me you can see here
and we get the note that the user wants to delete all right
then in here we're going to make this function asynchronous and just a wait on
our node service delete this
node with this id
all right i'm going to save now if you look at your
code in here you can see we have one error here in our notes list view and
let's go ahead and fix that and we can say it says show delete dialog
and we haven't yet actually written the delete dialogue so
what we need to do is need to go and fix that actually so it creates a delete
dialogue as well
so let's go inside our dialogues that we have here
in here utilities dialogs so let's go and right click on it and
create a new file called delete dialog
and delete dialog is going to be very very similar to the log out dialog so
let's just go ahead kind of maybe we could use the log out dialog so copy the
code from log out dialog and bring it into your new file called
delete dialog and just paste it in there and we're going to call this function
show delete dialog
okay and it's going to create a generic
dialogue in here and in here we're going to say delete
and we're just going to say are you sure you want to delete
this item the option builder is going to be cancel
false and then we're going to have an option that just
says yes true all right so now you see how easy it is now that
we have a generic dialog just we're reusing it everywhere okay
so then let's go back to our notes list view and fix this function fix the
calling of this function and get help from visual studio code to import our
delete dialogue and that error also goes away
so now i save my project and all of a sudden you see we have delete icons
appear to our every tile and
we should now be ready to actually put this into test so i'm going to tap on
the hello world item here and now you see it says are you sure you want to
delete delete this item pressing cancel doesn't do anything but if i press on it
and say yes then the hello world note is deleted and our notes view is getting
notified of that information from its stream builder because remember
notes service as we have it here let's go to our
services here uh crud
and node service upon deleting a node let's have a look
at the leaks node function here you see what it does is that if it could delete
a node it actually removes it from its array of nodes and it notifies the
stream controller actually no that's the delete node
oh yeah basically it removes the node and then puts the entire array of nodes
in the node stream controller okay so that's how the notes view is getting
notified of a deletion of an item we can delete another one if you want and
that's it so well done great job for sticking with
me throughout this chapter this was probably one of like the most
challenging chapters in that we had a lot of errors from the beginning
and we had to fix them but one of my goals for for this course is
not for you just to learn how to write flutter application but actually get in
the mindset of a software developer so and every software developer they have
their own preferences i included and one of my preferences when i'm doing
refactoring is like to cut things from the source as i mentioned in the
beginning of this chapter so that's why we got so many errors in the beginning
but you stuck with me and we fixed all those errors and now we came out of this
chapter actually quite victorious so now we have the delete functionality
what we need to do now is just to go and we because we've done a lot of work what
we need to make sure now is to commit and tag our work so that we don't
lose this work so um i'm gonna do some um
reorganization on the windows here so you see things a little bit better
i'm going to increase the size okay and let's see now
if we look at the previous tags we've come to tag 15 from the previous chapter
and now we need to do a tag 16 okay so let's go and look at the status
we have quite a lot of things that we've modified we've deleted the show error
dialogue from before we've also excuse me we've also added a whole new
folder here on under lib utilities dialogues
so let's do get at all and let's look at the status
a lot of things changed okay and what we're going to do is we're
going to commit these and let's just say step
16 okay and push your changes into your
host git repo we're also going to tag as step 16 so
and we're gonna push our tags if you look at your tags right now you
have one two three four five six seven blah blah blah so we have all our tags
up and including step 16. all right so that was for committing and also
tagging our work as it's tradition we're going to talk
about what we what we need to discuss in the next chapter
you can see we have the ability to create new notes and we also have the
ability to delete notes and also something that we didn't test is this
thing that when we create a new note and if we back out of it you see that that
note actually is deleted from the database so that's also working so we
have the ability to delete notes and the ability to create notes but we don't
have the ability to update notes and that's exactly what we're going to talk
about in the next chapter so i'll see you there
hello everyone and welcome to chapter 34 of the slaughter course in the previous
chapters we've been talking quite a bit about how we can create
and notes and how we can delete them so we've been working quite a bit with some
generic dialogues that we've also developed in order to be able to handle
error dialogues and also the log out dialogue for instance and also the
delete dialogue so there's been quite a lot of work done on
that side but we haven't really talked at all about how the user can tap on or
click on their existing notes in order to be able to
update that for instance and update that's a particular node so that's what
we're gonna take care of in um this chapter
so if we now start looking at the code that
we've written you you will see that we've called
the view that actually creates a note um the new node view
however we're not going to go and create a whole
new view that looks exactly the same as this new note view just so that we can
update existing notes so the goal of this chapter is to reuse this view so
that we can just use the exact same view but
when we when the user taps on a note in the note list we're going to pass the
tapped note to this existing view all right so that's what
we're gonna take care of in this chapter let me do a little bit of a shuffling
around here so you'll see the screen better i'm gonna
bring up visual studio code as usual here
i have scrcpy who is taking care of this android screen
and we can then have a look at the first task that we have to do as you can see
in the cache it says we have to rename the new node to your dart to create
update node view alright so let's take care of that i'm going to close all the
tabs in here and let's go and say command p visual
studio code or maybe an android studio is another command that you have to
execute in order in order to bring up the list of files i don't really know
the command in android studio but if you're not comfortable with any of those
you can just go to this new note view right here and we are going to rename it
so let's just do that now so i'm just going
to call as a cache in the case create updates note view okay
create updates notes view like that if the updating i mean if if your editor
is intelligent enough and it has some like um refactoring features built in
then you don't have to do anything special
for for this command to work but um you can
see in here for instance now we've changed this file name to create updates
nodes view but we haven't really changed for instance the class name so if i go
here this thing is still called new node view all right
so let's go in there and perhaps change that as well let me go to my notes
uh let's see create update note view and we're going to go actually and
rename this new note view as well so let's go ahead and do some refactoring
in here so i'm just going to say refactor and let's see do we have any
refactoring features here um we have rename symbol so maybe let's use
that and i'm going to call it create update node view
right let's see if it's successfully going to
be able to rename this for me so i can see it renamed the class for me and it
also renamed the state class which is exactly what i needed so if i now save
this we should have some problems excuse me
but i can see visual studio code was intelligent enough actually to rename
the main dart reference to this route as well
remember when we created this create
or what we call it actually before it was called
um new note view
that note view was a new note view was actually being used inside our routes in
the main function of our of our application inside main.dart now that
we've renamed that to create update note view both the class name the stateful
widget and its state then that new name should be used in
main.dart so if you're using vim or any other
code editor like if you're using sublime supply may not have this refactoring
feature that can actually go and rename where you've used that symbol so you may
need to do that by hand so you may actually get some errors in your
main.dart file but if you get those errors don't worry
about it at least you know what the problem is okay so you can go and fix it
yourself
all right so we've done that and now what we need to do is i'm actually going
to press command s here and command s in here just to make sure everything's
saved and as the caption indicates remember we also have our routes inside
constants so you can see our route is still called
new node route okay so i'm gonna rename this now and i
suggest that you do the same thing too let's just say rename and let's rename
that to as the caching indicates create or update node route okay so create or
update snow throughout just like that and as you can see again visual studio
code helped us quite a lot now it went and updated this as well
you see right
and something also happened in the notes view as well i can see and that's
because you see the where we actually
press the plus button in here to create a new node that was also using the uh
previously uh named
new node route but now it's updated to create or update node routes so all i'm
trying to say in here you need to rename that route so that it becomes create or
update new node route and depending on your editor it may be smart enough to
have some refactoring features if it's like visual studio code then you're good
to go just rename it but if it's not you may have to do that by hand so just go
ahead and rename where you refactor in your code where you're using
that route to use the new name okay
all right so let's have a look at this dilemma now
you see in our
notes view when we create a new note we just say
navigator of context push name all right now the goal here is when we create this
nodes list view we're going to allow the users you see at the moment we have on
delete node but we're also going to have a parameter called untap we're going to
develop that soon but the dilemma here is that when you
then say on tap we need to also go to this view into
this route that we have create or update node route but we have to pass an
argument to that route an argument just as it is for a parameter of a function
or an argument to a function is like data that you pass to that
route and you say hey i'm initializing this route but i'm passing some data to
it so then that route can then in turn reactively sorry that ralph can then
react to that and go and read that argument and say oh was i pass an
argument yes then i'm going to do this was i not pass an argument then i'm
going to do something else in this case if you pass a note to our create or
update note route then it's going to say oh i have an existing node i'm just
going to populate myself and my contents with that note and i'm not going to
create a new node remember at the moment our create update note
view we have this function set up in here
that says create a new node we're gonna fix that soon okay but remember that
at the moment when you go into that view by default it's creating a new node and
we're gonna change that so that we're saying we're going to rename that and
saying like create or get note or something like that soon you'll see um
but in that function then we're going to say
where we passed an argument where we pass an existing note if yes we don't
have to create a new node if no we have to create one okay
so the way arguments work then is if you have a look at our notes view where
we're using push name there is a parameter in here called arguments and
as you can see at the moment it is just an optional object meaning that well it
can be no or no we're not we're not leveraging that at
the moment but we are going to soon so at the call side where you're creating a
where you're creating a route and pushing it to the to the
navigation stack you can pass your argument using that arguments parameter
okay and at the receiving side in this case
are let's see create or update node view here
in here you can read then your argument
let's see let's go to some place that does make sense let's say in here
okay you can read that argument calling now you don't have to type as i'm typing
i'm just demonstrating something to you okay and we can use model uh route
and we say of is context and then you can say settings
dot arguments then that's where you basically get access to your arguments
through your modal route so now you know how to pass arguments and you know also
how to receive them all right so
let's go to the next point um you see
we may need to somewhere also in the future receive an argument inside our
any of our widgets and that argument can be any type that
you specify for instance you can pass an integer from one screen to the other or
you can pass a string or you can pass an array or in our case you can pass a
database node so as you could see in in this code let's
go in here um
what's this optional yes settings and then arguments
you see at the moment this guy is an object so it doesn't really know what it
is but it'd be really good if you could
create a function somehow that allows us just to say for
instance context get object of type t something like that so we
could just say given a build context
we want to extract an argument of any type from it if that argument exists
okay and then we're going to use it in our
code in here and to and we get our build context and then grab our notes out of
it so it's what we're going to do is like create a generic way of extracting
arguments from our build context and that's exactly what we're going to do
now okay so
to do that we're going to create an extension on build context and that
extension is going to be called guest argument and as i've indicated in the um
as i've indicated here in the caption at the bottom of the screen you
can see that we are going to create a new file
under lib utilities generics and a file call gets arguments so you can see we
have utilities at the moment here and that utilities follow me just fold
everything in here so it's not so scary to look at you can see utilities
at the moment has a folder called dialogues under it but
what we want to create is a folder called generics and then a file under
that called get arguments okay so
uh let's go ahead and do that right now so i'm gonna go to uh
utilities where where to go utilities dialogues okay so i'm just gonna right
right click on utilities and say new file and i'm gonna say generics
lyrics and get arguments dot
dart now in here what we need is um
to just start writing our extensions so i'm just going to say extension
and get argument on build context okay
now if i typed build context visual studio
code was smart enough to import material if you're using sublime or any other
text editor it may not be intelligent enough to do that for you may not have
like the extension to work with dart and flutter and
kind of so you may have to import material yourself but remember we also
only need um build context and modal route from
entire material uh packaging here so it would be it would make a lot more sense
if you just say show build context
and modal route
right so we're not going to use more from the material package
than those two
all right so let's go ahead and create this function so we're saying
that we are going to optionally return a value of type t that means any type that
you ask us to and we're going to call this function get
argument okay and get argument itself takes t all
right so in here what we're going to say is going to say modal route is model
route of our build context
or this because you see we we are creating an extension on build
context and this identifier in here refers to the current build context on
which the get argument function is actually invoked so if you're not
familiar with extensions i've talked about them before
and so it i think it was part of also the dart introduction in the beginning
absolute beginning of this course so you may want to go back to that in order to
understand how extensions actually work okay so remember model route in here if
you look at it it can be an optional in here you see so
what we need to do is to guard ourselves against that so we just say if modal
route is not null
and otherwise we're just going to return null we're saying that if we can't get
the model route then we can't extract any argument from it okay so let's get
the let's get all the arguments from our
model route now so we're gonna say args is model route settings
dot arguments okay and then remember args is also now an object as it was
on the call site the call site may skip over passing an argument to us and we in
that case we're not going to get any arguments which means args is going to
be null in here okay so let's just guard ourselves against
that so we say if args is not null and args
is of this given type then we're going to return rx okay uh oops
rx as t so what we're saying in here is that if
we could grab any arguments from um our modal route settings arguments and if
that argument is of the type that you are asking this function to extract then
we're going to give it back to otherwise we're just going to fall through to line
number 12 in here and just return and null all right
now i'm going to save this file okay
that was that part now what we need is let me bring up the
caption so you see what we have to do
so let's now go to our view which we call create actually it's
easy now now that we have a lot of files in our project it's actually easier to
navigate if we just do command p in visual studio code for instance to jump
to specific files so in that file it is now called
create update node view so let's go there
and as the caption indicates our creates note in here let's have a look and see
if we can find that function create new node here you see
so what we need to do is we just need to rename that um
create new notes to ask them captions to get create or get
existing notes so i'm gonna do that i'm gonna say create
or get existing note and again we just do the code smart
enough to rename where i'm actually using that function as well you can see
in here okay so you may otherwise if you're not using
visual code or if you're not using the refactoring features of your favorite
editor you may have to rename that a call site as well
so i don't think i have to mention this again i think i've now mentioned it
three times so just so you know if you're renaming something just make sure
that all the call sites are also updated okay
all right so now that we've done that we actually need to grab the existing nodes
if it is already there okay
so um so let's do that you can see it says in
create or get existing no gets note argument if any all right
so let's then in here say if we if our widgets like the widget that actually
called us created us has passed us an argument of type
database note then we're going to get that okay so let's just call it widget
note is um
we need now a build context because remember our extension was created on
build context however this function at the moment has no build context so let's
go ahead and pass a build context in here
okay so let's then go into the call site and
pass the build context in here call context which is passed to us in the
build function all right so trusting that you've done that
we're now going to go and say context get
and you see now we need our get argument function in here but as i type nothing
appears here and that's because we don't have an import so
i can see if i just type get the argument and ask visual studio code to
see if it can solve that problem for me it's saying that oh there is again
arguments.dart file which has a function do you want me to import it so i'm just
going to say yes please otherwise if you're not doing this you
may have to import your get arguments.dart file by hand all right so
now i'm just saying get arguments and remember get arguments function in
itself has no parameters so how do you call this function okay how do you tell
it to extract a t of like database node well that's very
easy you just put this less than sign and and grade it inside
like that and then you type the type of object that you want to extract so if we
just say data base notes all right
and now that we did that remember get arguments returns an optional object of
that type and in this case our database node is then an optional database node
all right meaning that you either have a node
so that the user has tapped on an existing node and came here or you don't
meaning that a user tapped on the plus button and came here okay
so then we say if the widget node is not null meaning that we are updating
an existing node so that the user has tapped on an existing node and ended up
on the screen then what we're going to do we're going
to save that inside our node private variable here
i think we set it up somewhere around here you see
so we're going to say our node is the widget node
okay and in this case what we also need to do
we need to make sure that the text field inside our on our screen
and i can show you here so if you go here
this text field it should be pre-populated with that existing notes
text and the way we can do that i mean we don't have direct access to our text
field but what we do have is this text controller which we set up in here text
controller okay so let's go and set that text controller's text so i'm just gonna
say text controller the text is equal to widget note
dot text and then we're just going to return the
widget note so the notes that we
could extract okay otherwise uh
what we're doing in here we're saying existing note notes so the logic
is going to stay the same the rest so if we could extract the node from the
passing widget or the color widget then we set that as our node set the text and
then just return the widget note otherwise we continue exactly as we did
before okay so let's see in here what we're also
doing existing note we're just returning in but i can also see that upon doing a
creates note in here we're not setting that note so what we need to do in here
let's just say final new note okay
and and then we store that note we say note is
new note and then we just say return you know so
in here we're also saving our notes okay so that's really good so we actually
working with an existing notes all right
okay so i'm actually not sure how this has
worked before this may have been a bug in the previous um sections in that we
didn't actually store the node in this node private variable
so maybe we had that bug from before i
can't be completely sure about that so i'm just gonna press back in here but if
you had that bug as well if you were like returning just on a weight of node
service create node and you weren't saving that i'm not sure how these
um these functions were actually working
because i personally oh i can see that we were setting it in
here so we may not have to do that anymore so let's then go ahead and i
mean this was quite smart but it wasn't that good idea that the widget's build
function was changing like a core part of this widget so let's
remove that now okay how it was working so that's the reason
it was working but it shouldn't work like that all right
okay let's move to the next section now um
you see if we go back to this part in here if i press the delete
button do you remember this we developed this
in one of the previous chapters of this course we made sure that we have a
callback and that callback was defined let's go in our
notes list view i'm actually going to do it like this notes list view
do you remember this callback it's called delete note callback
it was just a function that returned nothing and accepted the notes and this
way we could tell the notes view that hey
the user wants to delete a note do it delete that now
and that was being called upon the user pressing the yes button remember it's
this view that is actually showing the delete
dialog all right but if you look at that
but if you look at this delete node callback
what is it actually a call backup is a callback of a note all right so it has
nothing really to do with delete it's just called delete node callback all
right can we utilize this also to
tell somehow when the any of these notes is
tapped can we utilize the exact same function to tell the notes list view
sorry to tell the notes view that hey you the user tapped on a note well of
course we could do that because it has no return value and it just
accepts a note so we have a little problem with the naming of this right
now it's just called delete note call back but it shouldn't be all right so
we're going to utilize that both for delete and also for tapping
on an existing node so let me bring up the caption let's rename
that delete node callback to just node callback so i'm going to right click on
it i'm just going to say rename rename symbol and let's just call it
node callback okay and now you can see it's actually renamed it here for me as
well and everything should be working the way
it was before so we don't have to do anything special it's just called node
callback now all right
okay let's move on to the next section now
which is very related so what we need to do now is you see at the moment the
nodes list view it's not handling at all the user tapping on any of these list
tiles and we're going to fix that so i'm just going to go to my notes
and make sure that i have all the information here
so what we need now is just to make sure that the user can tap um
on those uh on the on tap all right so sorry that the user can tap on these
list tiles and then um we're then going to call a function just like the node
callback and tell our owner widget that hey the user tapped on one
of these just do whatever you want so let's go ahead and add a field here and
say on tap sorry note callback and we'll just call it ontap
the constructor is not happy now saying that yeah you have a final field that
you haven't initialized so let's just add that here right after undelete and
i'm just going to make this required parameter and a comma at the end just to
make sure that you get the formatting right as well
we're not using on tap right now and if you've noticed we've also broken the
notes here that's okay we'll get there we'll fix that soon the reason we've
broken note2 is because we're not passing on tap since it's a required
parameter okay we're gonna fix this luckily in order to handle tabs on a
list tile we don't have to work with gesture recognition or anything like
that but what we could do is just to say untapped you see it's already there so
there is a function that has no parameters
and what we need to do in here just to call our own ontap in here and you can
see we have to pass a database node and luckily we already have i believe a note
right here okay so we're just gonna say untap and
note that's it
okay um so we're doing that now now what we need to do is to go back to
our notes view and handle that case you see
so i'm going to go back to our note 2 and and scroll to the part where we're
getting an error and we have on delete um
but we don't have the on tap so i'm going to go to my notes as well all
right now in here right after on delete note
let's go and add this untapped functionality in here
and you can see visuals helping me and saying oh this function actually accepts
a node so if i move my mouse over it it already tells me it's a database node
and remember that's just what the nodes list view is giving us all right
and then here let's make this function an asynchronous function the reason for
that is because we're going to actually grab our
um let me actually see if we have to make
it asynchronous i don't think it needs to be async first let's just not make it
asynchronous i had it as asynchronous in my notes and i thought that we have to
do that but maybe there is a reason behind it i
don't know yet but uh let's just go ahead and not add asynchronous at the
moment so what we need to do in this case is
also do something very similar to what we're doing in here navigator of blah
blah push no not that one sorry this one navigator of context push name create or
update note route so it may actually make sense to copy that code and let's
go to in on tab and paste that i'm going to
put a comma here so it breaks it down for me
and in here what we're going to do is just to say arguments and we're going to
pass the notes there okay
so we're just saying that here's a note and
go to that screen and pass that argument to it then when we go to
the um create update note view
this function gets called create or get existing node
which in turn tries to grab that argument of type
database node from our context using our get argument
generic function which then goes to the modal route of that context and then
grabs that argument so it's like three layers of extraction but that's that's
quite fine now at least you have a generic function to grab your arguments
okay so i'm going to press command s it might be good to do a hot reload
sorry hot restart just because we've done quite a bit of
changing so i'm going to delete these two nodes like that and then i'm gonna
press the plus button let's just in here i'm gonna say my note
number one i'm gonna go back and then i'm gonna
press press and i'm just gonna say my note
number two now i have my note number one and two in
here then i'm now gonna test that to see that we can actually go and edit an
existing note all right so i'm gonna go to my note number one and tap on it and
now i can see i actually went to our notes and it says it still says new
notes and maybe that's okay we could just
leave it like that we could update the text maybe later that's that's fine
but at least i can see the text so i'm now going to change actually this my new
note sorry my note 1 to my note 3 and go back and i can see now i have my note 2
and 3. so this is a really good sign because that means that updating an
existing note is actually working and we're not creating a new note because
otherwise that note would have appeared in this list so i'm going to go to this
new note 3 and then change it to one as well so now you see it gets
updated all right perfect we got updating working and it
was quite a breeze to be honest with you if you ask me so
well done um what we need now is to make sure we
don't lose our code so let's go as we usually do at the end of every chapter
and we're gonna go commit and tag our code okay i'm gonna change the screen
layout and i'm then going to increase the size of the screen so you
see what i'm doing a little bit better let's go to our terminal and if you look
at oops if you look at
um i think it's was it command k yeah let's look at our git log and you see
the last uh commit that we did was step 16 and also your tags the last tag was
also step 16 okay let's go and commit now
as maybe before that let's have a look at
status and a bit has changed modified modified
deleted it thinks that this file was deleted
though it really wasn't um it was just renamed so
um that's unfortunate that it marked it as
deleted that's okay though but a little bit unfortunate there there are ways of
doing that so that git actually understands that you rename the file but
i can see that visual studio code wasn't able to actually mark that as rename and
it also it just marked it basically was marked as deleted
but that's okay we can live with that so let's just say git add all and let's
just say then git commit step 17
all right and then we just say git push so we push
all our changes and let's do a git status to make sure we didn't leave any
files behind and we haven't so in here we're then going to say get
tag step 17 as well and push our tags okay
so that part is now done we've
done our updating of
existing notes and that's fantastic so as is tradition for every chapter in
this course we always talk about what we when we need to work on in the coming
chapter so
we have a little bit of a problem in our source code at the moment and that is
inside our node service so i'm going to get rid of this bottom bar here and go
to node service and you can see in our node service
we're exposing a functionality here called gets all nodes actually i don't
think we're using this get all notes we're just using
all notes stream and um
let's see where that is here all notes stream and that is just reading the
notes stream controllers stream and
and uh that is coming from here you can see
from our notes and that notes is
being populated inside let's see get all nodes remove we have here
so you see we are at the moment reading all notes and we're just exposing them
to the outside world but wait a minute our application has the concept of users
so so if we if we now log out of the
application and log back in with another user then
that new user is going to see my notes because there is nowhere inside this
node service that we have a concept of a user like we're not actually filtering
these things out and exposing only relevant data to the user okay so
we need to fix that it's very serious uh it's not a bug it's actually something
that i've intentionally left until this point because yeah we didn't have to
handle that it was just more fun to work with the ui of the application but we
have to be very conscious about these little things that we haven't
implemented and that's exactly what we're gonna do and fix in the next
chapter so i'll see you there
hello everyone and welcome to chapter 35 of the swati course
in the previous chapter as you saw we started talking about how we can update
an existing node in the node list and we refactored our new node view as it was
called before to become i believe create update node view and this node view is
now able to do two things either create a new node
or update an existing one so we didn't create a whole new view just to be able
to update an existing node so that went really fine
and however as i mentioned
at the end of the previous chapter we have a little bit of a problem with our
node service in that right now node service doesn't really take into
consideration which users logged into the application and hence it cannot
return relevant nodes for that particular user so what the node service
at the moment is doing is just fetching all the nodes from the database and
returning it to the current user this is going to cause an issue in that when we
log in with one user we're going to see all the nodes in the system and when we
log out with a user and log in with a completely new user we're again going to
see all the notes that are stored in the note server so we have to fix that in
this chapter before we get started with that we have
a little bit of a problem with our updating
and this is a bug that's been inside the application for a while since we
basically created our cloud service and we have to fix that so let's have a look
at what this bug actually is before i can
before we go on so i'm going to put scrcpy in here
and i'm going to put visual studio code in here as well
all right so i hope you can see the screen so here right now we have um
maybe i don't have to hope for it i could just bring the screen to be a
little bit bigger so if you look in scr cpy right now we have two my note number
two and that is exactly the box so let's go in here and to the first one and i'm
just gonna say my note number one oops
and go out and everything looks fine right now it's just because we are
updating our local cache as well so things are looking good however if you
do a hot restart of the application and my scr cpy just died so that's okay
i can live with that it's a free software so as your cpy and and i can
see now i've lost actually my debug command of scrcpy as well
so i'm gonna restart the application but what is going to happen now is as
you'll soon see is we have a little bit of a problem with our updates note
functionality so you can see now that i now that i restarted the application all
of a sudden both notes were changed to my notes number one and that's not
that's not correct that's because there's a bug inside the application so
how it's manifest manifesting itself is that when you update a note
locally it looks fine but if you do a hot restart excuse me then it's gonna be
tripping like it is tripping right now and the bug is right here i don't know
if you can notice that excuse me
i don't know if you can notice that but we have this call to
the update function however we are not actually telling and this is also by the
way this is inside node services dart inside the update node function
in here you can see we're issuing a query to sqlite and we're saying update
the nodes table and set the text to this text all right and that's exactly what
sqlite is doing it's going through all the rows inside the note table and
updating their text column with the given text
so what we missed in there is a where argument so we're not telling sqlite
right now which row to update so it's updating all
the rows okay so we need to fix that as a matter of
urgency so let's go in here and say we have now
let's see this is our update
and right after the creation of this
dictionary we're going to say a were and we're going to say the id field of
that column that we want to update or sorry the id field of the row or note
that we want to update is going to be equal to something and where args
are going to be equal to our nodes id so i need you to also write this code
the way i've written it here so now if you say my note number one and i go in
here and i say minor number two then it's going to do the right thing so if
you do a hot restart then you can see that the notes are actually populated
correctly okay i'm not going to do a hot restart just
because i know scr cpy may crash again and i have to restart the whole process
so i don't want to waste your time with
that and that's why i'm not gonna do a hot
restart but this should work okay sorry again
okay um now back to what we were working on um
or back to what the main goal of this chapter is so
let's have a look at how we can fix the problem with our user server with our
node service if you go here not being able to return relevant nodes
except it's returning all the nodes so i believe it's inside node service right
here oh we were there already sorry about that so we have our node service
and you can see at the moment when we say
here notes this is happening inside uh cache all cache notes which is you can
see it's reading all the notes from the database using get all notes putting it
inside putting it sorry you couldn't see that cache notes is reading all the
notes and then putting them inside the local local variable and also populating
the stream controller with that okay but what we need to do is need is that
we need to make sure that the current user is saved somewhere inside this note
service so that note service knows that okay here's the current user whenever i
return all my notes to the call site using this all nodes functionality in
here i need to actually filter out the notes
inside that list to make sure only relevant notes that were created by that
current user are returned from this stream okay
so what we need then is to kind of keep
hold of some sort of a current user in our um
in our service inside this uh node service so let's go ahead and do that
let's go actually define our um database user in here
and we say this is optional and it's equal to user
however we always want to make sure that that user is set before you actually
grab a list of notes okay so this is the
expectation of this note server so the note server says that if you want to be
able to read all the notes the way you're doing it as clean as
you're doing it you also make sure that you've set this current user okay
so if that if that expectation is not met we're going to throw an exception
and we're going to call that exception user should be set before reading all
nodes as the caption indicates we're going to go to our crowd exceptions
which we have from before so let's find that crowd exceptions in the given
folder is sorry yes in the given path that i've mentioned in the bottom of the
screen lib services cross crowd exceptions
and we're going to define a new exception called user should be set
before reading all notes like this
all right so please go ahead and define that as one of the exceptions in your
application as well under crowd exceptions
all right so
what we need now is a way for us to be able to filter
all the given nodes based on the current user
so let's have a look at our all nodes at
the moment here you see what we need is to ensure that this all
nodes can actually filter uh the given nodes inside this stream
and using some sort of filter functionality
so what we have you can see a stream here
let's say stream a stream has a function called where
so what it does is that as you can see it
has um it it allows you to grab the current content of that
stream and then you can pass a test on that so you can say if this object is
equal to this then do that and return this value otherwise return something
else so it's kind of like a filtering mechanism on a string on a stream's
value however our stream includes a list remember let's go back here
in excuse me in here you can see
we return a stream of a list of database nodes
so what we want is a where clause that's two layers deep
we want to be able to filter out and change the contents of
this stream based on the current user and we need to then filter the list
based on the current user's id and only return the database notes that are
relevant for that user so this is a bit of a special case
so for that we need to create our own function
which is a manual like filter function on our
on our stream okay so let's go ahead and do that so what we need to do in here
and is to create a new file as you can see under lib extensions list filter so
i'm going to go ahead and do that let's see if we already have some extensions
so i can see under lib right now we have constants enum services utilities views
but we don't have any extensions so the best way then to do that to create that
filter the dart file is just right click on live and say new file
and then i'm going to say extensions list
filter. okay
so then what we're going to do in here is to create an extension on our
on our stream so let's go ahead and just say extension
filter on stream of t
so the reason i'm doing it like this is
that so we can grab hold of the contents of that stream inside our extension okay
so like if you did something like this
that would still work but in here what we're saying is that we're extending any
stream that has a value of t and in our filter function then we can
access that t as you'll soon see okay so then we're going to say
stream of a list of that object
and we're going to call our function filter
and in our filter function we want to grab another function that does a
testing of the items so let's then say bool
um function that grabs an item of that type
so you can see now we're basically broken down the requirements of our
filtering that is what's supposed to be two levels
deep is now one level leap because our filter function passes t
which is our database node to this where function okay
so this doesn't exist at the moment but we're creating that okay
so in here what we're going to say then is
what we are going to do is we need to map our um
stream and that will you can see it gives us
the values so in here we get the items and in here then we say items where
we pass that word clause in here and we say to list like this
so and i can see in here actually we have a
filter of t but our stream needs to have a list of t so then that's gonna fix the
problem for us so in this case we're actually drilling down two levels deep
inside the list okay so this is the function that we just
created so it allows us to filter a stream of lists of something and then
our where clause is going to get that something and should that something pass
the test then it will be included in the final list so
look i know this is complicated stuff but please pause the video think a
little bit about it we have a stream containing a list of things
now we want to stream of the list of the same thing as long as those things
any individual thing passes a specific test
which is specified using this work loss okay
this is difficult i know it may be some it may be like so difficult for some
users that you'll be like i don't get any of this i don't understand but
you will just need to practice you need to just grab a hold of this code go go
ahead and implement this on some other functionalities like a list of list of
things and see okay if i have a list of lists of things how do i filter out that
thing inside and it will finally click okay
i know it's it's a bit complicated so we've done that now
what we need now um is to set the current user in the node
service as you can see right now we have get or
create user functionality in our node service
so let's go back to our node service and find that function get or create user
and at the moment it just takes an email as the caption indicates we need a
parameter inside this function that also says set as current user so when you get
or create a user which we're at the moment doing i
believe in our notes view so let's go in here
notes notes view in here uh you see get or create a user so this
is like the bare bone this is the actual very important part of our application
where a user either is retrieved from the database the way he or she was or
it's created and it just makes sense to make that user the current user at this
point okay so let's go in our node service
and let's change that functionality so i'm going to bring up my notes as well
and let's add a parameter called set as current user right here going to put a
comma there and let's just say um that this
parameter is a boolean set as current user and we're going to set it to true
by default all right so i need to do the same thing please
so after doing that when we retrieve the user we're going to look at this
parameter we're going to say if set as current user set
as current user then we're going to set our own user to this user that we just
retrieved from the database and also don't forget when you create
this user and you also have to set the current
user if that boolean flag is true so let's just say
set as current user here as well then we're going to say user is created user
so what we did here is we just said if we could retrieve that user from the
database we and this boolean parameter is true then we set our own user to this
user otherwise if we had to create that user
and this parameter is true then we do the same thing we set this current user
to the created user and if you're getting some errors in here saying that
this underscore user cannot be found it's probably because you missed adding
this a database user to your node service
which is something i mentioned just before we moved on to creating that
filter function okay or sorry before we created this exception
all right that part is now done as well um
now what we need to do is to do the actual
filtering and and that is something that we need to do is uh you can see as a
cache index change all nodes stream to filter for the current user
and that's something we need to do in the all nodes
function or sorry the getter so right here
what we're going to say is i'm actually i think i'm going to change them
yeah just let's leave it like this so i'm just going to say no stream
controller and dot
stream and right here we can use our filter function you see now visual
studio code is like confused like oh there is no filter function on a stream
but remember we actually added that ourselves so i'm going to get help from
visual studio code and say command dot on mac or control dot on linux and
windows and visual studio code and then it's gonna understand oh there is a
filter function that you've defined on stream do you want me to import that and
i'm gonna say yes please so now we have the
filter remember filter then gets a note right and if i move my mouse over it now
you can see that says oh you have a database note however our stream
actually contains a list of database nodes and all of a sudden our filter
gets one note at a time so this is the beauty of creating your own extensions
so that you can drill down inside existing objects and grab what you need
inside your application all right so in here what we need is to create a
function then you remember this function has to return a boolean we haven't
returned anything from here yet that's why we're getting an error
so at the end of this function we need to return a volume so let's just say
final current user is this user and if this current user
is not null which is like the condition that we actually expect then we're going
to do some code otherwise we need to throw our exception
user should be said before okay so this is
our expectation from the caller if you're reading all notes from this
interface you need to make sure that the current user was set when you call this
function so this needs to be true okay sorry this yeah you may not have seen
the code but you could also argue that oh wait a
minute if this is like the expectation of this interface that the current user
should always be said before you read all notes
then why don't you make that the default why
don't you just do that and remove this function and always set the user as a
default well the reason behind that is
the current user has to be sent only when you're working with all nodes now
this node service should be able to work like to update existing nodes or remove
existing nodes it in those functionalities should still
work if the current user is not set right because those functionalities are
pure cross functions that say update a node with this id get a user with this
id delete a node with this id etc etc they are not dependent on a current user
however all nodes is dependent on the current user and it just makes sense to
have this functionality in here that says set as current user that is
defaulted to true so if you're using all nodes then it throws an exception if the
current user is not set okay so that's my reasoning for having this as a
parameter and not making it the default um
behavior of this class all right so if current user was not
null that's like the happy path so then we say we return this note
it's not as long as its um user id is the same as
the current user id so we say note
a user id should be equal to current user
dot id okay and remember we're not returning a note we're returning a
boolean remember our filter function it has a where statement that has to return
a boolean so we're not returning any nodes in here we're just checking is
this node's use ready the same as that then do this okay
so that should now be good to go so what we
could do i know this may actually and break things now because i have some
problems with scr cpy but you have to excuse me for that it's it's nothing
that i have control over but since we've changed quite a lot of code uh i'm gonna
now close all these screens at these tabs and i'm going to do a hot reload
but this most probably is going to crash the scr cpy
oh it didn't great thank god for that so we have our notes now how do we put
this into test what we need to do is to log out and log
in so i'm going to go to console firebase
and let's go to our application which is my notes flutter project
we have two authenticated users these two emails at the moment so right
now i'm logged in with one of them i don't really know which one so i'm going
to log out here so i'm then going to log in with
pixeltab gmail.com foobarbas log in
and i can see those email those um notes were under pixel tab so then i'm
going to log out again and i'm going to log in with the other user
like this toolbarbad and i'm going to then press
the login button and i haven't yet verified my email so i will have to do
that so let me just see if i can take care of that right now
i'm going to then bring my email and go to
and see if i can find this um verification email and i can't so i'm
just gonna send send email verification and it's gonna send a new email
verification to me all right i got the email verification
and it looks like this so i'm just gonna click on that and i
can see now it says your email has been verified okay
so let me go to restart then and now that
i've verified my email i'm going to try to log in with a user
as oops this is register i want to go to
login so
here foo barbats
and then log in and now i can see for my user i'm not
seeing any notes but just to make sure i'm just going to create a new user and
say this no sorry create a new node i'm going to say this node was created
for van dot or just put my email in here like this
okay i'm going to go back and i can see that
the note is displayed here then what i'm going to do is just to
log out of this user and log in with the other user
just to make sure that that oh that was created by the other user is
not displayed to this user okay
and now we can log in and i can only see notes that were for this user so
congratulations that was a lot of work that we did and that we did and uh the
application seems to be working the way we've designed it so
that's great job what we need to do now is just ensure
that we we won't lose our code as is a tradition and so we need to commit our
code and also tag our code okay so i'm gonna do some uh
shuffling around here on the screens and i'm gonna increase the size of visual
studio code so you see it better let's do git status and see what the
status is we've modified two files and we've also added a whole new folder so
i'm just gonna say git add all and if you look at our logs the previous
step was step 17 now we have to commit our work and tag
it as step 18 and if you look at our are your tags as well you should have step
17 here let's say git commit and i'm going to
say step 18. here i'm gonna push these changes to
remotes which in my case is github you may be using bitbucket or some other
remote and less than tag as step 18 as well
here and put your tags
alright so that part is done now we have tagged and committed or code so if you
say git status you should have nothing handling here to be committed all right
wow fantastic so again as tradition is we always talk
about what we need to mention in the next chapter what we're going to go
through in the next chapter at the end of every chapter so
up until this point we've been using our notes crot service and
that's been working really good everything's been saved on the on the
device however if you really think about it
you've now learned how to work with crowd and that was my that was like one
of my intentions at the beginning of this course i wanted to teach you about
crud because it's one of the absolute most important things that any back-end
developer or front-end developer such as flutter
developer has to know about so i hope that you've learned that now
however we have a big problem here and that is all our notes are saved locally
in a sql like database and should anything go wrong for instance if
if the users something happens to the user's telephone all that data is going
to disappear so the user's notes may disappear and
you may think well what's so wrong about that well if
you're like me i use my notes like my the default notes
application in macintosh and also on linux quite a lot so i store very very
important information sometimes in my notes and you'd be surprised that the
outline for this course i actually managed it all i managed all of that
inside the notes application on my macintosh so i wrote the entire outline
took many many hours and i would have been devastated
if those notes disappeared for some reason or if my kids got a hold of my
telephone and just removed the notes and there was no reason and then there was
no way for me to grab those notes back again so
what we need to do now is just ensure that we can store these nodes in some
sort of a back end so that it's sitting in the
cloud so we don't have to manage them locally and that's what we're going to
use firebase for and we're going to start talking more and more about
firebase storage from the beginning of next chapter so i hope
you enjoyed this chapter and grab your refreshments coffee or tea or whatever
you want some chocolates and i'll see you in the next chapter
hello and welcome to chapter 36 of this flutter course in previous chapters
we've been working with our quad service quite a lot and also we've been working
with firebase authentication so far we've stored the user generated
notes inside the crotch store which we're backing with a sqlite database and
we've also made that cloud service kind of um
aware of the currently logged in user so when
a user logs in he or she can only see their own notes and when that user logs
out and another user logs and then the previously created notes in the
database aren't exposed to the new user so we've taken care of all those but we
still have our notes only stored in a local storage
and from this chapter on we're going to be working with actually moving away
from storing the user data in a local database
and instead going towards storing that inside firebase
now when i was designing this course i was
thinking about how i can introduce more and more concepts to to become a better
software developer and a flutter developer and one of those absolutely
crucial things was crud create read update and delete and um though firebase
is a good way of doing that but firebase removes quite a lot of the logic that
you otherwise need to understand to become a better developer so firebase
has abstracted away the concept of crowd quite a lot and that you work with data
in the cloud and you don't really know how that is being populated and where
that is being populated so when i started designing the course i
thought maybe okay we could have a look at storing data locally first to get a
good grip of crud and then after that we now we understand
how crop works and how those operations are performed at a low level on a
database level then we can move away from it and go to a more abstract layer
so this was a choice that i met early on when designing this course and it is
definitely not like wasted time you now know how to work with sql light in your
applications and you will probably be using sqlite more and more as you go on
in your flutter development um career so
i am i hope that you understand that we are
we still have good use of uh sqlite and we've understood that but now it's time
that we move away from our local storage and move to using um firebase instead
so i want to bring up the caption for the next section of this chapter and
that's uh that we're going to talk about cloud firestore so if i bring up my
notes and go to that url that i provided right right there for you
and bring it up here and you can see here in in here it says
firestore is a flexible scalable a nosql cloud database to store and sync data
um the way the way it works i mean you can
go actually to this link that i've provided for you here and it tells you
about how you can actually add cloud firestore to your application but i
believe we've already done that so if i bring our um
application also to the screen increase the size and we go to our pop
special and we'll look at our dependencies we're
at the moment using firebase core firebase auth and um in here also tells
you you have to use cloud firestore so let's go in here and we can see we've
already dragged in cloud firestore from one of the absolute absolute earliest
chapters in this course we've already
added this dependency to our application so you don't have to do this but if you
don't have cloud firestore added to your application you may need to do that now
by following the instructions in this link and if you've if you don't have it
it's probably because you've missed one of the early chapters in this um
course so
we're going to be using the cloud firestore in order to store user
generated data and in this case our nodes
now you may be familiar with sql and nosql
but what i mean what
i can explain cloud fire stories is that you will have um
two concepts that you need to understand um which are called um collections and
the other ones are documents so whereas in traditional sql storage you
will have hard dependencies and every uh table for instance when we design our
sqlite database we actually have to design our tables with specific
layouts inside the table so we have different fields we have
foreign keys etc so that's like a typical sql relation relational database
but when you go to node sql for instance firestore then things are more document
based so for those of you who are doing backend development you already know
about that for instance so um
if you're using sequel light then things aren't document based as you would think
um but when we go to firestore then you
will have like a lot more looser data definition for your tables and for your
documents basically so one document inside the same collection can contain
two fields and the next document can contain three fields so
that's a lot more open the way it is created with firestar
so for the entirety of this course from this point on we're going to be
dependent on firestore in order to use it to store user generated content which
are notes in our case so let's now talk a little bit about
production versus test mode um firebase as use firestore as you'll soon see it
has um different ways
of allowing you as a developer to interact with your database so
and there is a thing called a test mode and another caller production mode and
in test mode and what it means is that as you're developing your application
which we are for instance at the moment then you may need to for instance open
up your database um so that you can actually interact
with it with your from your application without even authenticating a user for
instance so even if a user is not authenticated you can actually issue
some commands toward firestore in order to read data delete data
and and change data so that's that's as you're developing
your application while you're still working with your authentication but
remember we've already nailed down the authentication so you cannot actually
end up in the notes view or the notes list view which is embedded
inside notes view if you forgot about that
you cannot end up in there if you haven't authenticated and if you haven't
verified your email address so we know that in our case we don't actually
really need to use the test mode of our database with firestore we're kind of
gonna immediately switch to production mode and what production mode is is for
instance when you develop your firestore database as you'll soon see in this
chapter as well um
you will be able to add some more rules to the database
so that unauthenticated access to the database
is going to be denied and this is the kind of like model that we're going to
be using in the rest of the this course and also almost at the end of this
course we're also going to add some more rules to
our firebase uh sorry firestore database so that we make
it even more explicit who has access to what
just know that there is a test mode and a production mode test mode is a bit
looser in terms of um in terms of security but production mode
is a little bit tighter in that case that it it just tries to
make sure that on authenticated access to
uh for instance a document so the user doesn't have access to are going to be
rejected
all right we've i've just noticed that i just
mentioned a few things about rules and you may be wondering about what these
rules actually are and what they actually mean
so i've prepared the link here so i'm gonna see if i can actually open it on
my computer as well so i can bring it to the screen
here it is okay so these are the rules that i was
talking about so you see if you're for instance a back-end
developer like i am you will also be very familiar with deploying your
application so if you're for instance django developer or node.js with express
or whatever or flask developer then you are probably used to
deploying your application to some sort of a cloud
service and then you will also be
responsible for specifying how users can interact with your backend and what
rules are applied on what cases uh firebase since it is not like this
traditional backend that you have to deploy yourself since it is a product
that's already there and it's deployed it needs your help in order to
understand its security rules so as you can see this is a typical firebase
firestore configuration of a back-end and you can see in here it says the
service is the firestore service and match these documents at these paths and
also only allow read and write if the user is
authenticated so if you're a django developer you already know about like
requests you also get that you're in django so a request user will contain
the currently logged in an authenticated user there so that this is very similar
to that and i'm sorry if i'm talking a little
bit about back-end development that's just because i'm trying to like make
this connection for those of you who are back-end developers and trying to learn
about firebase firestore if you're not a back-end developer just
know that these security rules are there to help
you
they're there to help you secure your database because you see
the way we've actually generated our application let's go to the source code
and have a look at it a little bit and when we set up our uh firebase with
the firebase cli and firestore cli there were some files that were generated for
us automatically and they were inside this firebase option so
i'm going to open that for us here and you can see some information in here
as you can see for android application there is an api key app id messaging
sender id project id and storage bucket if anybody gets hold of this information
as you now are going to get hold of this information by watching this course
you will actually be able to replicate this firebase options. in your own
application with my api key app id and sender id and interact with the database
that i'm in control of even though you personally don't have access to that
database because that database is stored under my
profile in
firebase console so using this api key and app id you can
interact with the database and it is only the security information it's only
the um authentication information or the
authentication rules that i specify in my firebase
config that will then decide who has access to what
so don't worry also about this i'm going to delete this firebase project actually
by the time this course is released so i'm completely happy with this
information being public and shown to you just so you see what i actually mean
so just know that with various roles that
we can define on our firebase firestore project we can specify who has access to
what and based on what rules for instance if the user is authenticated or
if that user id is actually present in that document's id field for instance so
something like that
okay um now what we're gonna do is actually
start creating a um firestore database for our project so
uh what i'm gonna do in here is i'm going to bring up safari and i'm gonna
go to console firebase.com so i suggest that you do the same thing
change the screen layout a little bit here
so you see my screen better excuse me
and then i'm gonna go to our minus flower project so i suggest that you do
the same thing for your application all right
so when we end up here then on the left hand side you'll see something called
firestore database and i want you to click there and just ensure that you've
selected the correct application in here as well you may have quite a few just
like i do then what we'll need to do in here and
it's just to say create database okay and as you can see this is now the
screen that may look a little bit scary but it's completely fine
and you can see there are two different modes specified here as we talked about
production mode and then the other one is test mode
in production mode the rules by excuse me the rules by default are quite
um bad as you can see in here it says any document inside the database is
unaccessible so or inaccessible inaccessible
it says don't allow read or write because the condition is just false
so and you can see it says all third party reads and rights will be denied
but this is really not the um
this is not how we are going to set up our
firestore database we as i mentioned before we are going to tighten this up
quite a lot in in the future but not just right now so i need you go into
start in test mode and you'll get this absolutely beautiful um
message saying in um the default security rules for test mode allows
anyone with your database reference to view and remember database reference i
mentioned that that's inside this firebase options so that's the reference
that we're talking about okay so it may sound a little bit abstract but it's
really not that difficult to understand so
and it says edit and delete all your database from
all the data in your database for the next 30 days so okay
and you can see the rule that has been set up in here says allow read write if
request time is less than blah blah blah so it's opening up your database
basically for 30 days it's actually quite intelligent pretty nice okay so i
need you to do that and remember we're gonna tighten this up soon okay
and then you can see in here it says allow basically set up a location for
where your data is going to be stored now there may be some sort of like um
conflict of interest between like the legal portions of your
business and also where you want to store your data and where you actually
feel comfortable doing that but and gdpr definitely makes this even more
complicated if you're living in europe so
i mean even if you're living abroad gdpr makes things complicated some websites
that are hosted in the us are still not accessible by users in the eu
and this makes things a little bit complicated i'm i'm basically
in sweden right now so i i prefer to use
maybe a location that is um
has something to do with europe and uh i can see europe west while sweden is
kind of like in the middle so i'm just going to use europe west right now but
again this isn't so so significant right now it could have
some speed implications for application depending on where the server actually
is so it's really good that firebase is giving you the option to choose the
location of your firestore database so you may want to read more about this
and you can press learn more in order to read more about this but i'm just going
to pick europe west just because i believe it it could make more sense for
me since i am located in sweden so
choose a location that makes sense for you and then press the enable button
wow that is a an absolutely horrific looking loading screen
what that is i mean it's not even centered so that's okay firebase
remember we're using firebase as a free service so i just want to make sure that
everybody understands i'm very very thankful for having firebase because
it's made life a lot easier for me even though i can create my own backends
but i sometimes still prefer to use firebase so
um just because it's so it's so easy to use so uh thank you so
much any anybody who's working on firebase and providing us with free
services um so
so let's have a look in here um about in our rules so let me increase the size of
the screen like this and perhaps also
increase it like this so you see it better let me see if i can
perhaps close the section to the left a little
bit and i probably could actually have done that
so i'm going to go back in here and press this button to close that section
all right so what we need to do now is to as the caption indicates we're going
to change the the security rules in our database
and i change it so that
we allow read and write if the user is authenticated
um so we make sure you as you can see it says request off is not null so let's go
ahead and change that so i'm gonna remove everything after request
dot like this and you can see it gives you access to off path resource time
method so i'm just going to say off is not null
okay so you can actually bring it to the same
line as well if you want to so after you've done that you can say
allow read write if request auth is not all and that literally just means that
people who are authenticated with our application and they have
and they have a valid firebase user when they interact with the database are
allowed to read and write read from and write to the database
however remember this is database wide at the moment it
says any document and we still haven't talked about documents so much but i'll
tell you soon about that but any just imagine anything in your database can be
read from and written to if the user is logged in and that's not so secure
because that literally means that i as user one
and you as user two have access to each other's documents okay even if the
application itself is like segregating these two documents saying that oh
you're user one i'm gonna just give you user ones documents but internally as a
firebase user given our current security um
rules you will have access to my documents
even if the application's limiting your access just remember that okay
so after you've done that i need you to
please press the publish button so as you can see it says publish
changes can take up to a minute to take effect and that's all right because
we're going to actually take more than a minute before we jump into using these
new rules in our application so okay now
let's talk about collections here um
and i've prepared a doc and a link there so let me see if i can find that
link here as well so as you can see in here there is a
good documentation that will talk a little bit about collections and
documents and you could go through this um but i'm not gonna do that right now
but just so you know here's the link at the bottom of the screen if you want to
do that i'm going to talk about collections
personally so you will understand it in my words so
at this point what we need is just to go to our firebase database
okay and what you'll see is a screen that kind of looks like this so it has
your project name in here and then there is a button called start collection okay
just imagine collection as its name indicates is a group of related objects
objects could be you could interpret them as tables as you traditionally have
in your relational databases such as sqlite um
so a collection just imagine for instance
if we say what does our application do our application stores nodes for
all its users so user a has nodes user b has nodes but user c may not have nodes
so the only thing our application is storing in
in database right now is notes so that could be its own collection okay so we
just create a collection called notes and in that collection we're gonna store
all our notes okay so every user is going to have their own
notes that's how we are going to do it in this
course however you as a developer may just
think i'm going to do it differently what i'm
going to do is i'm going to create a new collection of notes for every user so
user a is going to have a collection called user a notes
user b is going to have user b notes or you may just
assign create a collection with every user id so you remember we get a user
identifier from firebase you may decide to you create a collection for every
user based on their user id okay that's fine but if you're following along with
this course i strongly suggest actually do it the way i'm doing especially if
you if you if it's the first time you're doing this if it's if you've done this
before you may just be comfortable with creating
another type of collection then be my guest please go ahead but it might then
be difficult for you later on to follow along with the course
okay so those are collections
so let's go ahead and um tap the start collection button in here
um as you can see in here it says okay this collection is being created in the
root path and just give me an id and here's a collection set of documents
that contain data and in here it's storing a collection of
users but remember we don't have to actually
store users in our database firebase is already taking care of this i actually
believe this is a bad example that they provided to ask people to say example
collection of users because this kind of gives id idea to developers oh now i
have to store my users here but those users are already stored at the firebase
level okay so let's go and go ahead in here and
just say we're storing nodes okay and we're just gonna say next
and you can see in here now we're getting something called a document
parent path notes and then it says a document id a
collection must contain at least one document cloud firestore's unit of
storage documents store your data as fields auto generate a document or the
id or customize one if needed okay so
that that brings us to what documents are
um a document
you could look at it as if you're if you know about uh
sql from before if you followed along with what being and what we've been
creating like when we looked at db browser for sql lite
then we had these tables like user and notes
these uh these are like the schemas of a document
so as you can see here and here says every note
is created this way it has an id it has a user id it has a text is synced with
cloud remember all those fields and it has that's the schema
in far in the firestore world those are documents so that entire notes
schema is one document and every field in it then it can have a data type so
those fields you may know them as columns
from before when we created our own tables okay so
if we go back into db browser you may not have this db browser for sql
light open and that's completely fine we're not gonna actually work with it
right now you may have you may even have like is toss that database in the trash
and that's completely fine i just want to show you this um
that when we created this node table or the node documents then we had different
fields remember id user id text and those were the exact same things in here
okay so if i if i go ahead and create a new
console firebase and have a look at for instance my
other uh firebase projects i can see i have a notes app and you can here see
that um the way i had designed this uh in the beginning of this course is i had
a collection and then every collection had documents in it that had text and
then user id okay so that's what we're gonna do in here we're just gonna say a
field of text and it's typed string and it has no
value okay and then we're gonna add a new field in here and just call it use
righty okay and then in here it has no value
either and then a document id that we're just gonna auto generate okay so we just
pretty much just created a new note okay with a random document id and it has a
field of text and another field called user id
great then i need you to press the save button and now you'll see here we have
our notes collection and inside there we have a document that has these two
fields okay so what you could do also is to delete
either a collection or delete a a document so i'm just going to say delete
document and start delete and as you can see now we have an empty collection
called nodes i still find this a little bit peculiar
that when we create a collection firebase
forces us to create a document inside it like if i go and say start collection
and then press the next button in here i can't actually save my empty collection
and it says every let's see here a collection must contain
at least one document so
i'm not sure if that's actually true because you can see now we have a
collection with no document so i'm not sure why that was created why
that uh rule was set when you create a new
collection but just know that it's not completely true so you can have a
collection with no documents all right
so now let's talk a little about streams of data if you remember from our
application in if we go to our i think it's called uh
node service here
you remember that we have this stream of database nodes as a stream of list of
database nodes and we call it all nodes in our application up to this point
we've had to manage these streams manually in that we have to like go
create a stream controller do this whole dance of um
unlisten populate the stream controller with the nodes
you'd be really really happy perhaps to hear that when we go to firebase and
firestore we don't have to do any of this because firestore
already has all of this built in in that when you for instance read all the
documents inside this notes collection that will actually be a stream of those
uh data points for you so
no more stream controller and no more streams
that you have to manage manually okay those will be exposed to your
application using firestore
so so as you saw and when i created this
collection to begin with i created it with
a note document that had a text and it had a user id field so
our goal in this chapter and going forward is to make sure that every node
has a text and it is actually linked to a firebase user using that user's user
id okay so
if we go to our application to our auth service so let's
go to off and then auth service in here and remember we're using firebase auth
provider so let's go in there and you can see that
when we say create user with email and password for instance then this function
returned something called user credential to us and user credential
actually has quite a few properties you can see it has a credential and it has a
user inside it of type user so if you go into that user you can see it has
different properties like display name email email verified metadata phone
number etc but this user also has something called a user's unique id
which we actually need in order to store notes into our collect notes collection
so and this is what i mean every document
that we create is for instance going to be node some
random id or something which we haven't decided yet and one of the fields let me
actually see if i can resize uh this safari window so you see it better so
it's going to have a text and the text is going to be generated by the user but
it's going to also have a field called user id okay so in this user id field we
actually need to store that user's gener
firebase generated id in there okay and
now going back to what we are doing with that user do you
remember we're not actually um exposing the firebase user to our application and
that's a great level of abstraction however we have a little bit of a
problem in that right now our user has email and is email verified it doesn't
actually have a unique id so our application is not going to be able to
associate new notes with an auth user
it's not going to be able to associate a new note with a user id okay
so we need to fix that so i'm just going to go to my notes a little bit in here
and what we need is to update our auth user as you can see in
here so in auth user.dart file as i've opened in
here and what we need is to add a new field
which is a required field and we need to make that
the id of that user okay
so let's go ahead and do that now so i'm just going to go ahead and say final
string and id so this field is not optional
here you see every user that comes into our application should have an id and
that's like the expectation that we have on our off users okay so i need you to
go ahead and add that please here of user class as well
let's then go in here and i'm going to add this um to um
the required fields i can see visual studio code wasn't able to actually meet
this required parameter i'm going to help visual studio code and
do that i'm just going to say required this id and i need you to do the same
thing please so now we have a problem in here in that
our auth user in here doesn't have an id where we created from firebase user
let's go and remedy that let's just say the id in here is the user uid remember
this uh parameter that i uh talked to you about okay
so that is now created and let me actually go to scrcpy i can see that
visual studio code has a little bit of problem hot reloading right now so
that's because probably the application wasn't in the foreground so that's fixed
now talking about scr cpy it's perhaps a
good idea for me to bring in crcpy here just to make sure that we're not
bringing and breaking anything okay so
so that's one change that we have to make to our auto user the other change
that we have to make is to make sure that the email parameter of our user is
not optional you see the way we are creating at the
moment are um
our application is that we've created the login process of a use email and
password authentication so we don't have like facebook authentication or google
authentication we only have username and password
sorry email and password so given that condition we can be sure that
every authenticated user in our application actually has an email
address okay so
let's go ahead and just say that email is not an optional field anymore and in
here we're going to explicitly unwrap that email all right so that's another
change that we made to our application so now that we've done that you can see
flutter is not so happy with those changes saying that well yeah you broke
something and it's our tests that have been broken
so as you can see uh we need to make sure that id is actually included in our
tests as well and since we're not actually creating a
specific test for that user id we can just add a random id in here
let's just say my id okay and i'm going to bring that and
bring it down here as well so we have an id field in both cases of auth user
inside our tests
okay now we have another problem as you can see
in the captions in our create update note view
we are unwrapping the user's email and that's what this little orange views um
folder is it's not red meaning that
well yeah it's not an error but it's a warning so let's go to this create
update note view and have a look at this uh
field in here as you can see we're in inside the get a create or get existing
note and we are unwrapping this email but
right now the warning is saying what is it saying the uh uh
asterisk will have no effect because the receiver can't be not try removing the
asterisk operator and i need you to do that please
we have another problem also we have another warning inside the notes of you
and i believe we're doing something similar in the notes view so let's see
if you can find a warning [Music]
where is the warning
i actually don't oh here we have the user email in here as well so i'm just
going to remove the asterisk after that so i need you to do the same thing
please
okay now we're gonna get to the juicy parts
of the uh cloud storage integration so i'm clean i'm basically removing all the
file all the dart um tabs from here i'm actually not deleting the files i'm
removing like that tab so it's a clean slate
then what we need is to um create
all our cloud storage exceptions you see if you remember from when we worked with
our quad service which is a node service then we also had a file under the croth
folder called crowd exceptions and in here we define all the different things
that could go wrong when the user is working with our node service now that
we're moving away from crud we need to have our new exceptions defined
somewhere and and
as you can see in the cache just like we had the crowd exceptions we're also
going to have some exceptions thrown by our new fire
firestore service which we haven't developed yet but we need to define
those exceptions at least okay so
what we need now is to go and create that file so i need you to please create
a file under lib services cloud and then create that file as cloud
storage exception so i'm going to do that as well so let's
see i'm going to fold all the folders in here
so we have lib services and then cloud you can see we don't have cloud at the
moment so we do have services and we have off in there and crowd so i'm gonna
right click on services and say new file and then in here i'm just gonna say
cloud and then slash cloud storage
exceptions.dart okay
so after the creation of that file
i'm going to remove the project explorer there as well what we need then is to
define a super class for all our cl cloud
exceptions if you remember from the crowd
exceptions that we created in here all those exceptions were actually of
type exception and that's one way of doing that however
if you want to group your exceptions under one
super exception
and you could then handle them quite smoothly or better
actually i would say in
at the call site and so that basically is going to use inheritance and then you
and we are going to create a new exception as you can see
here called cloud storage exception and all our cloud exceptions are going to be
of that type so makes grouping and catching these exceptions in the future
a lot easier okay so let's go ahead and
create our first exception it is called i can see it's called cloud storage
exception so let's go ahead and say clouds and
class cloud storage exception and implements exception
okay and we're also going to create a
constant constructor for it so it makes creating instance of this a lot easier
and you could also basically say that this is um an
immutable class meaning that this class and all its subclasses need to be
immutable you could do that all right that's fine as well but usually
exceptions aren't marked with this it's usually data classes that are marked
with immutable so i'm not gonna do that right now
okay that thing is done um
now so that's the parent exception we should try not to throw that exception
as it is we have to throw subclass subclasses of that exception okay
now the first exception that we're going to
define is could not create node exception i believe it's called yes and
we're going to throw this in our to be written a class soon uh upon you
trying to create a new note if firebase firestore is not able to actually create
that note then we're gonna throw this error okay
so i'm gonna then define that exception and you will need to type this then um i
just brought it from my notes
now also in this screen where we have all the notes displayed for a given user
we may also not be able to retrieve all the notes for that user for instance if
there is a network connection issue or whatever whatever other issues that may
arise so we need to have an exception for that
as well and that exception is called could not get all nodes exception okay
so let's define that as well and it's written just like could not get
all notes exceptions exception
the next exception that we have to define is called a could not update
nodes so we have create node exception get node exception and now we're on the
u part of crot so you see the
create part is a c in crud gets is r and now we're looking at you okay
and that is uh could not update node exception so
so we could say this is um
you in crud and the get
is r in crop and create a c in crud okay and so we
have c r u and then we have to define d
which is for delete infrared and that's exactly what we're going to
do now so let's go define could not delete node exception all right so
let's then say be in crop okay so now we have
um three four uh exceptions defined and all of those exceptions are uh
inheriting from cloud storage exception
okay um now that we've talked about the
exceptions we also have to talk about the actual cloud storage service you see
we have our quad service at the moment which we've been working quite a lot
with and we're very proud of it actually it's a lot of code in my implementation
at least in here we have about 360 lines of code
i mean it's not all code there there's also spaces there's like
i think there are some annotations like immutable etc but there's quite a lot of
code okay and there's a print statement in here which i actually have to remove
okay so
there's quite a lot of code and this is working with sql lite but we also need a
service that works with firebase firestore
so we need to create that service soon so just know that we are going to have
crud in here which is going to talk with sqlite
but we're moving actually away from it so
let's then fix that um
so let's go in here and have a look at our constants
and if you look at our node servicing here
and we have our constants in here we have routes and at
the end of node service we have some constants defined right in this class
or right in this dart file and some people may like this but i
personally prefer to have my constants defined in separate files even though
these constants are very related only to this file but just
making them putting them in separate places just makes it easier to look at
because these constants at the moment like hidden at the bottom very bottom of
this file so let's go ahead and define our
constants so let's have a look at the path it's going to be in services cloud
and then cloud storage constants on the services now we have cloud
and under cloud we have cloud storage exceptions i think exceptions yep now we
have to define cloud storage constants so new file cloud storage
constants dart and
i'm going to go to my notes [Music]
constants all right now if you remember from our note series
we define like the tables and excuse me
and we defined the tables the columns and and even the format of creating new
tables we don't really need these all we need are these two fields as you
remember the text and also we need a field for user
id like this
so let's define these let's just say owner user id so let's go in here and
say const increase the size owner user
id is just user id like this and then we're gonna say const text field name
excuse me so i need you to define these two fields as well for your application
okay so let's go back to the original font
size in there so
now that we've defined that if you remember from our note service we had
these beautiful classes in here a call called a database node and a database
user now given that we're moving away from
storing things and notes inside the sqlite
database and we're moving to towards a firestore um
databases we actually don't need a database user
anymore but we do need some sort of a class that
represents these documents that we're going to create in here okay and
what we are going to call that is called a cloud node
so let's go ahead you see here is called a database node so then you kind of know
that it is a local database maybe you could rename this local database node if
you want to but i'm not going to do that simply because we're moving away from
this so what's the point of refactoring it so
i'm going to close node service so then let's go ahead and create a new file
called cloud note dart under services lib services cloud
and i'm going to call it cloud underscore node.dark
in here now what we need to do is actually implement cloud nodes
excuse me so
what a cloud node actually is going to contain there are three properties that
the cloud node has to contain and they're namely the
actual identifier of that node and i apologize i actually have to put myself
into do not disturb so so
there are three things a cloud node has to contain
one is the actual like primary key of that note in our database every document
that is generated by firebase is going to have a unique id if you're
coming from like backend development then you're already familiar with this
for instance django has this idea of a pk which is primary key you can also
read it as id so everything that's stored in the database has some sort of
a primary key firestore is no different so every
document that is created inside a firestore database is also going to have
a primary key okay so that's the first property that our
cloud node is going to contain the other two are very familiar because
you saw here in the documents we're gonna have a text field and the other
one is like the owner user id so there are three fields that we have to add to
our class so let's go ahead and do that let's just say
um if i can type here so class sorry i have a microphone right
in front of my face like it's blocking my keyboard so that's sometimes that's
why i have to like look like this just to find my keyboard
so let's say cloud node um
and inside our cloud node let's define these three properties so let's just say
final string document id okay
and i'm going to copy the string here as well and say owner user id and then
we're going to say text okay help from visual studio code to
implement the constructor and um in here then i'm going to say
this is a constant constructor okay as i said you could actually go and define
this as immutable which i actually prefer in this case to be honest with
you i hadn't i hadn't planned to make this immutable but i think actually
makes sense if it's a cloud node then let's just say it's immutable okay
so that's that's the first part and i also know that we need to make these
required parameters so let's go ahead and do that let's just say required
before all of these parameters okay so that they're actually required named
parameters that are not optional basically
okay that's that if you look at how our database nodes
let's see if we can find database node inside nodes service
so let's have a look at database node do you remember that we had these fields
but we're pretty much never calling this database nodes a constructor we're
always using this thing database node from row
and this is basically the object you just see this map is the object that
we're reading from our sqlite database and crew and then we're internally
creating instances of our database node from that object okay
so this kind of map is what you will also
receive from firestore
however it's going to be wrapped inside something called a query document
snapshot so it's just a wrapper around your data so
let's go ahead in here and and what we're going to say is if you just type
query document snapshot then visual studio code is going to import
this automatically for you okay so then it should be imported in here so
that's great and also we need our um
cloud storage constants so let's go and import those as well so let's just say
package and my nodes and we have uh what do we have
where is this stored inside services cloud so services cloud
constant or sorry cloud storage constants so
you need cloud firestore dart and then your constants as well
let's go ahead and create kind of like a constructor that we are going to call
from snapshot and this constructor is going to allow firestore to give us a
snapshot of it and cloud nodes and then we're going to create an instance of our
cloud node from that okay so let's just say cloud node from
from snapshot and parameter is going to be query
document snapshot that has that map that we actually need
like this and we're going to call it snapshot like that okay
so now you can see that we're getting some
errors from um from dart saying all final variables
need to be initialized and a function body must be provided okay we're going
to fix it soon so this is this is the um signature of your function then in here
your job now is to make sure that all your fields are initialized so let's
let's just say if i can type again document id
it comes from our snapshot id that's a property that is stored on this
at the snapshot level so you can get that id okay
and what we're going to say is that we have an owner user id that we also have
to fill in so that comes from the snapshot
uh snap shot
data and in there then we have to say the
owner user id field name let's see owner user
id
under user id let's call this field name so sorry about that let's go back to the
cloud storage constants and fix this to say owner user id field name actually
okay
so we missed that but that's okay it's just a naming change so
then we're gonna say owner user id field name
so that's for the owner user id and we're going to get the text which
is equal to snapshot dot data
and text field name as string
okay so what we have is a beautiful cloud node immutable class with a
constant constructor and also we get this snapshot um query document snapshot
from firestore soon and we can create instances of our cloud nodes as you'll
soon see
all right now what we need um is to create our new cloud firestore
service so this is like the beginning of moving
away from cloud storage into firestore so this is actually very exciting and a
little bit um a little bit intimidating maybe at first
because well we kind of have to like redo quite a lot of work
but given that firestore provides you with pretty much all the tools that you
need as you'll soon see the implementations of the functions that
we're gonna that we're gonna do are so minimal because the base is there fire
stores already provided the base we just have to hook into it and grab the data
write the data etc so so let's close all these tabs that we
have at the moment excuse me and let's go to this um
services cloud and create our new firebase cloud storage dart file
firebase cloud storage dart
all right so i'm actually going to do that as well so
firebase cloud storage
in my notes all right so let's go ahead and say we have a new
class called firebase cloud storage like that
at the moment it doesn't do really anything but what we need to do uh is to
make uh make this a shared instance
and i'm gonna bring the caption for that and
if you remember we've already made our node service
a
a singleton so let's go back to our node service
command p on macintosh and visual studio code or control p in
windows and linux to bring up this search files by name field and i'm just
going to say note service if you remember inside note service i
think at the top we had this pattern
for creating a singleton do you remember this
right so we kind of need or sorry this part we
kind of need the same thing not kind of actually pretty much exactly
the same thing except for this part because this talks with a stream
controller so i find this pattern of creating singletons in dart still quite
hacky i think i've mentioned this before when we created the node service
but it's something that we have to do so make sure our firebase cloud storage is
actually a singleton okay so i'm gonna bring that code from my notes because i
don't think it's actually worth writing this and it's not worth your time or my
time but this is what you need to create so
what is happening in here is that we have a private constructor
then we're going to create a factory constructor which is the default
constructor of our of our class firebase cloud storage right here
and that is going to talk with a static final field which in turn calls this
private initializer so
in um in other languages like swift and rust it's it's a lot easier to create a
singleton but this is a pattern you have to do so
first create a private constructor then create a factory constructor that talks
with a static final which in turn talks with the private constructor okay
okay after you've taken care of that what we need to do is to grab all our
notes from our cloud storage okay
so let's just go ahead after this factory constructor we're gonna expose a
field as the note as the caption at the bottom of the screen in the case call
notes so i'm just going to say notes equal to
we're just going to say firebase and firestore and it's going to auto import
it for me so this is not a strange thing anymore to you as well
and then i'm just going to say our own instance and then
excuse me a collection called notes quotes as well
okay so this is how you actually talk with a
firestore so you can see that the signature of this collection is actually
returning use something called a collection reference
and you will soon see how we can extract our actual notes from this collection
all right and also remember
this isn't gonna work if you haven't actually created your notes collection
so if you haven't done that if you forgot to do that please go ahead
excuse me to go ahead and do that right now
so the first thing we need to do is to create a function for creating new nodes
all right excuse me
so let's go ahead um into our project and create a function as the
caption indicates i'm going to say void create new nodes in here
and then we're going to say we need a an owner id
so required string owner user id i believe we call it and then it's an
async function okay and then in here since you have
like a stream or a read write stream uh of all your notes and that's what this
uh collection reference means it's it's not
only a stream that you can read from but also it's a stream you can write to
that's why that's why it's not called a stream okay
because the stream is like you try to read only from it so
and in here what we're gonna do is going to say notes add
and you can see it literally says give me a map or a dictionary or however you
want to call it an object that has keys and values
what do you want me to store in a database and that's what nosql kind of
means in here is document based it's it has no real structure of what you're
adding everything that you add in here is going to be packaged into a document
that is going to be stored in here with the fields and the values that you
specified in here okay so let's go ahead and say we provide you
with a with a document in here and the first
field is owner user id field name and that's gonna auto import it from our
constants from before remember and in here the value of this is going
to be the owner user id and
the text field text
field name is just going to be an empty note
for now okay and remember this is an async asynchronous function which
returns a future of a document reference just like we have our collection
reference in here but we actually don't want its results right now at least so
we're just gonna wait on it so don't forget that weight because without doing
the weight this function is not actually going to be invoked
wow okay um what we need to do now then is to go to
the next item excuse me which is
getting notes by user id so the signature is going to be it's going to
return an i
of cloud note you given a user id so
as we said every every node we store in our database uh
is gonna have these two fields an owner and a text field so now what we want is
to grab all the nodes for a specific user okay
so let's go ahead and do that so it's called
um get notes and it's quite a meaty function actually i can see in here
so let's go ahead and do that right now let's say future of iterable um of cloud
nodes and i think we have to import cloud node as well so pressing this
button imports this for me if you're getting some errors it's probably
because your editor hasn't been able to find cloud nodes so
and then we're going to say get notes and a required parameter in here
under user id okay and it's an asynchronous function so like that
so what we're going to do then is to um a weights
uh on our on our notes in here you see we can
actually retrieve notes from our notes collection in here by saying notes where
so we're gonna do a search inside the notes uh
collection reference and that and you do that using the where clause okay
and these things could actually increa like create an exception i believe the
word clause could actually throw an exception whether it was this one
it's not documenting here but i do believe that it could actually create an
exception so let's go ahead and catch this so
let's just say try we're gonna try and then should anything happen in here
uh we're just gonna throw and could
not get all nodes exception and this is going to auto import that from our
previous code so i i shouldn't explain this over and over again you know
already how that works okay so now that we have that we have a try
and catch statement in there so let's just say we await on the notes
and we say uh where clause and the word clause is
going to say okay what is the field that you want to do
your work search on and we want to search for all notes that are for this
owner user id so let's just say owner user id field name
should be equal to you see that's the parameter is equal to owner user id like
that okay
waiting on it you see sorry after doing a word this gives you a query but then
you need to actually execute this query and you do that using its get function
and you see it returns and
let me see gets if i move my mouse over you see it returns a future of a query
snapshot with all the objects that firestore could retrieve from the
database okay so we have to get um
what we do then is to do then
that's that's how we work with future so event clause of the future allows you to
return it what it does is it returns the value of that future to you and it
allows you to return either a synchronous value inside the then
function or you could actually return another future
those who are familiar with node.js or just javascript in general
or even swift they're familiar with how promises and how futures work so this is
your chance of actually returning a value given this
future that is returned to you okay so we're going to call this basically
value at the moment and if i move my mouse over this you can see it says a
query snapshot of these um potentially written
red documents so in here what we're going to do is say
docs which is all the documents that could be read
and we're going to map all those and you can see in here
if i call this doc if i move my mouse over it so it creates
document snapshot whereas this one was a query snapshot this one is a query
document snapshot of those fields okay so let's go in here and what we're going
to do is to say we return inside this return a cloud node
and we have these three fields okay we have the document id owner user id and
the text so it's our chance basically to create
an instance of our cloud node right now i'm gonna put the
columns here so we get the formatting a little bit better
and what we need to do is to get the document id and the way to do that is
this dock has an id in here you can see it's a string so
and the other one is to dock and then we have the data
and let's just say owner user id field name
and that's a string
and in here we're gonna say then a doc data
and we say text field name as a string now remember this looks very
familiar where have we done this before yeah we've done this in cloud notes from
snapshot and don't worry we're actually gonna use
that function as soon we're gonna remove this return statement the way it's
written but let's just write it like this right now okay so it's easier to
understand
wow all right um i think i think that should be it
and so we have that excuse me
and um
yeah i believe i believe this is going to cover it for us right now so not much
more to explain about this to be honest so
we could also put a comma here to
make the code a little bit more readable and we have the value then
return and what we don't have to be honest with
you here is this return statement in here
or actually we created this like this so yeah it's an arrow function
so we don't have to have a special return statement but if you don't like
this kind of an arrow function you can grab your code that you've written up to
this point like this and create
curly brackets in here and instead use this syntax to say return
instead okay so it kind of depends on what you prefer um
i don't have a preference and i could use an error function the way it is so
i'm just going to leave it like this okay
and remember we're at the moment awaiting on this but we're not returning
it so let's just return so this is all basically just a fancy way of us
excuse me communicating with firebase firestore and reading documents and
there's so much to explain that i can't go through all of these but i really
suggest that you play with these functions yourself read the
documentations and see why is it that i'm using where and then get
so uh for that you need to read all the documentations
that come with these functions so you understand them better
okay um so that's getting notes by user id
now what we need is also um
[Music] what we need is
the ability for us to be able to provide our notes list
in here with a stream of notes for that particular user okay so
um as you as you know now in our note service the way we have it is we are
exposing this stream of list of database node and that's what we kind of also
need to do with our firebase cloud storage like have a function that our
nodes list excuse me can't subscribe to and read
all the available nodes for that given user so let's go ahead and do that let's
just call it a stream iterable and i have that function signature so i
don't think i should actually write it manually but you may need to write it so
so that's a function signature okay and in here what we're going to say is
that we're going to go to our notes collection in here and get all the
available snapshots let's see we have our notes and then we
have our snapshots and we're gonna map that and
let's just say yep gonna get our documents inside that
snapshot and then we're gonna
map that like that and let's just call it doc
and in here we're gonna create a cloud note from snapshots
of that doc like that and then in here
we're going to say where
that's our note and then we're going to say the notes
owner user id i'm gonna actually write this and then i'm gonna tell you what
i'm basically doing because there's quite a lot of code in here and like
pausing to describe every little bit of this code could actually make it look
more complicated than it is so and i'm just gonna then say owner user
id okay
but a semicolon there wait a minute
this ends there and then a semicolon there yeah so let's see what is
happening in here so this looks actually quite intimidating to look at but it's a
very simple piece of code so what we're doing in here is if you want
to grab a stream of data as it is evolving you want to be able to
subscribe to all the changes happening to it then you need to use something
called the snapshots as you can see this is a stream of query snapshot whereas
where is a query itself okay and then get
is a future so it just the get one literally takes a snapshot at that point
in time and returns it to you but if you want to like keep hold of
like if you want to be updated about all the changes live as they're happening to
your data in the notes collection then you need to subscribe to the snapshots
that's what we're doing okay so that's that first part with snapshots so we're
literally saying that we want to see all the changes as they're happening live
okay then it says okay i will give you all
the changes that are happening live and that comes inside the query snapshot
remember query snapshot from here remember query here
oops inside the get so
after this point is it's literally what we did in the get notes it's saying that
okay here is a query snapshot and then we're saying okay there are documents in
there and that's exactly what we're doing in here there's documents in the
query snapshot and then we're mapping every document to a cloud note all right
and then we're putting and where clause at the end
that says we're only interested in notes whose u owner user id is the owner user
id provided in here so without this word clause we're literally exposing all the
notes um to the current user for all users in the
system so that word clause is very important okay
so and this work clause as you can as you can see it is actually inside
flutter bin lip core iterable so that's nothing that is it's not a function that
firestore has provided for us okay
wow that was that was a lot of information
okay let's go ahead and talk about updating you notes sorry updating
existing notes so as we talked about it before if you have a note and you tap on
it the way it works in our application right now is i can tap on this node and
go and change its text like 22 and come back out and now it's changed to 22 okay
so we need to also expose this functionality
excuse me in inside our firebase cloud storage um
as well so the function is going to be update node and it's going to take two
parameters document id and a text so let's just say
it's going to be a future of void and we're going to call it update node
two parameters in here which are required i'm going to say required
string and document id
and then required string text
and let's make this an async function
all right then what we're going to do is we're going to put a try and catch in
here in case we can't update the notes and then here we're just going to
say throw could not update note exception okay and you may actually
ignore this e if you want to as well so you could just do like this
or you could just yeah i think actually we can't do an empty cache catch so you
may do like this if you prefer but i prefer to do it like this
all right and i can see that the formatting is a little bit messed up in
here so i'm going to put a
comma in there and inside the try statement in here now
what we need to do is to go to our collections again in here and
let's just say we get a doc you can see it says okay what is the path of that
doc and we're going to say the document id
is a path and then let's then go ahead and say
um dot update and it says okay what is the actual
update and inside the update what we're gonna do is gonna say
text field name is this text all right
so this may look a little bit crypt now also we have to wait on it may look a
little bit cryptic in the what is doc dock id
remember inside this function in here it says give me the path you see this
parameter path and what we said is that inside the
notes collection every document is going to have an identifier so we actually are
going to go with the document id which we instantiated in here do you remember
doc id is going to go into our cloud node document id so that's the path is
notes slash that document id so that's how far firebase firestore it called and
basically keeps hold of its paths it's the the path is in this case if i create
a collection you see it says oh the collection is being created in the root
folder and it has a collection id which in our case is called notes and we refer
to it here so we've already constructed the notes path and every document inside
it has its own id so it's going to be slash notes slash document id all right
so i hope and i'd explain it for you
let's now talk about deleting notes um so
deleting notes actually very easy as well so we don't have to do so much with
deleting nodes so it's very similar to updating nodes and
we're just going to go ahead and use document id for deleting notes so
as the caption indicates create a new feature of void in here and we're going
to say delete node and we're going to go ahead and use a required string
parameter called document id
it sync and let's just do a try cache in here in case we can't delete the
document and then we're going to say throw
could not
no notes exception i believe it's called
yeah inside the
try statement in here we are going to say notes
doc with that document id
all right and then we're just going to say delete
i remember i believe this is actually future void so let's just wait on it all
right so that's really all you have to do for
delete so there's no magic in that it's very similar to update note except that
it's not taking care of any like fields or anything like that
wow huge huge chapter we've talked a lot about now uh about firestore and
firebase storage so thank you so much for for sticking with
me throughout this chapter and but if you remember i mean if you look at what
we've done is not so much code it's 68 lines of code for me it may be less for
you if you haven't done all these extra commas in here so
maybe like 60 but there's a lot of new concepts so
i thought that i had to i took the liberty of maybe even over
explaining things but i think in the beginning it's very
important just to understand how everything works
um okay
so great job we've done what we promised to do in this chapter we have actually
tested to make sure that this is this is working we're gonna do this in the next
chapter but as it's tradition we're gonna make sure that our work is
committed to our uh github repository or bitbucket wherever
you're using your uh or wherever you're hosting your git project so let's go
ahead and do that i want to change the screen um
layout a little bit i'm going to get rid of scrcpy
oops and i'm going to close the screen
make this bigger in this uh view and then i'm
going to go to terminal okay excuse me let's have a look at our
status there's quite a bit modified in here and also we've added a whole new
folder so i'm just going to say git add all
and let's have a look at our log the previous commit was step 18 and let's
have a look at our tags i can see step 18 here as well
let's commit now let's say let's say step 19
excuse me again and then we have
commits and we've committed and let's push those
changes let's also tag and say step 19 in here
okay and let's push our tags as well
all right that's that as again is tradition at the end of
every chapter we'll talk about what we have to discuss in the next chapter
and as you can see it says uh we need to start using our new service instead of
sqlite database so that's a little bit of a
um like a turning point in our whole uh course in that we're gonna like toss our
local storage and go away from that and start using our firebase cloud storage
and so uh it's it's i think the next chapter is
actually one of the most exciting chapters
excuse me in this whole course so
grab some refreshments if you want to and i'll see you there
hello everyone and welcome to chapter 37 of this flutter course as you've seen in
previous chapters we've started to move away from our local database storage and
that was on sqlite and we started going more and more towards using firestore
databases that are hosted by firebase so that was a very exciting point in our um
in this course basically and for me as well as the as your instructor to go
over to a cloud storage rather than using local
uh storage and you see we used crud and as i mentioned in the previous chapter i
really wanted to introduce you to crowd because it's such
an important part of software development that you will sooner or
later need to use crowd storage locally on your computer on your applications so
um that was basically done
on purpose so we first talked about local storage and then we move away from
it and simply because uh even firebase in
itself is some sort of a crud storage not some sort of it is crud but it is
stored on the cloud and concepts of crop would have been a lot bit more difficult
for me to explain to you had me not first implemented implemented them
locally so um
in the previous chapter we prepared our service which we i will bring the code
here so we can have a look we we actually called it let's see
it's inside our services cloud we call it firebase cloud storage
right here and um we also talked about how we can
basically start integrating in this firebase cloud search in our
application and this is the chapter that we're gonna
um make those plans concrete okay
if you follow the chapters from the beginning chronologically in
this course you'll know that what i like to do when i try to refactor things is
to cut things from the source and by that i mean now we want to get rid of
our local crud storage and what i like to do as a strategy is to go to
uh the application and like either comment out that entire piece of code
which has to do with our note service and the crowd exceptions
or either we cut it out completely or we
commented out okay so let's go ahead and deal with that now
so i'm gonna change the screen layout a little bit here and i'm then gonna go
into our notes service so please go to the note service and select the entire
code in here and comment it out so that's for note service and then
we're also going to go to our i'm going to save this file and then we're going
to go to crowd exceptions select the entire content and comment it out please
so that's that um another thing that we need to take
care of is um inside our new firebase cloud storage inside uh get's notes what
we forgot to do is where i actually didn't forget to do i intentionally left
it like this so that we could get the basic idea is as you can see here we we
are inside this uh get notes function as the caption indicates at the bottom of
the screen we are returning an instance of our cloud node use using its
constructor its default constructor however if you remember from this cloud
node snapshot we have a convenient constructor that can create
an instance of our cloud node using a document snapshot and that's exactly
what we're getting in here you see query document snapshot but we're not using
that convenient constructor and that's exactly what we're going to fix
right now so excuse me
let's go in here where we have the dock and i'm going to change this code to go
from a normal function to an error function and then in here i'm gonna say
we return a cloud node from snapshot of that dock okay just like that
i press s to save this file command sorry and you can also remove that comma
at the end so you either leave it like this with a comma at the end so it
becomes multi-line or you remove the comma like i do in here and it just
becomes one line all right okay
that part is done
now what we need to do um is to be inside this
firebase cloud storage and you can see in here
inside the functionality uh sorry inside the create new node at the moment we're
saying void so we're not returning the node that we're actually creating and we
need to fix this so we need to actually create the new new
node and return it so let's go in here and i'm just going to say final
make the code a little bit bigger final
document is equal to a weight on this
and if you look at your document now you can see it is a document actually
you may not be able to see it now you can see it probably it is a document
reference okay so it's a reference as its name indicates is not the snapshot
in order to get the snapshot we need to just issue the get function on it
so let's just say final fetched note is a wait
on this document get and you'll see now fetch note is the
actual snapshot that will contain the data of that document all right
so in here we will just return a cloud node
like this or
let's see cloud node with these parameters
the document id is going to be the fetched note
id the owner user user id is provided to
our function already and the text is just going to be empty like this and
also make sure that uh in here we don't return void except we return a future of
cloud nodes okay so
save your file after that and this part's also done
okay um
now we need to make sure just i'm just gonna
close uh all these tabs and as the caption indicates we're gonna go to our
create update notes view and fix that up so it can
talk with our new service which is the cloud firebase storage i think we call
it firebase cloud storage sorry about that
so i'm going to press command p in visual studio code on mac or control p
and linux and windows and then just say create what's it called
create update node view okay and here as the caption indicates we
need to import three things our cloud node dart file
the cloud storage exceptions dark file and the firebase cloud storage dart
files so those are at the moment inside the um
let's see they're inside services cloud folder
so i'm going to go in here i'm just going to say import package my nodes and
then services cloud
so we have first cloud node so let's import that
i'm going to copy this path and then use it again to import cloud storage
exceptions like that and then we also need cloud
what's it called firebase cloud storage like that so that's
you will need to also do these three imports if you haven't called your
application my notes then this package is going to be different it's going to
be packaged the name of your application and then services etc etc okay
okay um
the next thing that we have to do as you can see in the captions here
we need to make sure that our create update node views state which is right
here which at the moment contains our node service as its node service it has
to move towards using the firebase cloud storage
so i'm going to go to my notes as well in here just to make sure i'm giving you
all the information that you need so let's change our node service in here
and call it now firebase cloud storage and that's the service okay
and in your init function then you need to also make sure that we get the
singleton instance of our firebase cloud storage in the init state function all
right also remember this note now is not a
database note anymore but it's actually a cloud node so let's call that cloud
node as well all right and and now we can see we have an unused
import in here so i'm just going to remove that since we don't need that
unused import then the next thing we need to do is as
a caption in the case we have to go to create or get existing node and we have
to make sure that it works with the cloud storage so let's go in here
perfect so in here