scrcpy together actually as we're going to do
in this course so
i'm just going to take in my notes here that i've explained that so
um before actually we go about installing scrcpy we need to
do um we need to install adb and
this adb is like um i believe it actually stands for android
debugger or something let's see what actually adb stands for
i'm gonna bring up a um a safari window here as you can see adb
stands for android debug bridge and adb is a great tool if you want to for
instance be able to talk with your android telephone all from the command
line so you can send it a message and say hey take a screenshot
hey do this or click here or yet close this application whatever so you
basically send commands to your android telephone or tablet through your
terminal it's um it's fantastic and
with with
adb i mean having adb install your computer then you can actually install
scrcpy which uses adb in order to talk to your
telephone and send commands to it and receive images from it etc so
with that said we need to install adb so i'm going to close this turn window here
and i'm going to bring up terminal i'm going to increase the size of this
terminal window so you see what i'm doing okay
so in here then i'm going to say brew install
cask android platform tools okay
so this will then allow you to install if i can
using android platform tools then um you will be able to grab adb from that so
android platform tools insta installation actually includes adb all
right so
um i can see that i mean for me you can see that i've already installed android
platform tools so i get this message here saying that well you've already
installed it but if you have not installed android
platform tools before you will running this command will actually install it
for you now i don't want to reinstall it so i'm just not going to do this
suggested command here but just know that before you install scr cpy you will
need to get adb up and running okay and that comes in android platform tools
all right
so let's let me just go into my notes and
say that we've talked about adb so after you've done adb we need to go and i'm
going to bring up safari again let's see if i can bring up the window
here so you can see what i'm doing as well then i'm going to say scr cpy
okay and then you will see that the first suggested website is on github and
this is exactly where you need to go so go to scrcpy here and you will see
information about how you can actually install scrcpy and it says on linux you
can do apt installer crcpy on windows you can do a download here
and on mac os then you can do brew install
scr cpy
so i've already done that so i've already
actually installed scrcpy so i don't have to do anything special
and um you can see it actually tells you here i'm going to increase the size of
this window so you can see a little bit better
and it will tell you here that you need adb accessible from your path if you
don't have it yet then do that command that i mentioned to you okay
so after you've done the installation on
your computer then you should be able to bring up a terminal so i'm going to
bring up terminal here and
as you can see here i have my android telephone and it the screen looks like
this right now so it's just on the home screen nothing special
then i want to bring up scrcpy
but before you do that if this is the first time you're doing
this process you will probably need to enable something called usb debugging on
your android telephone and
depending on how your what your android phone looks like or
what it is the usb debugging when you plug your
android telephone it will kind of show you
um a screen like this
so i'm going to enlarge this a little bit so you can see better
so this dialog will pop up on your android telephone saying that oh do you
want to allow this computer to do debugging on this um on this telephone
and what you need to do is just to say always allow from this computer and then
press the ok button this is only so that you will be first of all able to install
and debug your flutter applications
all from visual studio code or from android studio right on your android
telephone or tablet and also it will allow you to run scrcpy
which in turn uses adb in order in order to communicate with
your device okay so
that is for usb debugging all right
so what we need to do is actually bring up scr cpy so
in terminal i'm just going to say ser cpy
and as you can see here it's going to talk to my android telephone and it
brought up a window which i'm going to slowly bring here to this screen so you
can see so
i'm going to leave the terminal here because the terminal is actually fueling
this thing so if i close my terminal this is also going to be closed so just
keep this terminal open or if you're using item for instance like i'm using
then you can bring up a new tab and continue working with another
command line otherwise you can just close it or you can just minimize this
if you're if you're bothered by it so as you can see now i have my android
phone here mirrored on my screen i'm actually going
to do this so you can see it a little bit better i'm going to bring it right
here in between so this is my actual android phone so if i click here with my
mouse it actually interacts with my phone so
i can bring up my phone here so you kind of see them side by side
and if on the if on the scrcpy screen here i press the
back button you will see that my android screen
changes one more time click on google
so it's really interacting with my android telephone here okay
so i highly suggest that you actually
install sdrcpy to be honest with you it's a great great tool if you're into
mobile development or if you want to become a mobile developer so
um and regarding what i said earlier about
devices i think in you will get really really far with the
ios simulator and the android emulator however
i personally should suggest that you spend
and invest some money into getting devices for for yourself they don't have
to be top of the line latest devices but
one android telephone and one ios telephone
or even tablets will do but preferably telephones you don't even have to have
sim cards in them just just the telephone device physically itself so
um and
i mean if you're getting into mobile development you will kind of after many
years kind of have a lot of telephones anyways because you will get like this
year's new telephone and then two years later you get another telephone so you
kind of pile them up um
and you could use those all telephones then as test telephones as we call them
all right so
that's that part now what we need to do next is to now that our android phone is
connected here what we need to do is to go to visual
studio code into our project and choose that um
so choose our let me see bring up visual studio code here if i can visual studio
code this is i have so many screens here so
it's a little bit of a challenge to actually
line them up all here so what i'll do here is i will get rid of the side
window all right and i will bring up then scr cpy on the right hand side and
then just resize the screen a little bit here
and then like this so i have you this is like my usual setup so i have visual
studio code here on the left and then i have my android phone mirrored on the
right hand side okay so what then you'll need to do after
you've done all of this work is in visual studio code just say command
shift p on mac or ctrl shift b on linux and
windows and if you're using android studio i don't to honestly know the
commands there to select a device in flutter they may be like a drop down or
something so please do that so here i'm just going to say command
shift b and i'm going to say flutter select device okay
and in select device i'm actually going to choose my
android telephone which is the one being mirrored here
choose an android phone and then i'm going to say run run without debugging
okay
so let's then see
that you can see here it says launching dart on gm 19 blah blah in debug mode so
since it's an android application now all of a sudden we just switch from ios
to android previously our application was being like our source code was being
compiled by xcode and now since we're trying to deploy to
an android telephone it's the gradle it's gradle basically that's taking care
of the build process so if you're an android developer then you know that
basically gradle zero build system and yeah
it is working um it is basically doing the build in the
background so i'm actually so glad that we got this
error right now so i'm gonna take here in my notes that we've talked about in
vs code select android and then show android phone mirroring working okay
so you see here we got some errors
actually when we talked about in chapter what chapter are we on we're on chapter
10. in chapter 9 when we talked about running our application on ios we
actually got something similar there was an error saying that oh your
uh dependencies firebase they need this
version but you're on that version and and the under
and the code that actually solved it if you remember we went to our pod file i
just put this platform here saying ios 13 because you see we have four
dependencies at the moment we have firebase auth we have firebase core
analytics and something else which i don't remember let me have a look at the
notes here there were core auth cloud firestore and
firebase analytics these four dependencies they have their
own requirements so they say that we as dependencies cannot be installed on an
application that for instance supports a very old android os or a very old ios
version so these dependencies are putting requirements on your project so
and we fixed that yes uh in the in chapter nine we fixed that um by going
into the pod file and commenting out this basically removing
the comment from this line and changing it from 9
to 13. so we fix it like that for ios but how do we do it for android now we
get a lot of great information here and it says that you kind of need to find
this debug default config and min sdk version okay so let's look for default
config so i'm going to copy that text and i'm going to then command shift f in
visual studio code and search for it and as you can see here we have a little um
flutter version name and then flutter version code to integer
and i can see here there is information about flutter versions like
if you go to our build gradle and
there is a flutter version code to integer that is the
and the where's the main sdk here min sdk version okay so i'm going to search
for min sdk version and here i can see it is 19 here it is
19. and android min sdk version 19 so there's actually quite a lot of
places where 19 is mentioned all right
and the error itself let's read it requires a higher android sdk version
fix this by adding the following to the file build gradle android default config
min sdk version okay so if we look at the default config here
it's talking about this thing min sdk version i can see that previously this
used to be a number and recently it has been changed to flutter min sdk version
so i'm going to bring up a safari window and i'm going to say change flutter min
sdk version so let's see what people are actually suggesting is there a good
command that allows us to do this you see people are still saying that we
need to do it like that by changing it to a specific version but i believe
there should be a better way of doing this instead of hard-coding it um
with the new flutter project with the flutter style you're unable to change
the mini sdk version and local properties
great okay so if we go to a file called local.properties that's what they're
saying here so i'm gonna
try to find local properties and i can see here
there is an sdk set here but there is no min sdk version
so we probably need to just go and fix that
up so i'm going to copy paste and i'm just going to say flutter.sdk version
19. okay save that file then i'm going to go back to the main dart and then say
run without debugging let's see what happens this time
and if it accepts that local properties change that we just
made and it's still saying that it won't be
able to users running so uh what we could do in here to be honest
with you is just troubleshooting so let's just say go back to the root
folder of your application and say flutter clean android
why is it doing the xcode workspace and then say flutter
pop get
so if this works properly then it should have cleaned the android code for us and
like put the version 19 in our build gradle like this should actually resolve
to 19 so let's go to main dart and just give it one more try if this if this
solution doesn't work then we unfortunately have to go into our
build gradle file and and do what was recommended and put the min sdk version
there as a constant value of 19 just to get the code
compiling so let's have a look here at um
what our gradle build is gonna do
so i don't really know what happened with
it
i it doesn't seem to really be doing anything so one more try run without
debugging and see what happens launching
i'm gonna have a look at my android phone here as well running gradle task
assemble debug
and for me it's not running anything at the moment on this on this phone so what
we're gonna do is let's go to i mean this solution didn't work so
i'm gonna remove that and i'm gonna go to build gradle and put the
target sdk version i think that was the min sdk version sorry
and here we're just gonna say 19 instead okay
like that like it was actually suggested to us so
um let's then go to main dart and then say run without debugging one more time
and if this solution doesn't work i may actually have to like restart the visual
studio code if it's kind of confused for some reason
because usually when you say gradle like when you start the build
process it actually gives you some feedback it either says that something
failed or that yeah i um it then ran successfully and in this
case i can see it's not running so i'm just gonna say quit visual studio code
okay and then i'm gonna bring up visual
studio code so i have a lot of projects usually so
i'm gonna [Music]
minimize all of these things and i'm going to only open
our my notes application so let's go in there
to our my notes application and let's give this a try one more time i'm going
to go to run without debugging and let's see what happens
oh now it's choosing iphone 13 pro in debug mode so that's because i restarted
visual studio code and it doesn't know which device to run on so i'm going to
say select device and then choose my android phone again
run run without debugging and hopefully crossing my fingers here
that since we've changed the
um version number then it's going to work
and i can see here
i see so now it's com complaining about multi-decks so i mean this is great
stuff i'm so glad that we're seeing all these errors because usually we don't
have the possible i mean usually you see in tutorials that yeah everything's
working fine uh he clicked there and clicked there and everything worked but
here we're actually getting to the point where you see every issue that could
arise and then we're gonna fix it together and this is like a day in the
life of a software developer things go wrong but then you'll have to fix it so
um this multi-dex is something that you'll have to
configure and we're going to say use multi-dex flag so
i'm going to go to safari and i'm going to paste it here
um and then there is a solution hopefully somewhere in our default
config you see it says multi-dex enabled so
let's go to your to the build gradle in app which is right here
you see android app build gradle in your default config as it says here
multi-decks enabled just bring it here it's it there
and then go to your dependencies at the bottom of this file right here and bring
implementation multi-decks right there okay so i'm just going to paste it right
there go back to my main guard file here and then say run run without debugging
so let's see what happens
and there are some warnings here that are printed in red you don't have to
worry about them so much right now there are warnings as their name
suggests so um you don't have to worry so much to be honest with you as i
mentioned so there we go here is um our flutter
application now working and running on um
on the actual phone so i'm gonna bring then the phone here
and you can see it is showing the exact same thing so if i with my mouse go over
you can't see that because you're actually seeing my face
so um and then you will see the value 3
printed here as well so that's that's great
stuff um
then
i don't know why this uh screen is rotated
i rotate it back oh it's because my phone is actually
rotated so i'm gonna rotate it back so it's uh
it's not rotated in the wrong orientation great so we got a lot of
problems to be honest with you there um but that's okay that's usually what
happens when we're working with mobile development at least in the beginning
when you're doing the setup so i'm actually
grateful that we're getting these errors so you see them so you don't just think
everything is going to work from the absolute beginning so
even though as i said in the introduction i haven't planned all of
this that these errors come up i don't want things to be perfect so even though
that is happening but i'm still quite grateful that they are happening so
what we need to talk about now is something called screen sleeping and um
as you're developing your uh application on your android telephone or tablet
you'll notice that you will run your application on the phone or the tablet
and then after after a short while your screen will go
to sleep which means the screen will be locked
and then when you try to then rerun or rerun your application or re refresh
your application then you will get an error from flutter saying that it cannot
deploy the application because the device is locked so
that is quite annoying that the telephone does it but it is for a good
reason the telephones like for security purposes they have to lock the screen so
that if you leave it somewhere on a bench or something in a park and you
just forget it and you go away then it is locked so no one's going to get
access to your telephones data with that said what we need to do
is disable it while you're developing your applications because
what you want is a telephone that's always there is available the screen
doesn't lock so you can always deploy a newer version of our application to it
or as or as long as you you don't lock it yourself manually
so what we're going to do is i'm going to bring up the phone here so you see
what i'm doing i'm going to go here i'm going to go to the settings
screen um here and
you will probably need to i mean in order for you to actually even be able
to run your application and do funky things with your application on your
telephone you need to enable something called developer remote so developer
mode on android and on ios is a series of development tools that the phone
provides only to developers and in order to get those tools you need to perform a
series of actions like a monkey or something on your telephone and
um i'm not going to provide instructions exactly how to do that for all different
phones because depending on the manufacturer of your telephone
especially if it's on android then developer mode is brought
into life in a different way so what you need to do is to find out the
manufacturer of your telephone and the model of your telephone here is a
oneplus pro 7 i believe and then google and say oneplus pro 7 developer options
or developer mode then you'll get some information about
how to enable that i've already done that so if i go to i believe it's
utilities or sorry i think it's system then
you can see there then i have an option called developer options okay
so in order to disable screen sleeping you have to go to developer option and
say stay awake and that is by default disabled all
right
so um
we've now then talked about um developer tools and we've talked about
that you can interact with your telephone uh using scrcpy so
to be honest with you i think i think that's all you need to know for
um for the android setup there is not much more to talk about the rest is just
developing our application as usual and then running it on the android phone and
then mirroring the screen using a crcpy so that's what i'm going to do for the
entirety of this course i'm going to primarily run the application run our
application that we're going to develop in this course on this telephone and
mirror the screen using scr cpy but you may choose to use an ios
simulator or an android emulator or an ios phone or a tablet whatever
so i can't provide descriptions about how to do all of
those things because that is a complete course of its own but at least now you
have the tools and the necessary information in order to understand how
you can actually deploy to an iphone and an android phone all right
so uh
with that said now we can say that we're actually good to go on android
um and in the next chapter which is chapter 11 we're going to get to some
juicy stuff which is uh setting up our project on firebase and if you remember
from the introduction we're going to use firebase for our back end
so um then
you know what's coming in the next chapter and uh now you have the tools
necessary in order to get the app running so with that said then let's go
and configure our firebase project in
chapter 11. hello everyone and welcome to chapter 11
of this course in this chapter we're going to talk
about our back end setup which is with firebase
um and i'm as i as i've said it before i kind of assume that you've gone through
the chapters of this course chronologically so you started
from the absolute beginning introduction and then
you're following along so there's lots and lots of lots of information as you
can see it's about eight hours of information before this chapter
so i feel like since i've explained everything so thoroughly in all those
chapters i'm not going to go through all that again
so i will jump over stuff that i've already explained so i if you haven't
watched those chapters i really suggest that you at least skim
over them a little bit so you see so you get the gist of it
um now i'm looking at my notes and i can see
that in this chapter as the caption shows here we're gonna set up our back
end our backend is using firebase and while developing this course i
contemplated creating a like as a part of this course have a
custom backend as well that we do with django i personally do django
development uh for back-end and websites like rest apis and also for
simple websites as well but to be honest with you if i then go
and create a simple back-end with django and then show you how to integrate with
that using flutter it really has nothing to do with flutter
like the backend part has nothing to do with flutter itself so
having that issue in the beginning of this course i
was faced with a challenge of do i go into the rabbit hole of creating custom
back for this course
and walk you through also creating a custom package which has nothing to do
with flutter and flutter is the reason you were watching this course so i
was faced with that challenge of whether i should do that or just use uh firebase
and i choose and i chose firebase simply because it is a product by google it is
kind of like serverless so it is a server without you actually having to
write code as such so i picked firebase for its simplicity
so that we can get the backend working up and running without so much work and
i hope that you understand that that is the reason that we're not doing a custom
back-end but firebase is a very reliable uh
back-end created by google and it has all google's financial backing for
further developments and for support so you
don't have to worry if you're picking firebase and if you're thinking oh is it
going to continue being supported the quick answer is yes it is going to
be supported it is so big everyone's using it and it's too big even to fail i
would say right now at least for the
uh upcoming uh next few years i would say
i can't predict the future for 10 20 years in the future but
for now you don't have to worry about that so
um so that's what we are going to do in
this chapter i'm just going to take it in my notes um
now previously when uh flutter came out like in year 2020 or even the beginning
of 2021 if you want to integrate with
firebase you have to do a lot of custom work
now in the recent versions of flutter
there is a a command that you can issue from your
terminal it is called flutter fire cli and this command
is amazing because like the work that you have to previously do manually a lot
of custom work dragging files and p lists and jsons configurations app ids
etc etc it was such a big undertaking that a lot of developers
would make a lot of mistakes during that process and it was just not good so
um there is now a command that you can
issue from from your terminal which allows you to do all that custom work
but it does it for you so you don't have to do do that manually so
as i provided here there is a link i'm going to open that link
if i can somewhere let's see if i can bring up safari
it opens in a wrong screen i'll bring that screen here
so you'll see it as well enlarge that screen and also enlarge the
font so it is more visible so you can see it says fluffifier
overview and it says get to know firebase for
flutter we recommend starting with the get to
know firebase for flutter code lab and video okay so there's a video here if
you want to watch it and uh and it says okay if you're
migrating your existing project then look at the migration guide migrating if
you're not familiar with that term uh if you're not coming from a software
engineer background migrating economy so you have an existing thing and you want
to make it newer like
and put in new stuff in it so you kind of migrate your information from the old
project to the new one so but in this case we don't have to worry
about that because we're we've created a brand new project so there's no existing
firebase installation in our application that we have to worry about okay
there's a lot of information here you can see it says using the cli etc etc
and that is actually what we're going to do now
we are going to have a look at how we can install the flutter fire cli
and you can see here it says you should execute the dart pop global activate
flussifier cli and then you issue flutter fire
flussifier config so let's start by copying this code from here copy it and
i'm going to bring up my terminal and i'm going to increase the size of my
terminal so you actually see what is happening here okay so i'm gonna paste
that command in and i'm gonna let it do its thing
i've already done this installation before so for me it may actually go a
little bit smoother or a little bit faster but for you it may take a little
bit longer depending on whether you've already installed flat of rsli before or
not so now that that is installed the next
thing you will have to do is you will actually need to make sure i mean it's
not provided in the documentation but it's something that i'm providing for
you because i know that i've personally run into this issue before
so um
this flutter fire cli it will give you this command as you can see here flutter
fire okay and if i in my terminal say which flutter fire
you can see that flutter fire is installed in this folder so it's under
my personal folder on my computer slash dot pop cache slash bin and then
right there so unfortunately when you install lots of fire cli it doesn't
it doesn't tell your terminal where it is installed so if you then immediately
after that say flutter fire and then blah blah blah as it is mentioned here
classifier configure your terminal will most probably say that what is flutter
fire so
it's not provided here in the documentation but i'm telling you here
as you can see in the caption that you need to tell your terminal where flutter
fire is actually installed okay so
um then what you'll need to do is uh to do
as i've mentioned here you can see i've said that you need to change your path
and include your home folder slash pop cache slash bin so if i go to my
terminal configuration if i say um in
vshrc you can see at the top here somewhere i
should have there you see it says export path and i say okay my new path is the
old path plus using this uh double column here or column
this folder as i've mentioned here in the captions at the bottom of the screen
so you will need to do this as well so i'm going to quit vim now and then after
you've done that make sure that you source that
configuration so in my case i would have to say source
zsh rc and that will read the paths um
fresh otherwise you could also take the high road and like
close your terminal completely terminated and then start it again which
in turn reads the configuration and brings flutter fire a path
into existence
if you don't want to source that's what i mean
so now we've talked about that now let's
actually talk about what the firebase cli is
it is a um actually let me make sure i tick all of these items that
i talked about
in right now let me just mark them as done
in my notes so
um so what you need to do now is what we
need to do now is to talk about firebase cli
and um as you can see here is a cli to help us
interact with firebase right from our terminal now
um this this used to be done manually
previously in that you would have to go to firebase and like create a whole
separate project and then integrate that project into your flosser application so
you don't have to do any of that anymore so
um what you need to do now is as the next step is to install the firebase cli
which does all of that work for you so i've provided here as you can see
there is a command here that you can issue
and then you can go to a firebase google com docs cli install cli mac blah blah
so i'm actually going to go to that location
in my web browser here so you can see what i'm doing
here and you will see there's a lot of
information provided here i'm going to bring up the uh i'm going to make the
size a little bit bigger i'm going to bring my face maybe to the bottom right
as well so you can see more information on the screen
and you can see for mac or linux then there is
yeah let's go here mag you can install the firebase cli for macro linux using
one of the following options so standalone binary blah blah so you
need to have a look at this documentation on on how you can install
the firebase cli on your on your computer whether you're using mac or
whether you're using linux or windows so
so after you've done that after you've
installed the firebase cli you will actually need to
log in in your into your account using that
firebase cli
so let's let's do that let me actually in
here um let's bring up our project uh in visual studio code so i'm gonna bring it
up here and bring up the right caption as well
so you see what we're talking about we're going to talk about firebase login
and log out you see when you want to integrate your flutter
application with firebase you need to create a
firebase project on something called the firebase console
so this project is pretty much the configuration of your firebase backend
on firebase's console on their website so you need to configure a backend so
what we need to do here is now before we can actually configure it back in
in your terminal you need to tell firebase what user you have because i
personally have many google accounts and any one of those google accounts can
potentially have many flutter sorry many firebase projects
because firebase projects are linked to your google accounts okay
now in order for our firebase cli to understand where it needs to create the
project you need to tell it to log in with an account all right so
the way to do that is to bring up terminal and as you can see here is my
terminal and i'm going to clean this a little bit
i'm going to bring up the font as well so it's quite ginormous and that's okay
so what you need to do now is to tell it to log in
so i'm going to say firebase login okay
it's gonna do its work and it's telling me i'm already logged in with this
account if you haven't logged in with an account then you're gonna get a prompt
telling you uh okay which email and password do you wanna log in with so
now um it may be actually worth it to be
honest with you for me to log out right now so that you see the entire process
so i'm a bit hesitant to log out because
uh i actually have protected my google account with a security key
so i don't have the key right here and i
hope that i can find it so for the sake of for the sake of actually
going through this process together with you so you see how it works i'm gonna
log out so let's log out here
so i'm saying firebase logout and it says there is a new version of a
firebase tool so let's copy this here and i'm gonna see if we can install
um what did it say npm install
global so let's copy that here global firebase tools okay
if it can do its work then before we can continue
and npm is something called a node package manager and it is kind of like
if you're working with node.js if you're developing for instance node
applications which you which you don't have to know
about it's just a way it's like a tool kit for creating applications uh
remove the existing file and try again or npm with force okay
npm install global with dash dash force i think
yeah so it's it's like a dependency
management for node applications and firebase tools is
a node application so that's all you need to know really i mean there's there
are courses available about node and node.js then you can actually have a
look at how they work etc so i'm not going to go into details about that so
before i could i mean i could have actually done a firebase logout without
all of this but i just want to show you that things aren't planned like i can't
perfectly plan things here and when i tried to log out it said oh there's a
new version of node available blah blah so
now that i think sorry there's a new version of firebase tools available that
you can use that you can install with npm so
i did that so let's now say uh firebase logout
okay so the logit actually was successful
previously and so let's now say firebase login
and it says allow firebase to collect cli usage and error reporting
information i'm gonna say as a developer to be honest with you
you may you may be tended to say no like here but if you are a developer you can
put your shoe you can put yourself in the shoes of another developer working
at google working for firebase and they are trying to get some information about
how you use the cli and whether they can learn from your usage of the cli in
order to make the cli better so i usually say yes to these things
especially if there's a developer asking for permission so but you can say no to
this if you want to so i'm just going to say yes
and you can see here then there's a screen provided here asking me to log in
with one of my google accounts all right and
i'm going to pick my company's google account because that's what i usually
use all right so i'm going to choose that and it says firebase cli wants to
access your google account and it says okay what permissions it's going to use
you can have a look at this information if you want to
if it concerns you so if you if you're concerned about any of these things
please go and read the links provided here
i'm just going to say allow and once that is done you will see that
it says firebase cli login successful and then you can pretty much just close
this window safely and now it says logged in as pixelityav
gmail.com so i can say firebase login again and that would be the prompt that
you saw in the beginning of this video that you are logged in alright
good that was a lot of information now now
that you are logged in with the firebase cli you actually need to configure a
firebase project all right and we do that with the flutter fire cli which we
installed in the beginning of this chapter using this command dart pop
global activate all right so what you need to do now is to
issue the flutter fire configure
command as i've shown here down at on the left hand side so i'm going to do
that flutter fire configure so it will fetch all the projects that
i've already created in my google account and it says okay these
are the projects available flash chat fluffer note guessing chords random
project testing or you can create a new project
now i'm going to choose create a new project here okay
and it says okay enter a project id for your
new firebase project so what i'm going to do here is i'm just going to type my
notes all right so
as you can see my notes is the name of our flutter project as
well so my notes now i'm going to say okay i'm going to create the same
project called my notes okay i'm going to press enter here
i says yeah i'm going to create it and it's probably
i mean you can see that we immediately got an error saying that
this project already exists and you can see
um command blah blah blah yeah fail to
create a project because there's already a project with
with id mynotes please try again with a unique project id so
this is basically telling us that hey someone else has created my notes and it
wasn't one of the projects that we had created because if you if you have a
look at your if you open uh your web browser and say
firebase console go to your firebase console
and uh let me make sure that i'm logged in with my pixelity account yes
and if i have a look let's see dismiss let's
see get started firebase helps you watch
demo yeah we are logged in with that account
so i can actually see maybe i don't have any projects set up here which is a
little bit weird because we actually saw that there were some
projects set up under this account so i don't understand why the firebase
console so it's not showing them um
firebase console backed by google firebase console google
yeah there they are okay so it is on console.firebase.google okay
and i can see that my notes application is not an application that i own i
haven't created that so what it is saying is that globally
firebase projects have an identifier and now i've entered an identifier that is
already taken so what i'm going to do then is i'm going
to issue the same command uh firebase flutter fire configure and this
time i'm going to give it a little bit more information about the project name
so that makes it a little bit more unique so i'm going to choose
create a new project and then in here in the name of the
project i'm going to say mynotes flutter project
maybe someone has already taken this as well
i don't know
so it's doing its thing it's doing its magic basically so let's have a look
and i mean this is okay that is taking some time it
is doing a lot of work it's setting up like the ios project and android project
etc so this thing used to take a lot of time to
do by hand like maybe 10 folds the amount of time that this
cli is taking so i'm not so bothered by the fact that it's taking some time so
and here it will actually tell you okay which platforms do you want to select
and as i said like flutter allows you to create web applications android
applications ios applications and also uh
desktop applications or four platforms and then here it says okay which ones do
you want to create for our project right now you can just
say android and ios you don't have to worry about like
um mac os or linux or windows and web but
you have the ability to do that if you want to so choose android and ios for
now and press enter so it's gonna do its work
so let it do its magic
and now this is this is the amazing part that you had to do manually before you
had to previously go and register like your application with
apple and then go and register bundle identifier and then put the bundle
identifier manually in firebase and then download some files put those files in
your ios and android project now now you don't have to do that anymore
here it just tells you which bundle identifier are you using for your
project and if you remember from before when we created our flutter project from
the beginning we said flutter create and then an organization which for me was s
e dot pixolity do you remember that command
it kind of looked like um i mean if i bring up terminal maybe i
can even go back to it flutter create do you remember this command i will zoom
into it a little bit so you can see better this is how we actually created
our project we said flutter create.org as he pixeled in my notes so the bundle
identifier for this application will be sepixolity.mynotes
however since sc pixelity is the reverse domain for me this won't this won't be
the case for you so go back to how you created that
identifier for a project using your organization name and you now you have
to paste that in here so you will see i'm going to say s e
pixelity dot my notes okay
so enter that and it's going to configure your ios
project for you
and that was it so it has now
set up everything necessary for your project to work so i mean you may you
may just think oh well this was this was so little and what did it actually do
but for me who's been working with firebase and flutter for a very long
time this is all magical because it did a lot
of work it configured your application on the firebase console it actually
registered an android and an ios project hooked into this firebase project
downloaded the configuration files place them in the exact correct place in your
application so it did a lot of work but you don't
really have to know about that so um now if you want to kind of see the
result of it if you see here the output of this says that there is an identifier
associated with your ios app and then there's an identifier associated with
your android app so that's what we're going to do now
let's now make sure that these identifiers are correct and that the
bundle identifier that we provided to the cli is also placed in the
configuration file correctly so copy this for instance ios identifier
that was created for you so copy it and then search for it in your entire
project and then you'll find a little file here and let me bring it down
it is called firebaseoptions.dart
so this is where ios is configured and let me bring this like that so you don't
see it and this is where the android project is
configured you can see the um app id is right here and the api key is
right there so don't worry about this i mean you should not show your api key
and app id to anybody um so but since i'm developing this course for you i
have to show it i can't just go and censor it but don't worry about it by
the time you're seeing this um video by the time you're seeing this course i've
already deleted this project from firebase so there's not going to be any
security risk involved so um
so that project isn't going to exist even if you know the api key on app id
so don't worry about that but if you are developing your own application just
kind of be careful who you share your api key and app id with all right
that was a lot of information a lot a lot a lot so um
and i'm gonna actually tick here that we've talked about that
i create a new project and yeah that's that's all working as it
should so i'm also gonna go here in the
captions and i can see that i have some information here about enabling
multi-decks and multi-dex was something that we've already enabled in the
previous chapter which was chapter 10 for the android project so
now everything should be working as it did before to be honest with you so if
you in your visual studio code or android studio if you're developing
under your flutter app with android studio you can also
go and select your device to run on now in the previous chapter you saw that for
the entirety of this chat in this course i'm gonna use an android phone to
develop uh our application so you may choose to use an io simulator an android
emulator or an android phone or tablet or ios phone or tablet so but i'm gonna
use a real android phone and as you saw we have the ability to bring up scr cpy
to mirror the android screen so i'm going to bring it right here
change the size of visual studio codes window a little bit so you can see the
android um telephone right there as well then what i'm going to do
just to make sure that the project runs after all of this work that we've done
so that we haven't broken anything really let's then go and
debug the application sorry run it without debugging and this
is this is why you will see this is the result of all the work that we've done
pretty much nothing this is like
i mean it sounds funny to say it because we did
a lot of work with the firebase project but there is nothing that you can see on
the screen and that's that's the reality of doing software development you may be
putting a lot of work sometimes in doing something and this result isn't
immediately visible all right so but what you have done in this
chapter was that you actually set up your back end with just a few commands
you installed two clis the flutter fire cli and the firebase cli you logged in
with firebase cli and then you set up your backend with the flutter fire cli
all right now just to make sure everything is set
up properly also you can bring up your web browser i'm gonna bring it up here
and i'm gonna say console.firebase and
let me make sure that we have
our notes app here you can see my node slatter project
and you can click on it and you can see how it is set up for you you can see
there is an android app setup and an ios app setup so
you didn't have to really do anything now there's lots of things you can do
with firebase which we're going to actually play with throughout this
course but not right now just make sure that your
firebase project is created for you by logging into console.firebase.google.com
many dots
all right and we've talked about this now running the application on an
android telephone so that was already set up so we don't have
to talk about that now now that you've seen that you've set up
your backend you're ready to go and uh so i can say congratulations so that's
in order now
the android setup is already done so i can see that that is set up we don't
have to talk about that either however
what we do need to talk about is what we're gonna
discuss in the next chapter so
in the next chapter we are for the first time in this course we are going to talk
about the uh footer code actual thoughts or
code we're going to start writing a simple registration screen so using this
registration screen our right now hypothetical users are going
to look at the screen and say okay i don't
have an account with this application i'm going to register myself so
then you will be able to they will be able to enter
their email address a password of their uh choosing press some sort of a button
and we will then talk with firebase and say here's a new user register that
person okay so that's all for the next chapter which is chapter 12. so grab a
cup of coffee cup of tea whatever you want to do
get refreshed then and i'll see you in the next chapter
hello and welcome to chapter number 12 of this filter course
in this chapter and which i'm very excited about we're going to talk about
a basic register screen well up until this point we've been really configuring
our i mean if we go chronologically we've had the introduction we've gone
through so many chapters to talk about dart and its basics and even some more
advanced topics such as generics
and then as soon as we did that then we
basically started learning about setting up our
iphone and android application also after that
sorry the iphone and android application together with certificates profiles and
got scr cpy working so there's been a lot of information up on those till this
point so many hours of information that you can go back and watch
and i strongly suggest that you actually do that because i've explained
everything in such extent extensive detail that i feel like
explaining all those things again and again will be a waste of time both for
you and me and
in this chapter we are going to use all that information
that we've learned from the previous chapters and start actually creating a
registration screen a simple registration screen in our floater
application source code that talks with firebase and firebase we set up in the
previous chapter if i'm not mistaken so have a look at that chapter if you
haven't set up your firebase app back-end
or at least i mean we haven't really set up anything we've just like
well yeah actually set up yeah we could say set up um but we haven't really
configured in such great details it's just like we've set it up so
have a look at that chapter please if you want to um
before you continue with this chapter so so
i'm gonna go to my captions here and just ensure that i can show you the
correct captions now what we need to do in this chapter
is to start working on our registration screen and what i'm going to do here is
bring up a caption for you so that you know what we're going to do
the first thing you need to do is to bring your
visual studio code or your editor of choice
on the screen so i'm i'm going to do that and then i'm going to bring my
android phone mirrored on the screen with scrcpy
and then i'll see if i can bring my face to the right so you can see a little bit
of a bigger screen and what we need to do here now is to go
in this main dart file and remove everything that is a comment now
if you're coming from like a design background or a product owner or um like
in wherever whatever background that is not
software development related if you're coming from those backgrounds then you
may not know what a comment is however i'll tell you now a comment is a piece
of information piece of text that is written inside a source file such as
this main dart file that doesn't translate to an actual code so it's
information placed there usually for other developers or whoever
is looking at the code so that they understand the code a little bit better
okay comments in dart can be created in
different ways however the most i mean the most usual way of doing it is
with double forward slashes as you can see
here and a space and then some text all right
so i'm going to need you now to go into
your main dart file and we're going to remove all these comments right now
because they are basically creating a lot of noise for us right now okay
so let's go ahead and remove all those gray lines or whatever color they're
displayed on your screen they may be green
depending on your theme
i have tokyo knight as i mentioned before
in visual studio code so comments are displayed in gray
gonna remove all that comment there okay and that's it
so and i think this as well and i don't know yeah and it seems also
like uh so yeah i think now we've removed all
the comments so if i do command s that does a hot
reload and i'm actually going to talk about
what the hot reload is but if you've done this then you're good to go i'm
going to take that in my notes so we've talked about it
now the next topic to talk about here is hot reload versus hot restart now
these two are so important for you to understand that i think you should like
get this before you continue with the rest of the course and i'm gonna do my
best to explain what hot reload and hardware start are
if you're for instance coming from a design background where you have for
instance figma and you design your um
stuff you're you're putting some vectors on the screen you're dragging images and
i can go in your figma design and literally observe you as you're doing
that so i'm actually looking at your changes you don't have to press any
publish button nothing like that even if you're in your drafts i can still follow
you and watch you as you're designing now that future is very very much
possible in flutter as well however
the cost of doing that the same thing that figma does is quite heavy because
as i'm changing my code i actually i'm not going to be able to see my changes
unless i tell flutter that okay i've made some changes show me them on the
screen that is hot reload okay for instance if
i go in here and i say flutter demo home page and remove the demo home page from
here press command s that's going to save my
file which in turn is going to do a hot reload okay
so command s you can see this title now was changed
from here so it's set it says not flutter demo i'm
going to change it back command s hot reload and it's going to say home page
now you can also avoid for instance doing command s and just go in here in
your visual studio code or android studio and just say hot reload so i can
see now that didn't actually do it that was great because i can see a little
like blob here you see the circle on this file this in visual studio code is
an indicator of a file that has not been saved so
so if i save it and it itself is going to do a hot reload so i don't have to
actually manually press the hot reload button so save and then you can see the
changes immediately applied there however some changes to your code are
going to be so big that footwear is not able to resolve the delta from the
previous state of the application to the new states and we will come to those
changes very difficult to explain them right now but just know that hot reload
is usually works in 99 something percent
like i'm making up statistics here in most cases hot reload works in that it
can show you your latest changes however sometimes your changes may be so drastic
and so big and the the
calculation of the delta from the previous previous state to the next to
the new state may be so big that flutter isn't able to do that so then you will
have to do hot reload and then hot reload is
here sorry hot restart you will have to do a hot restart sorry about that
so there's more differences between them like internally about the state
like the state of your application and whether one
keeps your state and the other one loses your state so i'm not going to talk
about that right now because we haven't even talked about states in flutter so i
don't think it makes so much sense to talk about that right now just know that
in most cases hot reload displays your latest changes and that and it's
sufficient if you just do a command s and save your files
but hot restart it will basically kind of like rebuild your application
with new states okay so i think i think to be honest with you
that's sufficient for now so what we need to do now
is to have a look a little bit about at
restructuring the code that is created for us by default
and as you can see here um i mean we don't really know how these
things work right now um you don't even know like in the
caption i say material app inside run app and home page widget
what does this mean well you don't know that and that's okay
i'm not going to like confuse us right now with too much detail but what you'll
need to know right now is that let's go in here and i'm gonna bring the
logs up what i'm gonna do in here in this build
function of my app just go and type print
building
okay and command s and then you'll see that
printed to the screen so every time i'm pressing command s
this entire application is being built again and there is a little bit of like
a resource hug because
as you can see here material application is the entire
kind of like a scaffolding entire frame of your application including the bar on
top including this white view here and including that badge up there on the top
right it's like you are pretty much building
things that you don't need to build every time you save this file so it's a
little bit of like a a problem of um performance whether you want to do that
or not but in this in this uh course i'm just i'm gonna give you some advice on
how to make your application also run a little bit faster so to do that what we
need to do is just to tell flutter that hey look we don't want to build the
entire app every time or the app structure every time we're
pressing command s to how to hot reload so
your challenge here now is to if i get rid of
this what we need to do now is you can see
here in the main function which is the root
function that flutter calls when it actually runs your application it says
okay i'm running an app called my app and if you look at my app the only thing
it does it actually creates a material app that's all it does so
what you need to do now is to grab this material app so i'm just going to say
command x on mac
or control x i think on windows and linux
grab that and instead of this const my app
paste that in there okay and then kill your my app boom like that
okay and then do command s and just to make sure everything is
working correctly i'm just going to do a hot restart
and you can see everything is working as it should so what we did here really was
actually let's see my homepage yeah that's fine
um yeah so
what we have now is just the main function and something called my
homepage stateful widget all right so get your code also to this state
i'm gonna take in my notes that i've talked about that all right
so the next thing we need to talk about is stateless versus stateful
now state
i mean for me it feels like for me to be able to explain this i need to first
explain what a state is uh let's say in here i press this button
five times okay and then i go and i say oh i want to
change the title of this little label there i'm gonna say you
you've instead of you have or
yeah let's convert this to double quotes because we're putting a single code in
there i'm gonna say you've pushed the button
this many times and i'm gonna say command s or control s in windows and
linux to hot reload hot reload yeah command s okay
and you can see is that you've pushed the button this many times but it kept
the number five so if it rebuilt this application or
this widget or this thing that you can see on the
screen how did it keep keep the state well that is because
hot reload is able to sometimes as i mentioned before keep your state and
state is just data data usually mutated and created either by the
application or the user or both and in this case this is a state that the user
is controlling so by pressing the button he or she is increasing this number now
it's 10 okay a state full widget it can keep that
information so
it you see it has something called a counter
it's an integer and it keeps hold of that number so
and upon this number being changed it can kind of redraw itself so
stateful widget is something that is on the screen usually
something that you can visibly see such as this screen the white screen you
can see here stateful
and it can contain data upon who's changing it can redraw itself
itself so had we had the same widget as you can
see in my home page and it was stateless widget which is available as well
you see let's switch it
it wouldn't necessarily be able to redraw itself or contain any mutable
data i mean even stateless widgets for those who are a bit more familiar
with flutter you'll have like value not notifier and builders so even stateless
widgets can be redrawn depending on what you're trying to do
but they cannot contain mutable variables so that is kind of
like the um difference between stateful and
stateless so you can see here this is a variable that is not read-only otherwise
it would be final so if i make this final you can see it says oh you can't
reassign this value to something else so just know that if you see state full
widget then it is a widget that contains information that can be
changed as the user interacts with the widget or
as time goes by or as the widget sees fit however stateless widget is a widget
who's who has who doesn't contain any mutable
pieces of information and doesn't manage any mutable pieces of information
internally okay that's a lot of just just there's a lot
of talk i know if you're not comfortable with like if you if you haven't done
software development before you may not this may not make any sense to you and i
promise you as we go on and of course you're gonna learn more about it so
don't worry about it if you didn't get this
on the get-go
so
you can see now let's see um let's talk a little bit about i'm gonna
actually tick this
in the in my in my notes
okay so i can see in my notes that i had um
that as part of as part of uh what i was going to explain here i was
actually i had planned i can see my notes i had
planned in one of the previous captions uh here um
as part of this caption i was actually supposed to come completely kill this my
home page uh widget and i was supposed to actually create a
widget just called home page so let's do that let's just go back into that
caption so kill this my home page and now
go in here and change this to home page so what we need to do now is to create a
very simple home page okay so i'm gonna remove this title from here as well and
you can see now we have an error telling us that okay i don't know what home page
is now what we need to do is to create a uh actually let me see if i plan to
create a stateless yeah stateless widget okay
a great shortcut that you need to know in visual studio code and i think it may
be available in android studio as well is if you want to create a stateless
widget just type stl and you can see it tells you that okay
you want to create a stateless widget great
okay there it is then you give it the name of home page okay so now you have a
home page great and i'm going to do a command s and now you can see this is
one of the times that flutter was like okay
i don't understand what you're trying to do you change some stuff in this main
function and i can't do hot reload so you have to do hot restart so now the
screen is kind of gonna be black so
now we have what i had planned in the course initially for for this chapter so
great let's go now to the next point um
so you can see the screen is black here and that's because of this container
there is a little container there or something on the screen that you can't
really see because it's just black so you could go in here and say there is a
color and you can say colors red i just command s
and you can see now the screen is red so just know that there is something on the
screen but you just can't see it because it's all black so
the way to get your application to a point that is actually like presentable
to a user you usually have to create something called a scaffold now scaffold
as it as its name indicates it's kind of just like the basic building structures
of an application that kind of makes it presentable to a user to an average user
so even though if you're creating like a
graphically intensive application this black background may be completely okay
but in most applications when you run them then you'll get
then you'll get like a bar on top that tells you like the name of the screen
that you're on kind of like the title of a web page and you'll also get some like
a status bar on top where as you can see here the status bar is kind of like
black with all white icons on top and it will give you like a wide screen where
you can interact with your content so we don't have that and in order to
create that you have to create something called a scaffold so
go to your container here and say scaffold okay
now i'm gonna press command s and you'll see all this on then we get this little
white screen here and then there's a little tint on our status bar as well so
it makes it a little bit more presentable okay
so what we need to do now i'll basically
see if i've planned to add some bar title in here which i haven't so let's
do that right now so for our scaffold we're also going to add an is something
called an app bar so go to your scaffold and say app bar
and then say i create a new instance of the app bar class all right
and in here there's a property called title and as the title say text
okay and for the text i'm going to get rid of
all this documentation there's excessive amount of documentation here which kind
of blocks the screen so and for the text just say
register for instance and make it a constant
so and put a comma here and a uh comma here as well
so you see after you've done that your screen has a beautiful blue bar
here with the title of your uh application or the title of your home
page and there is a white canvas here for the
rest of your content to be displayed so now there are a few things in here which
i could jump over but i kind of feel like they're so important to explain
that i'm going to do that right now so in flutter every time you have for
instance here there is a text you see sorry there is an app bar an app bar if
you go into the source code of an app bar let's go a little bit higher you can
see it it says i'm a stateful widget all right so app bar in itself is a widget
so what we're doing here is saying we have something called a scaffold let's
go to scaffold it itself is a stateful widget so we're saying the main widget
we're returning from our build function as you can see it should return a widget
is a scaffold which is a stateful widget in itself it has a property called app
bar an app bar it itself is a stateful widget which in turn has a property
called title now the title if you look at the documentation it says
title is also widget so
let me also make the screen a little bit bigger
like this so you see it better so
now the title is a widget and we're saying oh we're going to use a text
widget if you look at text what it is is a stateless widget it means internally
it states or its state can change and it it doesn't have any mutable variables
okay oh i didn't want to change that so
if you see what we're doing here when in flutter you're just creating widgets
everywhere in flutter almost everything is a widget either stateful or stateless
and you try to you need to kind of try to stick to stateless widgets as much as
you can all right we're going to talk more about stateful and stateless so
now that we've added the scaffold and i've explained a little bit about these
widgets that were we've created and we've done a command as here just to
hot reload the application or this widget
uh what we need to do next is to create a login button
so let's go and create some sort of a login
button and you can see here i've written the
caption button on home page in the center to log in
or more accurately it could actually be register
so i'm going to change that i'm going to say register button
and button on the homepage in the center to register okay
display the caption to you there to and i'm gonna change my notes here
just quickly all right so now your task is to create a button on
the screen how do you do that well in scaffold you see the scaffold at the
moment it's the owner of that bar on top and it's the owner of this
white content here so what you need to do is to go and look at a property
called body and body is
in itself if i move my mouse over it says okay give me a widget you see
and of course i could say well i have no widgets null is also acceptable but in
this case we're going to create a button called text button so text button is a
widget if you go into source code you'll see it's a
text button button style button and that is a state full widget all right so
you're basically saying that i'm creating a button and i want to allow
the user to do something with it all right so we need to do as you can see
there is a little bit of an error here to say that says unpressed is a
parameter that you haven't provided to me so we need to tell this button
that when this button is pressed it needs to
do something and this is a requirement for the text button class that it's
telling you well i'm a button what do you want me to do when i'm
pressed if you don't press if you don't provide unpressed parameter to me i
don't i'm not even a button i could just be a label and that is what this error
is all about is saying that if you're creating a button make sure that you
handle what happens when the user presses on so
in here just type unpressed and i'm just going to get visual studio
to complete this code for me you can see it says okay an empty function
a function with empty list of parameters so no parameters
and then the code in itself is empty at the
moment okay so go after the create creation of that function and then you
see that there is another that you have to handle that says child
you see text button you would say you would probably just assume that oh a
text button should have some sort of a string parameter that says what is my
text so
if we write child here the beauty of flutter is that it says
child is a widget so text button doesn't doesn't make any assumptions about what
content you want to display on that button
what it does it says i need to display some widget anything it could be an
image it could be an icon it could be whatever it could be a list of things
which is not a good idea to do but you could still do that so
um go and create a child widget and now
you've learned about the text widget so i'm just gonna say a constant text
widget and in here we're just going to say register okay
now command s and you'll see now all of a sudden you
have a register button there so another cool feature now i want to
show you in visual studio and i think it's available also in android stu is
that you can go and wrap your widgets with other widgets so instead of for
instance saying that i want the text button to be in the center and then you
go and create a center if you know it also exists you could do
command dot or command dot on mac or control dot in windows and linux and
visual studio code on the widget that you want to wrap in some other widget
and then you will get this beautiful menu that
says you you know you can wrap it with many different things so i'm just going
to pronounce a wrap with center so as you can see center is a widget that has
a child property all center does is that it tries to center
horizontally and vertically it's child inside the available space of the center
widget itself the entire available space in this case
as you can see is this entire white background so center has access to that
entire white background right now because center is the root widget of our
body which is the only thing that our scaffold is showing at the moment
so center then is able to center align this
text button so let's command s and you can see the register button is centered
horizontally and vertically in the available space
now that i've talked about that i'm going to take it here
and what we're going to do here is very very important so
what we need to do is we now need to handle when the text
button is pressed that we're going register a user with
firebase okay now
we talked about this when i talked about like uh dart in the previous chapters we
talked about synchronous and asynchronous and i'm not gonna go into
details about that now registration i'm sorry i'm not going to
talk about that in details because we've talked about that in details before so
if you need to know about that i think synchronous and asynchronous were
probably explained in um i'll have a look at my notes
they were explained in chapter number seven so if you haven't watched chapter
number seven i strongly suggest that you do that if you don't know what sync and
async are um
what we need to do now is to tell firebase to register user now
registering a user with firebase is an asynchronous task so it's not going to
complete immediately so what we need to do now is to tell flutter that the
button press is an asynchronous task and all you need to do here is just to put
the keyword async in there okay so
that is that that's it in my
notes i've talked about it
now what we need to do is to have a look at
this link that i've provided for you um i'm going to close this safari window
let me see if i can show you on this screen
um
other sign-in methods great you can see as i'm displaying here
firebase allows you to enable various sign-in methods
uh to your for your users so um
firebase is not only limited to like google
services you can as you can see it can allow you to enable facebook signing for
users or apple sign-in twitter or phone number sign-in so there
are various methods available for you to enable in your flutter
application and in this application we're gonna use email and password sign
in and there's like documentation about all
of those in this link that i've provided provided to you so
i'm not gonna go through the entire contents of this to be honest with you
because there are just so much information and we're not interested in
all of these but still i believe if you're interested in firebase and
firebase authentication which we are going to use in this course it is great
if you could just have a look at this link that i provided for you here
so what we need to do now
is also right i've written here that i need to talk about a little bit about
anonymous users you see firebase when you start your application and you kick
firebait if firebase you basically start the whole process of
firebase you say firebase start firebase is amazing in that on the
client side it by default creates something called an anonymous user so if
you talk with firebase with your thoughts or application and say who's
the current user even if you haven't done anything with firebase before if
you haven't configured it or actually you have to configure it
which we have already done but if you haven't called any firebase functions
before in your application you could just say firebase who's the current user
and firebase will just tell you here's a current user it's an anonymous user so
that user is pretty much never going to be empty it's never going to be null or
nil or whatever you like to call it so or if you're python developer you just
call it none so that user is almost never none
so just know that firebase has a concept of anonymous users okay
i'm just going to take that in my notes that we've talked about it
so what we need to do in the next step i'm going to bring the caption up so we
have to kind of like speed things up a little bit here because there's so much
to talk about um what we need to do here now is just
to create two text fields now one for the
email and the other one for the password and we are going to then put our button
um next to those two text fields so text
field one email text field 2 password and then the register button as the
third component now if you have components like this that you want to
stack vertically one on top of each other and one after each other then you
need to use a which is called column all right
so what i'm going to do here is go here to the center and kind of like remove
that i'm just going to say command dot in mac or control dot in windows on
linux and just say remove this widget okay i don't want to center anymore
command s results register buttons on top left and what i'm going to do is i'm
going to command up again and say wrap with column okay now if you command s
you'll not see anything directly on the screen no changes all right
but what was created for you is a column widget with children property which is a
list of widgets that it can display so the first thing we're gonna do is to
create two text fields okay so let me have a look here and just make
sure yeah i'm just going to say a text field
and another text field okay like that
save you'll see two text fields display there so i can actually go in there and
start typing something okay like that so now we've created two text
fields with a column on the screen
i'm going to note that here a ticket in my notes so we've talked about it now
what we need to do is grab the text that is displayed in this
take these text fields and when you press the register button pass that to
firebase okay now you see i'm telling you that when you press the button you
need to grab the text inside these text fields but inside this function of
onpress you have no access to these text fields okay so you kind of need to pass
information from this text field and this text field to a text button and the
way to do that is is using something called a text controller
so a text or a text editing controller a
text editing controller is kind of like a proxy object that you pass
to your text field and the text field it writes its current text all the time to
that text editing controller and in your text button here then you can say
controller text okay so you can then so it's kind of like if your text field is
sitting here and your text button is sitting here then you'll have something
here in the middle that is your proxy the text editing controller that is
grabbing me for latest information from the text field and then your the text
button can read that information okay so just know that a text editing controller
is kind of like a proxy now that we need to manage some state we
need to manage this proxy object then we need to convert our home page to a
stateful widget okay so go in here to your home page command dot and say
convert to stateful widgets so all of a sudden stateful widget all right
so um now what we need to do is to go and
create those two text editing controllers so i'm going to go in here
go to your home page state here and say
late final what do we call them do i have any
specific desire here let me see my notes
no so there's no desire really for the
naming so let's just say late final text thing
controller and let's call it here email okay
and the other one i'm just gonna say password
now in the previous chapters we haven't talked about late what late is this
keyword in dark that tells your program that although this print although this
variable has no value right now but i promise to assign a value to it before
it is used so it's kind of like a it's a contract so
late literally means that i'm not ready right now i will do it later i'm not
ready to assign a value to this so what we need to do now is to
um is to create these values now
you need to also know something about stateful widgets now that our homepage
state is a stateful widget it will have two amazing
amazing two great functions one is called init state i
believe and the other one called is disposed now init state is a function
that will be called by flutter automatically when it creates your home
page so it says okay now you have the ability to create all your variables or
your late variables once
now whenever this homepage then dies and goes out of the memory or it's trying to
go out the memory it will also get a function called dispose
so you've said that in the contract i've
written that i'm going to provide a value for these emails email and
password text editing controllers and the best way to do that is to go into
this init state function here
and assign those to proper values so i'm
just gonna say email email is text editing controller like
that okay
and i'm gonna do the same thing for the password field
now you also need to understand that you after you've created these two you also
need to dispose of them all right so go in and overwrite your dispose
function and then say email dispose and password
so a lot of developers forget to do this especially like newcomers so don't make
that mistake so you created the text editing controllers and you're also in
charge of disposing them okay now um
okay uh so we've done that already after you've created your text editing
controllers you need to go to your text fields and assign
those controllers to your text field so in here there's a parameter called
controller and just say email and for your text field on the second
one which is for your password say controller
it's password so what is happening now is you hooked this proxy object that sat
here this one which is your email or password
text editing controller to your text field that is sitting here okay you
still haven't hooked it to your text button which is sitting here so this
link is kind of broken and we're gonna fix that soon
okay take it in the notes that we've talked about that
so what we need to do now at the moment if i press command s you will see no
visible changes on the screen however there's a little bit of a problem with
our text fields as you can see they don't have any hint they don't tell the
user what they expect the user to actually enter so
what we need to do now is to go and add something to these text fields called a
hint a hint is a piece of information
provided to the user and usually kind of like very subtle
color that tells the user about the information that this text field expects
them to enter and that hint will automatically be
removed as soon as the user types at least one character on that text field
okay so let's go to the first text field and say
decoration and i believe it's an input decoration
and then say input decoration okay and for the hint there's so much
information on the screen we can't see anything
and there is a hint text as you can see hints text and it expects a string so in
here say please enter or just say enter your email here
and you can see it's suggesting this to be a constant so i'm going to make it a
constant and a little bit of a comma there as
well and you can see now it says enter your email here
and copy and paste this decoration as well and put it in the next text field
so say that enter your password here
so let's enter your email here enter your password here
so um
let me also make sure that that is correct there and take it in the box so
um then if you start typing in those fields
you can see that the hints disappears as soon as you type something and if you
remove that character then the hint also disappears and the same thing for the
password okay so we've now got the
groundwork like the base work done here and we need to get
through the authentication so when you press this text button here where we
need to do authentication and that means we're just going to register for now
so what you need to do is you need to import
firebase so firebase was our dependency and using the import statement you can
actually grab the content that it was created for firebase and bring it into
your source code okay so as you can see here we're gonna bring
package uh firebase off and firebase off parts okay
now command s you don't see any difference on the screen because an
import statement doesn't really change the state of your application as such
and after the importing
we need to i'm going to take it here as well that
we've talked about it so what we need to do now is to upon
pressing this button where we're going to get your
username and password from these text fields so let's say final
username or sorry email and i'm going to say the email field text
i'm going to say final password is password
text we're going to our email and password
controllers and grabbing their text which is the latest text that the user
entered in those fields okay so
after we've done that now you can go and say firebase
auth instance
and then you will say create user with email and password you can see this is a
function that allows you to register or create a
user as its name indicates uh with firebase so
um i'm gonna do that so as you can see here as well this thing returns a future
okay so um
so this is this is not nothing that you can just like call and say hey do this
now um
without actually awaiting on it otherwise it will just say here i am a
future i'm something that i will calculate something in the future and
by not putting a weight before that call you will only get the instance of future
you will not actually get the work that it's doing you will get like a wrapper
around the work saying that this is the kind of work i'm gonna do but if you
have weight on it it will actually perform the work
if that makes any sense so i've explained the weight in that chapter i
think also chapter seven or whatever it was when we talked about more advanced
topics in dart so please have a look at that chapter as well
um after doing that you will see that the return of this is actually future of
a user credential so what i'm going to do is i'm going to say final user
credential is this and then i'm going to print it user
credential okay so command s
and just hot restart here just in case because we didn't import so what i'm
going to do in enter email here i'm going to say pixelityab.gmail.com
and for the password i'm just going to say fubar
bass okay so let's bring our console up so we can
see what our application prints to the screen
and i'm just going to say register which we're going to get an error for right
now so and you can see here it says no firebase
app default has been created called firebase initialize app
so this is i mean this is really good that
we're getting this because i actually have planned for us to fix that
um but before we go ahead and do that um i should probably explain what this
is why this is happening you see firebase there was there was if you
remember when we configured it there was a file created here for us called
firebase options and it has a lot of code in it and then
there's like a configuration here uh that here you see android and for ios as
well now what firebase is complaining about is saying that you've created this
configuration but you've never actually told me about it so
poor firebase so what we need to do now before we actually do the configuration
is to fix something that you can immediately see
on the screen which is which is incorrect
you see foo bar bas is your password it shouldn't be visible to the user so when
you're typing it it should be a password field and at the same time this field
here you see is is an email field but where is the add sign at sign isn't
immediately visible here so you need to tell these text fields to be configured
in a specific way so that they're actually suitable for email and password
registration fields so i'm going to get rid of this bar on
the right oh sorry on the left and what we need to do is to bring up
the caption for the next thing for the next topic to
talk about talk about first what we're going to do is to make
this password text field
secure so
what you need to do here in your decoration of the password field go in
here and say obscure um actually it's not in the decorations right here
obscure text it has true and if you press s on that
you'll see that your text is now obscure also you need to do a
enable suggestions false and then you will also do
autocorrect false these are three important
properties to provide here now you see enable
suggestions is usually like as you're typing in a text field depending on your
operating system it will provide you suggestions like
this in a password field you don't want to do
that you don't want to have any suggestions so that's for enabled
suggestions also autocorrect is when you try to type something and you know you
all probably know what autocorrect is so i'm not going to explain it so you're
disabling autocorrect based on your password password field which makes
sense so um now let's go and bring these two properties
also to our email field which is here
okay and what we're also going to do is to
tell it that it is an email it needs an email keyboard so let's go in here and
say input or keyboard i think type and it's called
text input type i think
and then dot email there's the email address so
save it now if i then go here you can see
there's an ad sign so i can um oh sorry you can't see it so i'm going to do
this so you can actually see the that sign so you can see their keyboard here
and then there's an ad sign right there okay
so that's for that and then suggestions are
also disabled so as i type there's no suggestions really for my um text
because you don't want suggestions on email fields emails are usually like
crazy texts so um or not usually but sometimes so you
don't want any suggestions there okay we've done that i wanna take all of
these items as done in in my notes now the next thing we need to do
is uh to fix that uh initialization of our firebase app so
we're gonna do it naively right now so i'm going to go
because you see we still have this error so if i if i bring this up
clean the errors and then say
pixelity a b gmail.com and i say ubar baz
i say register we will still get this error that says no if no firebase app is
configured okay so what we need to do is to actually
register sorry initialize firebase before we do
firebase instance create user with email and password
so what we need to do then is to go here
and say firebase initialize firebase
app
see what we have there
firebase auth instance or initialize app
i've actually forgotten the syntax for that so
let's see if we actually can learn how to do that by going to our
um firebase options
initialize you can see it should be done like this
and what we need to do then is to import firebase options as it's as it's showing
here firebase options and then await firebase.initialize app with this okay
so let's let's kind of grab that code and then go into our main guard file and
import firebase options so i'm going to go here and say import
firebase options and right before we
do the
registration here i'm gonna do
this code that was provided there for us so i'm gonna remove the comments
command s and i can still see that firebase isn't imported so we're going
to import it by doing import library package firebase core firebase core here
what i did here is that i basically took advantage something that's built into
visual studio code in order for me to get the import statement automatically
so i'm going to do command dot on it and it says okay
import this dart file so i'm just gonna take advantage of that why not
and you can see that it is imported here firebase core
so now that we've done that um i'm gonna
press command s my state is preserved in the uh in my phone here and let me bring
the logs here clean them and then i'm gonna press the register button
boom uh here and we got an error here and it
says device unlock initializing all firebase apis and firebase preparing to
create blah blah and let's actually see what the error was so
it is on handle exception request failed
and unreachable host and that is probably
because i actually don't have proper internet connection on my
phone here
so i'm gonna go here and i'm gonna go to settings
actually great that you're seeing these errors because these things do happen so
and i'm gonna turn wi-fi on so make sure that it's gonna connect to
a valid wi-fi here
and it connected i'm gonna go back to the application
clear the logs oh my god there are so many things displayed there
so then what i'm gonna do is i'm gonna repeat the same thing i'm gonna say
register now so
now we got to the next state that i have prepared that it
says you can see in the errors it says configuration not found now
what is happening here i'm not taking my notes that we've talked about the other
part of the code what is happening here is that
we haven't actually told firebase that we are going to take advantage of
email and password signing combination as i told you before there are various
way for various ways for a firebase to allow us to register a user uh apple
login um you can do email and password combination you can do facebook you can
do google maybe twitter as well yeah i think
twitter was there as well so you need to tell firebase that um
we basically want to allow this combination all right
so now i've explained that let's bring up
safari or your favorite browser maybe chrome and let's go to uh console
firebase google.com i'm going to bring my browser on the screen so you can also
see it and i'm going to then find our
application which was called uh my notes flutter project okay so go
to consolefirebase.google.com and find your
project that you created in the previous chapter click on it
then go to authentication as i as i show you here
and let's see uh
authentication actually get started
and in sign in uh what we need is this email and
password combination so go email and password combination and just allow it
all right so and then press save
and that's it that's all you have to do so i'm gonna
grab this screen just kind of bring it to another
monitor so you don't see it clean the logs and then say register
so you can see now all of a sudden you got user credentials back from firebase
so you actually could now um
register your application like register a real user with firebase like that is
actually magical so i'm gonna click on my notes that i've talked about
that so
however you see this this is a little bit problematic in that by pressing the
button but we're actually initializing an application and then we're doing the
create user with email and password what would happen if you had two or three
buttons on the screen all needing firebase you can't do firebase
initialize app in every single one of them so the solution to this is kind of
like initializing your firebase application before you
start and start with everything else in your in your on your screen and on your
phone so there is good documentation of how to do
that and i've actually linked to that so i'm going to bring it here
so what we need to do is take advantage of something called widgets flutter
binding and
what happens to be honest with you here is that firebase it needs some
it needs to kick start its process before everything
else is rendered on the screen and in order for that to happen it needs to it
needs to have some sort of that like the core flutter engine to be in place
and so that it can make its call to the core slaughter engine and say that i'm
done with my work so in order to do that then you need something called um
widgets flutter binding so i'm gonna
i'm gonna bring up the um caption for that and i can show
you that i'm this is this is the documentation that i'm showing you as of
linked there so
in our in your void function here um before we actually you see
maybe i'm jumping over a little bit but what we're trying to do is to try to fix
this issue here that we're awaiting on initialize app on firebase okay so we
don't want to do this on the press of a button we actually want to do it
somewhere else and in order to be able to do that somewhere else we have to
first take care of this widget binding okay so in your main function in here
then say um i think we need to say
widgets flutter binding dot ensure initialized like that
okay and if you want to know more about that i strongly suggest that you read
this documentation that i've provided here okay
so now that that is in place um now that you've done that do a hot
restart okay so you're gonna lose your state
here after the hot restart and that's okay
i'm gonna take that in my notes that i've talked about that
now as you know this initialize
app is a future you see it's a future of firebase app now what you need to do is
kind of like you want to tell flutter to not build this column before it has
finished doing that future and
the way to do that is using flutter's future builder widget future builder it
takes a future it performs the future and once this
future has succeeded or it has failed doing its work it will give you a call
back and in that callback it asks you to actually produce a widget you want to
display to the user depending on the state
of that futures result so it basically instead of you having to do this
initialization of firebase every time a user presses the button you say i'm not
going to do anything until that is done once that is done or if it errors out
let me know then i will give you a widget to display to the user depending
on the results okay so what we're gonna do
is gonna go to this body which is a column right now command dot and then
let's see stream builder we have but we don't have future builder so i'm just
gonna say command dot wrap with widget
and i'm gonna say future builder okay so i'm gonna build a future as you can see
it says okay builder is required so let's put a
builder parameter here and if you're like me and you forget these syntaxes
you can just control space in visual studio code on mac or command space in
linux and windows to get help and then you'll just use this syntax
there okay so bring your entire column
here you see this until the end of the column without the comma
then you remove your child bring that entire thing and put a return here and
just place it there okay like that
now your future builder um it doesn't have an actual future to come to perform
so for its future
let's see i wanna say that we've talked about the future
builder
and what we need to do now is to grab this future from here you see
await firebase initialize app and grab that future without the weight remove
the weight and put it in the future builders future
parameter like that
all right command s
on a hot restart and
you can see nothing has really happened on the screen so
you didn't have any difference you don't notice any difference basically
so if everything really worked as it should
um then what we need to do then is to
um if everything is working as expected then we should be able to register users
so what i'm going to do here is i'm going to provide the exact same user
already registered and then say register and you'll see now we get an error
let's see if i can show you there and it says the error is firebase auth email
already in use the email or the email address is already in use by another
account and that is this part which i'm gonna
bring the caption up for you
so we've also talked about that
all right so
the next topic that i want to talk about before we close off and round off this
uh chapter is connection states you see
we told future builder to perform a future
the future was firebase initialize app okay this thing
now if you look at the builder what we're returning from it right now is a
column but we're completely ignoring the parameters that are coming in here
the second parameter that gets passed your builder is something called a
snapshot of data type async snapshot as you can see there
an async snapshot of an object is the state of that object right now okay
so and that object itself is actually the result of your future in this case
firebase app so it's just that
it didn't understand that this snapshot is an async snapshot of your firebase
app but that's okay we don't actually need the firebase app in the snapshot
however one thing that you do need in this snapshot is its state you see a
future has a start point it has a line where it processes its information and
it has an end point it either ends successfully or it fails now the
snapshot is your way of getting the results of your future whether it
has it started is it processing is it done or did it fail so what we need to
do in here as we're waiting for firebase initialize app to do its work we're
gonna basically say uh we're loading just tell the user loading and as soon
as the snapshot is done then we're gonna say that
loading has finished
so let's do that let's go in here and say
switch snapshot
i believe it's called
connection state all right and then get help from visual studio code to complete
this so i'm going to say add missing case clauses and you can see there are
so many different cases right
done waiting active and done all right so
for none
waiting let's let's just say everything else except for done we're gonna return
like a text that just says loading so
let's say in here we remove all of these okay
in the done statement we say return this entire column
all the way here
right and then we don't need the break because we said return and then we're
going to say default default is a special case which is not
actually inside that enumeration but is a case that says everything else that i
haven't handled and in this case we just say return text
loading something like this as a constant okay
so i'm gonna heart reload sorry hot restart and the two hours
video this is happening so fast that we're not actually seeing the loading
but at least we have handled the case that if for instance a user's connection
is too slow or their device is too slow when the future has finished they will
see this column i'm gonna actually fold it
and if this feature hasn't finished yet it's not done then they will see this
text offloading all right and by the way this is how you can actually fold and
unfold things in visual studio code so fold
fold like this unfold all right it's a great way of seeing more of your code so
wow a lot of information this this video took an hour kind of like as i expected
um so we now have a basic firebase setup
we've done our initialization of the application of our firebase we talked
about a lot of widgets actually we talked about column
column we text talked about text future builder
text field container
god app bar so many things so this is a lot of content and if you
didn't get all of it that's okay we're gonna talk more about these in the
upcoming chapters but i strongly suggest that i mean if
you're watching this course and if you're just watching it
and if you're an advanced developer and
you're watching that's completely fine but if you're if you're develop if
you're not a developer or if you're a junior developer or someone who
doesn't have so much experience with flutter development and you're really
trying to learn everything i'm saying here please don't just watch this video
go and do this yourself go and write this code pause the video as i'm talking
i know i'll talk a little bit fast but that's just to save a little bit of time
pause the video write the code as i write it test it as i test it and see
the results for yourself because that's how you will learn not just by watching
so great we've talked a lot about
widgets and firebase configuration and in the next chapter we're going to
talk about login screen and also email verification and also clean up our
registration screen so without further ado let's just prepare yourself for the
next chapter and i'll see you there hello and welcome to chapter 13 of this
flutter course in this chapter we're going to talk
about the login view in chapter 12 as i can see here
sorry about that we talked about the registration flow and
we actually talked about quite a lot of things which after after that i i
thought maybe we need to kind of like go through them one more time just
every now and then talk about those those little widgets that we talked
about like a future builder center column text button and we talked also
about um text field text editing controller so
there were lots of components that we talked about but we got pretty much like
a a simple registration flow working it
wasn't really a flow actually it was just a simple registration screen
i'm saying that it wasn't a flow because it was just a simple screen that didn't
lean anywhere that's usually what is called the flow if you have a screen
that leads somewhere now in this chapter we're going to talk
about login the login view and we're also going to divide the logic that
we've created in our current home page and put it into a registration view so
we're by the end of this chapter we're gonna have two views one is for the
registration the other one is for the login okay
so as i've shown you here um we have those logic i mean the
registration logic in place now we have to work on login but we also work a
little bit on cleaning up the code because
usually this i mean as you get more and more comfortable with software
development you'll know that you will have like these flows of ideas
and then you'll start coding and write your code and then you test it and then
after a while you realize oh this got a little bit messy i have to refactor the
code so that's what refactoring kind of means like you take what is already
there and you kind of make it better make it cleaner more presentable so
that's what we're also going to do in this chapter
so the first thing we need to do is to create a stateful register view widget
okay so as you can see here this will be used
as the base of our register view
so let me go and bring some stuff that
we're going to need in this chapter the first one is my scr
i bring it to the screen so you'll see it as well
and scr cpy we set it up in one of the previous chapters so you should be
comfortable with that already um
i'm going to go to go to our app here which is the register view that we
created gonna bring my face to the right so we'll see a bit more of the content
on the screen and then i'm also going to bring up
visual studio code which is appearing on another screen right now but i'll bring
it up here so you'll see as well i'm going to increase the size a little
bit as well so it becomes easier to see
so this is where we lift things um let me bring up
and do the screen like this so this is where we live things we have a home page
which at the moment is the register view okay but we need to create a register
view like not just a home page it's called the home page so
and since we need a stateful widget we're going to use a shortcut in visual
studio code to create a stateful widget for us and that is with s t f as in
state full so if you want to create a stateless widget you'd say stl okay
so stf and in here we're going to call it what
should we say register view like that all right
so this will be as i've mentioned here this
will be the base of our
this will be the base of our registration view all the code for
register will appear here i'm sorry that i'm looking
here just to make sure that i'm basically
going through my notes i have very detailed notes here and just making sure
that you get all the information that i plan for you to get so if you see me
looking here it's just because i'm looking at the notes to ensure that
um so now that we've created register view at the moment it doesn't have
anything so it's just a container and the default color for containers and
background is black so let's go to our register view here
so let's go to our main function here and as you can see at the moment we're
returning home page as the home and what we're going to do here is just to say
instead of that return register view okay
and that is it's very possible we will get a problem here and you can see
nothing is changing because i'm changing something inside the main and that isn't
affected really by a hot reload so we have to hot restart so i'm gonna
go how to restart here and you can see now the screen is black
so um
that part is basically done
so what we'll have to do here now is to rename our home page to our login view
actually so we have a new registration view which we're going to write the code
for or actually place the code from the previous home page into register view
and we also need the home page to be renamed so it's very some i mean there's
lots of renaming putting things here and there but we're just playing with some
names basically here so the next thing you need to do is to go
to your home page which is here and rename it one way to do that visual
studio code is to right click on it and just say rename symbol or i believe it's
also command f2
or actually for me it's f2 if two does the renaming but on a macbook pro for
instance you don't you can't just press f2 because f2 has another function
so what you'll need to do is to press function keyboard keep key on your
keyboard and then press f2 that will bring up the rename dialog or you could
just right click here and just say rename symbol which does the same thing
so rename your home page to login view okay
all right so we have login view here now um i'm gonna take it that we've done the
rename um you see
right now all we've been doing here is just to like write our code write
everything in main dart but this is this is not a not the right way of doing
things especially as your projects get bigger you need to make sure that you're
you're taking the responsibility to also make sure that your code is readable and
the structure of your project is understandable by others who may also be
working on the same project now chances are that if you're watching this course
that you will be the only person working on the source code so you won't have
anybody else looking at your code even though
that you may be the only person looking at the code and working with it you
still will need to from time and time come back to the project fix some stuff
add some stuff remove some stuff so even if you're the only person working
with it you will need a clean source code to look at so if you come
back to the source code after a month and you start to add more and more stuff
to this main dart file after a while it will just get out of control so
you'll need to also do refactoring on your code just to ensure that it is in a
clean state so what we're going to do is to bring up
our project browser here as you can see we're inside lib and then
there's a file called main dart what we need to do here is
to move our login view into its own file and you can see here i've written that
we're going to move it into lib views login view this file doesn't exist at
the moment so you'll need to create it what you'll do here i mean in visual
studio code there's a great trick that you can do that it can create a file on
all the intermediate folders as well so instead of going here
and say new folder to create this views folder and then inside there i create a
login view what you'll need to do just say new file
and then type the entire path in there so just say
views and then slash login view dot dart and this will create the views folder
for you so it's great um
so what i'll need to do here is to take our login views code as you can see
here
as we had here class login view and then bring all that code into this new login
view file that we just created okay so i'm gonna get this out of the way
here and just paste it
all right and that's okay we're getting a lot of errors here and the reason
behind that is i mean we haven't talked about import statements so much before
but import statement is a way for you as a programmer to bring
in code written by others whether it is the flutter team at google
or whether it is a third party third-party dependency
and tell your flutter
project where those pieces of code are and at
the moment i mean if you're not coming from a
software engineering background you're not familiar with imports
this is um i mean the closest analogy that i can find is
as if for instance in figma you've created
um you're trying to create an instance of a
design that you've already created but figment doesn't know where that instance
is so you'll say oh here's a copy of the button instance
and then figma is like oh where can i find that button you haven't even
created it so then you need to first go create that button or drag it in from
another project and put it in your components
page and then you can create an instance of it so
if you're not into design and figma you may not understand what i just
said but what i'm trying to do is just to be as
inclusive as possible in this course to make sure anybody who's following this
course will try to at least understand bits and
pieces of what i'm saying so
going back to import what we need to do now is to tell flutter where those
pieces of highlighted code are and one thing to do in visual studio code which
can help you greatly if you're trying to go around this
writing things by hand is just to do command on mac or control on linux and
windows hold down command or control depending on your operating system and
press dot then you will see suggestions here as
where those components those missing components may be placed and what you'll
need to do here is just to import package flutter material because that's
where these components that we're using are actually placed so oops
i managed to click the wrong wrong option there so material boom
all right i think now almost everything has disappeared all almost every error
has disappeared except for these firebase errors so
let's go and let's see
so let's go in there
and say now firebase core import that
and also here we need to import minors firebase options okay
so i think everything basically is disappeared there's also firebase auth
import that as well alright so we're good to go now on this
login view however remember this login views code really is not
login view i mean if you remember the code that we've written in the previous
chapter this login view at the moment it says
log view but all it does is register do you remember that we have the text field
and even the button that says register so
what we need to do now is to drag the code as you can see here from
the login view here we need to kind of bring it into the
register view okay and our register view at the moment is here you see
there so let's go and try to do that a little
bit with care okay so grab all this code that is here in the login view here
there get dispose in its state
and also grab your email and password and member variables
from here and cut them
so i'm gonna go then in here in the register view state
then paste those right before the build function so there we go okay
go back to login view dart and you can see that there is a build function here
here and
i'm going to literally just grab that entire build function including the
override and
as i can see here the build function ends right there and i'm gonna cut that
also okay and i'm gonna go here and replace this override on the um
on the what is it called register view and paste that one from before here okay
so what all we did here is we made sure that the register view
it is indeed the register view and the login view is empty at the moment so
what you'll need to do you see there's an error here that says that okay you
have a stateful widget for login but it doesn't have any build function
so you'll now need to create that build function and of course you could do it
by hand
but it's i mean
it's not really it's not really that
good of an idea to
write all that code by hand of course in the beginning you may say that oh well i
just want to learn the best way to learn is to type and i completely understand
that but there are some things like there are limits i also believe like
once you've done it once or twice you'll kind of get bored of doing that or
you'll get tired of doing that so i actually suggest that for these
functions that you're overriding the best way is actually get your editor
text editor or ide to complete these things for you so i'm going to go on
this error and just say command dot on mac and control dot on linux and windows
and say create one missing override okay and in here we just say return
okay so that's our login view and you can see
here now we have
a register view that is right here and then we also have
a login view all right
so let's go then
in our main dart file here i can see that there is a register and let's just
actually restart this hot restart okay so we have a register
and our login view is completely empty so
now um what we need to do basically is kind of
like um
it's kind of work on our login view because this is this is like the goal of
this chapter we need to have a login view and up
until this point what we've been doing is kind of like create a register view
with all the code in it a separate login view
which was our previously previously created registry so
i mean this is all a lot of talk just to say that we have a registered view
but we don't have a login view and we need to work on login views so
if you remember um wow i mean you don't actually have to
remember you can look at it here the register view has two fields enter your
email here and for your password here and
this is this their register v and login are very similar to each other what
register view does differently is that it creates this it basically does a call
to firebase that says create user with email and password
but if you think about it everything else is very similar
sorry about that so you need to create you need to make
sure in both of them that firebase is initialized
you will have two text fields email password and you will have a button one
for register and for one for login so
what we could do to be honest with you is to now go and copy this code that we
got from our login view okay that happens i actually forgot that
so let's go and copy this code again from here
literally get grab everything from there and put it in our login view like that
and change this register button to log in
so now we have two copies of the same view basically once it's registered the
other one says log in all right so
and what we could do is now go to our main dart file here
and instead of returning the register view we could just return the login view
because we want to work on the login view now okay we have a user registered
and now we need to work on login and as a side note
if you follow the previous chapter you'll you'll know that we actually did
register a a valid user with firebase and
what you could do is to go to your firebase console
as we could do now just an ad hoc i hadn't planned for this
but what we could do say console.firebasegoggle.com
ensure that you're logged in with your account
then i'm going to go to this uh project that we created mynotes flutter project
go in there and then go into authentication and you can actually then
see the user that you created using the flutter application that
you're actually working on so when you call this function in your in your
register view this function firebase os instance create user with
email and password that user was indeed created in the firebase console so here
you have a user you could also disable this user and do other things but we're
just going to leave it like that for now okay
so what you need to do now is instead of register view tell your home page to
render the login view and you could just type login view
and if you just type a login view like that you will get
an error of course because login view isn't in scope but i believe visual
studio code could actually help with that because you see we haven't imported
login view at all so this main dart file doesn't know what
login view is exactly the same thing happened here do
you remember if we didn't have these imports we got lots of errors saying
that they i don't know where this class is so the same thing is happening in
this main dart file all right so i believe in visual studio code now i'm
kind of improvising but i think if you set login view and just press enter boom
it does an import automatically for you and let's see where it is here you see
but if you're not comfortable doing that just type login view
by hand and do the same thing i showed you before just command dot on mac or
controlled up in windows and linux and say import okay so it's going to import
it for you now we have the login view and if i
press command s or actually we have to do a hot restart
you see now there is a login button right here okay
so what we'll need to do is as you can see in the caption now that we're
working on logging the login view go to your login view
and go here where the button is pressed you see text button unpressed
what we'll need to do here is to call the a new function on our firebase
auth instance instead of create user with email and password we're going to
say firebase auth got instance
but sign in with email and password and you can see the function signature is
very similar to create user with email and password in that it takes two
parameters namely email and password both of type string and then what it
does return in fact is user credential and do you remember create user with
email and password also return user credentials so
it's very simple to switch between login and register in that in that sense so
grab the sign in with email and password name
that's the only thing we're interested in and just paste it here instead of
create user okay just gonna save that
some reason my scrcpy crashed and i have no idea why
so that's okay that wasn't planned what we
could do is to go to our and i can see you see it got an aborted so what we
could do is to go to our terminal and i'm gonna say scr cpy okay
and i'm going to bring it to the screen here so
and also if you're if you noticed here we have a login button but the title
here still says register so let's go and fix that let's go into the app bar and
just say login all right
and actually problem is i can also see that my
as scrcpy crash also the running of this process this application on that android
phone also crashed so there is i mean the flutter instance of this project
isn't really running at the moment so what i'll have to do is to go to main
dart and say run without debugging so and it's now launching doing a gradle
build gradle remember from the previous chapters is for android
and if it's using xcode it is for ios all right so
it's doing the greater build so if everything goes according to the plan
then we should get a login title up there and while this is doing
its work i'm going to go to my notes and just ensure
that i've talked about the things that i promise i'm going to talk
about all right it's installing our application i'm gonna remove the widget
inspector and now you can see we have a login
on top and that is working as expected all right so
as you can see here after the logging call here sign in with email and
password we're doing a print now
what we could do here is to enter some information of a user that
doesn't exist okay so i'm just going to say my personal email
and i'm going to say foo bar path and i'm then going to bring up the
console here as you'll see the debug console clear it
um and i'm going to actually remove
or do something like this so you can see the debug console a little bit better in
its entirety and i'm going to press the login button all right
and then sorry about that
so we have now um the next thing that we need to handle as
you can see uh
i'll perhaps increase the size even more here so you'll see it better
when i press the login button excuse me
using a user
that doesn't exist meaning that we haven't registered that user then we got
an error here that says firebase off user not found and that that makes sense
actually completely because the
we haven't actually done any registration for this user okay
so what we could hear what we could do here
is to go in here and i'm gonna bring things back up
kind of the way they were here
all right so here we're recalling this function uh
let me decrease the size because it's absolutely ginormous
in here signing with email and password
um we need to handle
a thing called an exception and i don't think we talked about exceptions to be
honest with you while i was i was teaching you about dart if you know
about exceptions you could just skip through kind of skim through this little
bit of the video but if you're if you're not a software development developer
from before or software engineer then you may not know what an exception is an
exception is when things go wrong and you haven't kind of
thought about those things from the beginning so as you can as you
for instance if you're if you're working with
if you're a software if you're a designer or a product owner
haven't done software development before you may have also used other pieces of
software and sometimes software crashes just like scr cpy just crashed a few
minutes ago that is perhaps probably
an exception or an error that the software developers who created scrcpy
hadn't counted with so they hadn't counted with
that an error might occur in this scenario
for instance so not having handled that the application
crashes it means that an exception happens and error happens that the
developers of that program hadn't accounted for so
and this is an exception that you're seeing here in your flutter application
so firebase is saying that you're trying to log in with a user that doesn't exist
so what do you want to do with it i can't continue after this i don't know
what to do so the way to handle exceptions in
flutter or in dart actually is using a try catch block so i'm going to bring it
here put the entire code for your user credential creation in the try statement
as you can see here and then go in here and say catch b
in parenthesis for now all right just like that
and then i'm just gonna say something that happened
in single codes all right so you can see here now we
have a try block as indicated here with this line it's all the way from on top
to here and then we have a catch block the way try catch works is that it as
its name indicates it tries to do the work that you're saying it needs to be
done in the trial block should anything bad happen it will go to various catch
statements that you can't then place after that try okay
so as you saw in the logs this error
let's see if we can find it here it was of type firebase auth uh let me
see on handle exception but we didn't actually get its type unfortunately so
what we could do here is print something bad happen and then
print the error itself okay so i'm just going to say clear the logs
command s and then i'm going to press the login
again sorry here and you can see now it says
something bad happened firebase auth user not found and then some information
and we could actually say print e
run time type and doing that will actually give you information about
which class of exception this is because you see
as you're working with flutter and as you're working with software generally
you're creating software you're writing code different types of exceptions
happen and these exceptions have their own identity every exception has its own
identity it's the series of classes or different places that it may come from
in dart you can pretty much anything can become an error even a text
can become an error or enum can become an error so
when you come to this catch block as i'll move my mouse over it you can see
that here it says i don't even know what this is this is an object so
it could be anything but you are actually in the in your
cache block you're mostly interested in exceptions that might occur from
firebase so since we don't really know what this
type is we're gonna print it out to the console
and we're gonna have a look at what type it is so let me do
a little bit of them how should i do this
is this a little bit better arrangement perhaps so you can see what happens yeah
perhaps then what i'm going to do command this hot reload
and go here press the login button and you'll see that the type of that
exception is firebase auth exception all right
so what we need to do now is to go to our code
and handle
firebase auth exceptions not just any exception as we're doing here
because we're catching any exception so what we want to do is to catch firebase
off exceptions in our cache block all right and a way to do that is i'm going
to do this now and i'm going to do like we were doing
before get rid of the consoles to see more of the code
so what you could do you can have specialized cache blocks in dart and
that means that you are not catching everything but you tell dark that look
in this particular catch block i'm interested only in exceptions of this
type and as you might have guessed that already a
try block can be accompanied by more than one catch block
this cache block that you can see here is called catch all it catches every
exception that might occur in the running of the code inside the try block
however if you're interested in specific
exceptions in this case firebase auth exception i believe oh i've cleared it
but i think it was firebase off exception i'm going to run it again
go to the login button and you can see it says firebase off exception so we're
interested specifically in that so let's go and say tell dart that we're
interested in that i'm just i'm going to say on
firebase off exception catch
e all right
so this is the format of catching specific exceptions you prefix your
catch statement with the keyword on and then you write the type the runtime type
or the class name of the type of exception that you're interested in
handling all right so in this case we said on firebase off
the exception catchy and we're gonna remove this catch from there
and we're gonna go here actually i don't even have to cut and
what you'll need to do in here just say print e code
you see save this before i before i tell you
what i was going to say after uc let's test this let's say login and
you'll see that the code is used or not found
so now that we told dark that we're
specializing in catching exceptions of firebase auth exception then this e is
not an object anymore really let's see if we can get some help now it says okay
if i can catch exceptions of firebase auth exception then i know that the
error that i can pass to you is of that type
now that you catching firebase authexception you can go to this code
and you see there are different properties that you can read from
message code email credential et cetera et cetera okay
so we're now interested in the code so
as the caption right here shows at the bottom of the screen you'll see that we
need to handle e-code equal to user not found all right so let's say if e code
is equal to user not found then let's say print
user not found like that else e code oh sorry actually we're not going to do it
outside kind of like running ahead of myself a little bit there
so we have now um
e-code user not found then we're just saying print user not found okay i'm
going to clear the logs here go back to see our cpy here and i'm just gonna say
login and you'll see all it does it says user not found all right
so so that's that we haven't really i mean
the caption at the bottom left of the screen says handle but depending on your
um background you may expect handle to do different things for
a software for a seasoned software engineer handle may actually mean that
well do something about it okay tell him tell the user like oh i couldn't log in
the user couldn't be found or whatever reason just show something to
the user and we could do that but at the moment we don't have the capacity to do
that we don't really know how to handle that so
what we need to do then is to simply say print so we just print it to the screen
so this is our handling for now okay it's very simple all it does is just
ensures that no exception is thrown to the user's face or that the application
doesn't crash
okay that was a lot of information um now as the caption here shows in the
login view we also need to handle wrong password
and i mean as you can see here the e code is a string so anything here could
happen that could be defined by string and one other
excuse me one of those errors actually is wrong
password so let's test that in here let's say else if if the code is
not user not found just print something else happened
and then print the errors code to the screen okay
so i'm going to save this and i'm going to then go here and then
actually change this email to an existing email which was the one that i
registered and password i believe was foobar or
something clickfu bar maybe
and i'm going to say login and you can see here it says now something else
happened wrong password so that could that could kind of mean that
well yeah actually that isn't my password this foo bar was in my password
i don't even remember what it was maybe it was full bar bass
but that is great it says something else happen an e code and that's exactly what
we have to sorry about that
and that is exactly what we need to handle here um wrong password so in your
else statement say else if e code
is wrong password
then we're going to say print wrong password
okay man is
so that's there clear the logs i'm going to say log in and you'll see the message
wrong password printed to the screen
all right a lot of work
we've done quite a lot of work now in the login view but we haven't really put
much energy into the register view you see they're very similar in that they do
almost the same api calls with the email and password ones that sign in the other
ones that's register however in if if we go to our main dart
file you'll see in here in our register view we're just calling the api and kind
of like hoping for the best there's no try catch statement here okay so what we
could do is have a look at how we did it for login we put the api call inside the
try block you see what we need to do is to go to main dart and for our register
view here register view state do the same
thing let's put this in a try block here
okay and then just say catch or say on
firebase off exception
this is i mean i'm not going to explain this again because it's exactly what we
did just in the login view i believe firebase authexception didn't
really exist in this in this dart file before but that is what visual studio
code helped me with as i typed it and pressed enter for auto completion
then it must have been imported somewhere
or it was probably part of firebase auth dart i believe actually so if i command
click on it it goes to firebase auth so that's why i
it probably didn't have to import anything because it was already imported
as a part of firebase auth okay
oh wow that was a lot of information also
now that we're working on the register view let's go to our main
dar main function here and since we're only seeing the login view let's switch
this back to register view and command s but this is not going to
change anything as you remember hot reload doesn't have an effect of any
changes that you it doesn't have an effect on anything that you're changing
the main function remember that you have to hot restart okay
so hot restart now we're in the register view
and we need to now handle wrong password uh actually
no that's not the login sorry about that now we need to handle
this weak password so
as you're working with uh firebase zoom you will notice that it has its own set
of security rules you also can override these security rules later for your
server if you want to for instance you can expect or you can say all my users
have to have passwords that are 18 um characters long and a mixture of digits
and alpha numerical values etcetera etcetera but
there are some default security rules set up on firebase
for credentials that every user needs to abide by so let's actually have a look
at that and let's
do a print here and i'm going to say print e
code okay and as you'll see in the caption as you
are seeing in the caption there is an e code of equal to weak password that
needs to be handled so i'm going to go here try to register user with my
personal email and the password of a b c all right then i'm going to bring up
the console clear the console a little bit
i'm going to do this so you'll see it a little bit better
then i'm gonna try to register with a password of abc press register
what happened here you see the code was weak password
and as you'll expect yeah weak password that is too weak a password to even be
used anywhere so um
so what we need to do here is to handle the weak password
error basically i'm gonna take in my notes that i've talked about some other
topics of login all right so we'll handle weak password
the way we handle the other errors in login view
then say if e code is equal to
weak password
and let's just say print week password okay
and we'll say um so that's that's that for now okay
and i'm going to just bring up the um debug console again
and press the register button one more time
now you'll see the information let me bring it so you can actually see it
yeah you can actually see it great you can see weak password being printed here
all right so that was great now let's go let me bring the let make
the screen a little bit bigger the next thing we have to handle
is um in this register view as you can see in the caption here
you can also get an error called email already in use so if you go to the else
statement here again and print e
if i try to register with the same email that i registered before
this user already exists and if even if i have quite a good password for this
user so i'm going to say fubar bass
1029. so we know that the error is not going
to be the password like it's actually a good password well
better than fubar baz at least and that or abc so i'm just going to say register
and
do we not get any value here or did i even press the register button
is it really registering pixelity a b
no i don't think so um
oh i hadn't saved the file oops so yeah i haven't saved my changes i'm gonna say
register oh now it says email already in use and
that is exactly i mean that is pretty much what we have to handle right
because we're printing e so um i didn't have to say oh no surprises
there so let's handle email already and use so
i'm going to copy this email already and use string just exactly as it's
mentioned here and i'm going to go to else and say
else if e code is equal to that string and then say uh email is
already in use okay
and then save it there clear the logs press the register button
again you can see now it says email is already in use okay
so um
let me also have a little bit of a look at my notes
um
i can also i mean to be honest with you in the notes i don't see anywhere
that we're really trying to handle uh these errors like actually doing
something about them all right so
perhaps a better thing to do would be
to really like show a message or something to the user
and i'm kind of wondering that right now like whether that's a good idea or a bad
idea for this chapter and perhaps just doing a print will suffice to be honest
with you not entirely sure about that so
um let's leave it at that for now okay i'm also gonna go here and make sure
that i'm not yeah i'm in do not disturb so let's leave it leave it at that email
already use perfect okay let's leave it at that
now the next thing that we have to handle
it could also write a situation where the user tries to enter an invalid email
all right so let's put an else statement here and say print
um e code again save it
let's go and remove this add sign so it becomes an invalid email and try to
press the register button okay now you can see uh you can't actually see now
you can see at the bottom in the logs it says invalid email and that is the code
for that error so let's handle invalid email now all right
so i'm going to go here and say else if e code we call to invalid email then
we're going to say print invalid email entered all right and save it
so clear the logs tap the register button and now you'll
see invalid email entered okay so
i mean that's really um all we have to do
right now for our error handling and as we're going on i
mean to be honest with you i still have a little bit of time to figure out
whether we're really going to handle these things by and by that i mean like
if we are if we need to display some some error to
the user okay and we may need to do that but it is a little bit complicated like
depending on how we want to handle it do we want to show like a message to the
user do you want to show a toast to the user um
or do we want to like display another screen to the user and that's kind of
like unclear even to me right now so maybe we'll iron these things out then
as we go on in in the upcoming chapters as well
so
now i can see here that login
we've talked about that and what we need to do then
in order to be able to carry on with the upcoming chapters
is actually to make sure that we are logged in to the application you see
we've worked on the register view we've worked on the login view
we're trying like so many different combinations here to register new user
login so i personally don't know at the moment whether
this application firebase instance actually has a logged in user and if
you're familiar with like python django or flask or if you're doing nodejs or
whatever development like backend development
you can be a logged in user but still end up being in a login view
so if you send a login login user to a login view doesn't mean that the user
isn't logged in instead it means well that user is
logged in but may want to log in as a different user so that is the case in
our application as well we have a register screen a login view but i
personally don't know what the state of the application at the moment is are we
logged in or are we not logged in because we're kind of like playing with
different views here okay so that's very important now because in the
next chapter i can see in chapter 14 we are going to work with
um we're working on separating the app
initialization from the login and register screens because you can see at
the moment we have this future builder that is
initializing firebase and it is doing lots of work comes with snapshots stay
done blah blah and we're doing the exact same thing in two views login view and
the register view so what we need to do is kind of like
separate that logic and ensure that we display the correct
view depending on yeah what the state of the application is and before we can
then continue or start that chapter we kind of need to make sure that the user
the current user is logged in all right so let's go to our um
main dart here and login logged in views already displayed so i don't really you
don't need to worry about this part import login view
what you need to do now is to make sure that instead of register view we're
displaying the login view and remember now we're saving something
changing something in the main function so hot reload isn't going to
work so you need to do hot restart so we'll get to that login view
and let's then enter valid details here so i'm going to say pixelityab.gmail.com
and i think the password was fubar best to be honest
i'm going to press the login button all right and there we got the
credentials for this user wow that was a lot of information and i
understand that um so what we need to work on now i'm going
to take some stuff in my notes is
as i mentioned we need to for the next chapter i mean we're kind of done with
this chapter to be honest we've talked a lot about like exception handling
separated the login view from the register view but our register view is
still in the main dart we're gonna we're gonna
fix that soon but what you need to know to do before
you continue with the next chapter and just ensure that you're displaying the
login view to the user and that you're actually logging logging in with a valid
username and password this ensures that the firebase instance that is running in
this application right now is going to cache that information locally on ios is
going to cache that information in a secure storage called keychain and on
android i think it's called shared preferences or something like that
so that information is going to be securely stored now on that telephone
which for me is an android telephone right here and
when i restart the application whenever if i like shut down my
telephone restart the telephone the os come back up that information is already
saved on that telephone so my user is logged in all right
so just ensure that before you continue with the next chapter that you've
registered the user first and that you've logged in with that user from
your application so that information is cached inside the application all right
good a lot of information in the next chapter
we're going to separate the app initialization from the login and the
register screens there are only a few steps that we have to do
in that chapter so
so i don't think that chapter is going to actually be so long
so grab a cup of tea coffee whatever you want chocolate or whatever it is and
i will see you in the next chapter hello and welcome to chapter number 14
of our flutter course as you saw in the previous chapter we
worked on the login view now we have a login view and a register view in place
and what you also saw is that we did some very simple
error handling for various scenarios such as
uh email address already registered weak password um
invalid email incorrect password or wrong password i
think it was called so now we have two views in place
um we have but we have two main issues to address here
the registration or the register view that
we created still lives in our
main.dart file and the other issue is as the caption
here displays is that the widgets are doing app initialization
if you remember from the code there was this firebase initialization
api invocation that we had to do and since
the login view and the register view are very similar to each other they're both
doing the initialization of firebase
what we're going to do in this chapter is
separate these um initializations and
make them one that's that's the first first thing we need to do so we just
have one initialization that's going to happen
and what we're also going to do is to bring the register view in its own file
so this this chapter is going to be a quick one unlike the other chapters and
i think that's kind of refreshing to be honest with you otherwise all chapters
are going to be very long and very detailed
so with that said let's then um
let's then start with the first thing we have to do
which is basically to move the register view into
views register view okay i'm going to see if i can bring up
visual studio code um how we had left it before
and i'm going to bring up scrcpy which
is my android phone running our flutter application right now
so let's do as the caption says here i'm going to make the screen a little bit
bigger so you can see better then go to your project uh or explorer
here visual studio core if you're using android studio you can go go to the
navigator there as well there's a similar one in android studio or if
you're using sublime that is exactly the same thing here on the left hand side
you can see the project structure then go to lib and then views as we have
the login view there let's create a view called register view so right click here
and say new file and i'm going to say register mu dot dart
okay so then we have to as the question says go back to our main dart file and
grab this register view from here group all the register view including
its register view state grab all of that
cut it in mac you do it with command x and in windows and linux i think you do
control x so um i cut that and i'm gonna then bring
it into register view here as you saw in the previous chapter doing
these things usually cause a lot of headache
for for your editor because i mean it's not
a headache for you because we can easily fix it for us it's not a problem but
it's just the editor that doesn't understand where all these classes are
located at so i i've explained this previously in
the exact previous chapter before this so i'm not going to explain it again so
let's say command dot in visual studio code and then say import material to fix
all the stateful widget problems and all the things that all the classes are
stored in material dart here in the flotter package okay
then we have other problems such as firebase so
command dot import firebase core to fix that command dot import firebase options
here it's that problem and we will also have
to import firebase off i believe and that is also fixed all right so now we
have a register view here perfect and um
if you see here in our main dart now there are lots of things that are
imported which aren't which aren't needed anymore
so let's remove those you can see these things are actually
you may say okay well how do i find all these problems like there's lots of
issues here but had i not come back to the main dart file i wouldn't have seen
them and the way to fix that is to actually bring up your
problems view here and you'll see that there are lots of problems stated that
you can go go and fix those you see print statements are here and then
unused imports which you can which you can clean up as well so
that's how you can use the problems window
i'm going to do that by hand now remove this and remove this so we have a clean
void main function here all right i'm gonna do a hot restart just to make sure
everything's working as expected then we have the login view here okay
so the next thing we need to do now is as the notes i'm actually going to go to
my notes and make sure that i have talked about the previous point
so the next thing we need to do is to create a dedicated home page that does
the app initialization and depending on whether the user is logged in or logged
out or if the user is verified or not then it's going to display the correct
widget on the screen okay so just to explain that a little bit more
is that i mean you i can say that you see in your main function here that
when your application run you it runs you're telling it to go to login view
but why why are we saying go to login view
why are we saying go to register view we have no logic at the moment that says
are you logged in then show the login view or if you're not like me and show
the registry so that's what we're going to do with our
home page okay so imagine the home page kind of being the manager of the
different routes that your application can manage so saying that oh if this
condition then do this if that condition display the other screen so
we need a home page and conveniently named is home page i mean lots of other
people may try to call it something else like a route page or whatever
but for now we're going to go with homepage because it's just so easy to
understand for everyone so let's then go in here
and say we want to have a stateless widget stl and we're going
to call it home page okay and i'm gonna press escape after that so now we have a
stateless widget called home page in our main dart file
now what we need to do then after doing that
we need to go in our main dart file and instead of saying login view let's just
say home page okay and if i press command is remember this is not going to
take any effect immediately because hot reload doesn't take into consideration
it changes the main function here so you have to do a hot restart so you'll see
black screen right now okay so
that's that
so what we need to do now is
to basically have some scaffold in our
homepage because we don't want to display just an empty screen to the user
okay so
let's go in here for our container instead say we return a scaffold
talked about scaffold in previous chapters so i'm not going to explain
that again and let's go and create an app bar with
which we've also talked about title accounts text and say home page
okay
well command s in mac or control s in linux and windows to save this file and
you'll see the changes took effect immediately
all right so what do we need in the home page we said
that the home page needs to initialize firebase it needs to first do that so
that we can get rid of this code in both register view you see this code future
builder firebase initialize app and then connection state done blah blah and also
we have the exact same code in our login view so
there's a lot of code to write in every view that we're gonna develop though
this application isn't gonna have so many views maybe six seven views but
still we don't wanna do initialize app in every view and do a future builder
it's just a lot of code so that's what our
homepage is gonna do okay so let's do that uh let's go and grab
this code um excuse me
let's grab this code with the future builder pretty much maybe the entire
build function okay from our login view so go to your login view grab the entire
build function until its end which is here this parenthesis okay ending
parenthesis close your login view close your
register view if you want to then go and replace the entire override of widget
build in your home page with that code that you just cut or
sorry copied from the login view paste it right here
now we we don't want the home page to have any logic that has anything to do
with um
text fields this homepage is we're going to use it for something a lot more noble
so you don't need all the text fields and
and all of these columns and uh your text
button so go to here where you're creating the
column in connection state done and grab that code all the way from
return so if i fold it you'll see that that is the entire return and i'm going
to actually delete it oops it didn't delete the entire code
okay so i'm going to do it by hand from the return
all the way down here to where the
column ends okay
and instead of that column what we're gonna do
is just return a text that says
okay just like that so if firebase
initialization is done it's just gonna say done and let's also change the text
here and just call it home all right now that we've done that you can see we
still have some problems with firebase not being imported because i deleted
those um um
imports previously so i'm gonna fix that now command dot on firebase and say
import that and command dot on default firebase options or control dot
depending on whether on your linux whether if you're on linux or a mac or
windows import firebase options
all right so now you'll see we have a homepage that just displays the word
done here once the connection state of our future
which is initialized app of firebase is actually done so hot reload
and you'll see hotdog sorry done is also displayed hot done
um so uh
i'm gonna take that in my notes that i've talked about that
all right the next thing we need to do in this
chapter is um to make sure that the user is not null
and that also the user is verified so under some rare circumstances with
firebase such as when you haven't initialized your firebase application
using initialize app the user that is stored in the firebase um
firebase code or in the instance of firebits
running inside your application may actually be null and we've talked about
null in uh previous chapters where we talked about dart and it's basics so you
can go back to those chapters and watch those so i'm not going to explain what
null is again but just quickly null is simply said the
absence of a value in this case absence of the user so
what we need to do in our application is to ensure
that a
the user the current user in the application is
um non-null meaning that it should be present and also that the user's email
should be verified okay so
you may be asking why is it important for a user's email to be
verified the reason
i mean also before i say why is it important for a user's email to be
verified maybe let's talk first about what an email verification is and
that whether you've already seen it or not so in a lot of services online if
for instance you go to a website even if it's a shopping website or
amazon or whatever ebay if you say okay i want to register a new user and you
say okay here's my email address here's a password of my choosing um
once you do that you will be logged into the website
they'll say okay if this email doesn't exist already
i'm gonna allow you to register this but then you wouldn't really be able to do
so much with the website you can search stuff but you probably won't be able to
buy things unless until unless you've
verified your email and that means that as soon as you register for amazon for
instance then it will send you an email to the email that that you chose upon
registration and there will usually be a link in that email and say thank you for
registering a user at amazon or ebay click on this link to verify your email
address you've probably seen emails like that so
you could just go to your inbox and search for verify and you'll probably
find lots of emails that ask you verify your account with the service so um
now let's now that we talked about what email verification is let's talk about
why it's important well let's say that i'm a user and i want to use this
application that we're developing so i want to score some notes in it
then i'll go and and register myself under an email that i don't own
all right so let's say then i register my
your email address with a password of my choosing since you haven't registered
your email address yet with the service icon and ahead of you and register your
email address with the service and now i'll just log in
remember i'm not logging into your email i'm logging into this application with
your email now now i've taken that email so if you then
who's the rightful owner of your email address comes to this application and
say oh i'm a foobarbaz gmail.com and i want to register an account with this
application and it says oops that email address was already taken so you'd be
like how is that taken that's my email address so
that is the importance of email verification what we need to do in our
application is to make sure that whenever someone comes and registers a
user using the email address and a password of their choosing then we're
gonna send a real email using firebase to that email address and say
hey you just registered a user here make sure that you click on this link that
says verify blah blah to actually verify your user with our application or with
our file with our applications firebase instance that sits on firebase cloud all
right so so what we need to do now is to go in
here in the connection state done you see
let's then check the current user okay let's see if this current user actually
is logged into the application so let's say firebase
um and then let's say
firebase app i believe it's called instance
let's see got instance
changelog firebase all right let's see if we can actually
google that together okay so this is good for you to also see
right base flutter get current user we're probably going to end up on some
sort of a stack overflow and we'll have a look at how we can
actually retrieve the current user as you can see the response here is from a
user whose username is quite
dissu kurt jr i apologize if i'm butching this name but you can see that
it's provided here for you that it says firebaseos.instance
and using that instance then you can get the current user so let's do the same
thing here let's say firebase off dot instance
and then current user okay
i'm gonna get rid of this screen on the left which which is our project browser
and i'm gonna print this statement right here before we return the done text okay
so i'll bring up the debug console clear the debug console and i'm going to say
command s all right and since we've made a lot of changes
here you see we created a home page lots of stuff in here so what we need to do
is just do a hot restart basically flutter in this case wasn't able to
really understand what we've changed in our home page so
there were so many changes that it just couldn't handle so a hot restart is the
remedy there now you can see here as we printed the
current user i'm going to do this so you can see more
of the the output i'm going to bring it up a
little bit i'm going to increase the size quite dramatically so you can see
it better as well and
i'm going to highlight the parts that were actually printed so this is what
firebase or this is what the print statement printed out for us and this is
user credentials that were created by firebase and
if you remember from the previous chapter i said that make sure before you
come to this chapter that you have a login user and this is the reason i
wanted us to i wanted the firebase instance in our application to already
know that you're logged in so that when we print your current user credentials
then as you can see it says here's the email address
and then there's a property called email verified false and it says are you an
anonymous user false and if you remember from one of
the earlier chapters when i talked about the firebase setup then
an anonymous user is a user who hasn't really logged into the application yet
and firebase is intelligent enough to
understand that any user who comes to your application who hasn't logged in
before or and their login information isn't saved in keychain or
shared preferences on android then that user is anonymous anonymous by default
so if you didn't take the um last action from the previous chapter
and you didn't log into the application with your current user
then you will actually be anonymous here so this flag will say true
but since we've already done that we've logged into the application then you'll
see our credentials being printed to the screen
now this is the part that i was interested in which is email verified
and it says false so what we're going to do here is to say
take the user so we're saying a final user is firebase off instance current
user i'm going to decrease the size a little bit here okay
and i'm gonna make the screen a little bit bigger so you can see it better
and let's go then create an if statement here
and let's say that we're gonna say what what have i planned for it let's just
say if user is verified email verified then we're going
to say print you are a verified user
and otherwise we're going to say print you need
verify your email first
so you see here because i'm so glad that
actually we're seeing this error you can see the entire error
it says how can i scroll here it says the
property email verify can't be unconditionally accessed because the
receiver can be null try making the access condition using question mark dot
or adding a null check to the target so what this is saying is if you go to this
user move your mouse over it uh if i can do that oh no
here you'll see that it says user is an optional user so what firebase has done
here is saying this current user property that you can
see here is an optional user meaning that well if something goes wrong and
firebase can't actually calculate your current user
for instance if you disable anonymous users which you can actually do
then firebase will be said it will be saying oops
null user the user is absent i don't know who this
user is so that is firebase api telling your
application that if you're using my api then you need to handle this case you
can't just ask me if the email is verified because the user may actually
be null the user may be absent so there was a great suggestion here you
saw here that says you can conditionally access that property using the question
mark dot syntax so let's do that question mark
done but as you do that you see you'll get another problem
it says okay you're asking me to compare an optional
boolean with
an actual boolean because remember your if conditions need to resolve in into a
true or false so um so in this case what you can do is
to either create something called for instance if an intermediate variable you
can say final email verified
and you'll say that is equal to user optional access to email verified field
or false you see this is the question mark question mark which we've already
talked about when we talked about dark basics so
what you said here is take the left hand side of this operator of question mark
question mark which is a null aware operator you say if the left hand side
exists take it otherwise take the value on the right okay so now if you move
your mouse over email verify you'll see that it's a boolean all right
perfect so you could either do that or get rid of this intermediate variable
that you created here and literally just put the exact same code in your if
statement and that will work exactly as it did up there so let's just go ahead
with that one less line of code one
line of code less maybe um all right so
if the user's email verified or false is true
which means that if the user's email verification could be read as true or
false and if you can't use false if the equation then in itself is true then the
user is verified otherwise the user isn't verified so
let's do command s there let's bring up our console i'm going to
change the screen layout a little bit so you can see better
and you can see here it says you need to verify your email i actually clean the
screen a little bit and command s again so you'll see a little bit less
information on screen and you can see our print statement which was here got
printed saying that yeah you haven't verified your email and you need to do
that first okay a lot of information but maybe less
than the other chapters and to be honest with you this is all we have to talk
about in this chapter i just wanted to display
or and show you that um or actually explain first what email verification is
why is it important and that we're we are going to use email verification in
our in our application as you'll soon see
and how can you actually read that property from a firebase user
great that was all for this chapter now the
next chapter is going to be a little bit different you may actually expect a
continuation of this chapter you would think that we're going to jump right
into email verification but i have intentionally actually put a little bit
of a pause in our flow because this is something you'll
have to do as a software developer sometimes in that if you see something
not kind of correct something isn't working
right then you'll need to address it as soon as possible and this is something
we're going to address in the next chapter the problem here that you may
may if you're a seasoned software developer or may not have thought about
is that we are just writing code on our computer
this code could be easily deleted by a malicious program a virus or if
something happens to our computer all this could just go away and you'll lose
everything that you've written so if you're not coming from a software
engineering background then you may not know what git and github are
now i'm not going to scare you to be honest
with you this is not something scary but um
what we need to do is just to make sure that we have a backup of our code and
just that's just common sense like even if you're a designer even if you're a
music producer even if you're a soft if if your product owner whoever
or product manager you probably know that whatever you're working on needs to
be saved somewhere safely so if you have a video file you're not just going to
put it on your computer you're probably going to make a backup of it if you're
working with figma that that file is already shared in the cloud is sorry not
shared it's already stored in the cloud so
it's very rarely that you will work on pieces of um documents that are not
securely stored in some sort of cloud and even if you're working for instance
with a document then nowadays there's also shared like um sorry there are
cloud solutions for storing your documents
securely in the cloud so um i mean it pretty much
almost always when you're working on a user generated document or a source code
in this case you'll need to make sure that it's securely stored in the cloud
and that's what we're going to do in the next chapter so we're going to talk
about git and github we're going to set up our gpg keys
or pgp keys how do you want to say it and we're actually going to dive a
little bit deep into git and what it actually means and why it is why is it
good why do software developers talk a lot about git and as you might know
this course well not might you already know this course
is about flutter but i couldn't help put this chapter in
because i believe if you're not a software developer if you're coming from
another background then it is my duty kind of to tell you
about git and github and why is it important how to use it how i like to do
very simple tasks with getting github so um
so let's then prepare ourselves for the next chapter which is going to be a
little bit less coding it's not really we're not at all almost not at all going
to be working on the source code we're mainly going to work with git and github
so with that said i will wrap up this
chapter and i'll see you in the next one hello and welcome to chapter 15 of this
letter course in previous chapters we talked a lot
about setting up our project so we've so far been working a lot with setting up
the project and the basics we also created our login and registered views
in our flutter application as i was developing this course myself i got to
the point that there was a lot of code being written by me and then i needed to
make sure that it is stored in a in a place where i can always go
back to even if i lose this information on my computer that i can go back to
that place and then retrieve that code so um
if you're a software developer if you're if you're a seasoned software developer
from before and you know what git and github are and you're comfortable using
them and you know how to set up for instance your secure keys with gpg
then you can safely jump over this chapter but if you're a designer product
owner product manager whoever who doesn't know what git and github are or
maybe need some help setting those things up
then this is a good chapter for you uh otherwise you can just skim quickly
over so
let's let's talk quickly about what git and
github are and why we need them um as i mentioned when you're working with your
code for instance as i was while developing this course then you're
writing a lot of code which is i mean intrinsically valuable because
your time was translated into those pieces of code as you were writing the
code you spent some time and energy and effort and wrote the code so it is quite
an important piece of information for you just to lose and depending on the
type of project you're working on for instance this project it has taken me
quite a lot of time to even develop the idea of the project and put it together
so while i was while i was putting together the idea of the course and
written writing all the bits and pieces that i have to explain in every video i
made quite a lot of backups of that of those ideas because had i not done that
and had i just put everything in just one piece of paper or something or just
even one digital document on my computer had i lost a document then well yeah
i would have lost it and i would have had to begin from the absolute beginning
and this is the same thing for your code [Music]
so you need to use two services called git and github in order to
store your code
in in a safe place so that you can always retrieve it later
so let's talk quickly about what is git and why do you need this um
so what you need to know about gitz is that git is a
piece of software on your computer that allows you to
manage various changes that you make to a code
base such as our project at different times keeping track of the date those
changes were made the person who made the changes and the changes themselves
and also it will be able to provide you the difference between your recent
changes and what was already provided in the or what was already
committed into this git repository well what a git repository really is is
a bucket is an empty bucket initially where there
is nothing in there and as you interact with your source code then you'd be like
okay now i want to turn this source code that i've written into a bucket so then
there's a bucket created around your source code called a git repository
which keeps track of all the changes that you're that you're making or
anybody else that works on the same source code is making to the code and it
will allow you to save snapshots of those changes at
at specific times of your choosing if you're a designer of your and you're
working with figma for instance figma already
automatically saves your work at the times that it sees fit so you never have
to press really a save button and also figma if you've seen it
and it keeps track it has a version history so you can literally go to figma
and say okay i've done my work i want to actually commit my changes in the
version history and i want to give it a name
most designers don't do that and they legislate must save their work
automatically and by that figma just says here's the timeline of your changes
at this time you did this at this time you did this so
even if you're a designer you're implicitly using something called a
version control and which in it in that case is figma
but when you're coming to the software development world we're working with
your flutter application there is no figma there and you're working with raw
code so you're going into visual studio code or sublime or whatever text editor
that you're using android studio as an id or whatever
then there is no service sitting there and saying oh you made some changes let
me let me help you save it in some sort of app
or a cloud solution so the system that allows you to do that on
your computer is called git so git is a software that allows you to keep track
of changes that you're making to source code okay
so i can see here that before we continue we're gonna actually talk a
little bit about git and so
what i'm gonna do here i'm gonna add lib a little bit here and improvise
and i'm gonna go here and make the screen a little bit bigger i'm gonna
bring up terminal and you don't see it on that screen because it opened on
another screen so let me just increase the size and bring
it up here so you also see it so i'm gonna go here to my development
folder and i'm going to go to my projects and
let's think go to
make a folder i'm going to say git okay
should i call it git or just let's actually create a folder called
testing okay let's go into testing then it is an
empty folder as you can see for now and what we're going to do is we're
going to tell git now which is a software installed on my computer um to
tell it that okay all of a sudden i want to turn this empty directory here into
something called a repository remember it's going to be a bucket then that
keeps track of changes in the current directory now before we continue maybe
oh sorry about that maybe you also need to actually install
git on your computer if you're not coming from a software development
background you probably don't even have git installed on your computer so i'm
going to bring up a a browser window here and say install
git so
if i google install git you will see that there there's like information
how you can install git on your computer if you
are on a macintosh and you have already installed xcode xcode comes pre pre like
pre-packaged with gits already if you're on windows i believe that you
actually have to i have a windows machine right here next to me which i
use daily i believe for windows you'll have to install git personally like
manual so let's say install git windows
uh get download package get a time get guys install git
oops my ipad for some reason got disconnected here so i'm going to have
some difficulty then um
let's see now install git on linux okay
i believe there is a good package actually for getting it on windows let
me go back here installer on windows you can see here
just go to i'm going to increase the screen size a little bit as well so you
can see it a little bit better here it says go to https get scm com
download win so i'm going to go here and it's going to start downloading so
i'm just going to say cancel because right now i'm in a macintosh so here is
where you can download git and install it on your computer
if you are on a windows machine and you have the linux subsystem which i do on
my windows machine then you may actually want to download git using see sudo apt
um on that
linux subsystem but it is possible that the linux subsystem
on windows already comes shipped with git so you don't have to do anything i
wouldn't be surprised if git was one of the absolute core components that was
shipped with linux um
so that's for a macintosh and also if you're on a macintosh and you don't have
xcode for whatever reason um
then you may need to also download git separately so let's go back here and see
how you can do that uh if you say mac os here it says there
are several ways to install get on mac users probably install the xcode command
line tools which we've already done so if you don't have it in slavery it will
prompt you to install it so otherwise you can go in here get
semcom download mac and then you can do brew install git
so if that is what you want to do then you first have to actually install
homebrew so
go into this link and say homebrew install basically just do as it says
here you see there's the command and then go and install
git using homebrew and if you're on linux then a sudo apt
install git i think maybe you don't even need to have sudo if you're installing
for the current user so just apt app is it get or install i forgot but
there's information about linux here as well
app install yeah get all so
yeah i mean i'm assuming you're kind of like on a debian based distribution as
well but otherwise there's information here how you can install it otherwise so
all right uh that was a lot of information and before
we continue i'm just going to try to make sure that i'm connected back to my
uh to my laptop to my ipad here because on
my ipad i keep hold of all the information that i have to provide to
you in some sort of like a chronological order so it is very important for me to
actually get my notes up there so i'm going to try to connect to my ipad and
yeah there it is okay
so now that you've i'm assuming that you've
installed git i'm assuming that that is done if you say which git
then it's going to tell me in this case that user being get that's where get it
installed if you're on windows to be honest with you i don't know the command
on windows to know whether it come like git is installed but on windows all you
have to do is just to type git and if if you see that
it throws an error it says git isn't available either you haven't installed
git and if you have installed git maybe git isn't in the current path so you'll
have to go and adjust your environment variables in order to get git and
is lots of information on the internet so we're not going to focus right now on
how to install git exactly because that's going to be like its own course
maybe but if you follow the instructions that
were provided on the website that i just showed you should be able to get far
so i'm assuming now git is is installed on
our computer and you can see here we're in a folder called testing so if i say
where that testing is you can see that is is right here now what we want to do
is to say testing for instance is the project that we're gonna place all our
code in okay so there's gonna be information that we're gonna write here
in this um in this folder there's gonna be some dart files there's gonna be some
png and jpeg files there's gonna be our application icon all that stuff
and we want to store this safely so
the first thing you may want to do is to to basically tell git that this current
directory in itself is a git's repository so the bucket remember the
bucket is going to wrap itself around the directory so
if i get the contents of this directory at the moment you can see that it's
completely empty but if you want to create a git bucket or a git repository
around this directory all you have to say is just to say git init dots
okay you'll see here now it says that
initialize amt git repository in this folder
so now if i get the contents of this folder you'll see that there is a new
directory called dot git and dot git directory is where git basically keeps
track of its internal like the changes to this directory and like
what you save when you save it who is it that
saved the work etc so now that you've done that now you've created a git
repository basically around this empty directory you can issue various diff git
commands such as its status
this will give you the current status on this um
on this uh directory and you can see here as soon
as we created a git repository with git in it all of a sudden my terminal
changed my prompt here and said that all of a sudden testing is not just testing
anymore but it's actually a git directory and we're on a branch called
main now
i don't want to talk about branches right now but just know that there are
um yeah let's just not talk about branches
right now because i'm planning to do that a little bit later so
so but what we are going to talk about is this little message here that says no
commits yet now in git whenever you're working um git
doesn't just save your work automatically you need to tell git to
save your work and those points where you save your work there are call
commits it commits as its name indicates is you committing your work you say i
committed to this and i want to save it and that's i mean it could be called
save but save is maybe
um it could be uh like
read as kind of more like a verb like oh am i gonna save it now or what is it but
if i say here's my commit then it could be a little bit easier to infer
that oh it's a piece of information that you've saved and you've committed to so
i think maybe that's the reason it's called the committee i'm not sure
so those commits are points of time where a
person that has access to this repository saved their work okay so just
remember that that is a commit and if we see here the status says no commits yet
because there was literally nothing that you told get to save now what we're
going to do is to open up visual studio code so i'm going to bring up you just
to studio code here and you can see it's an empty folder
and i'm gonna create a file here and let's just call
um let's call this um
info.txt so just text file okay so here's an empty file and i'm just
gonna type hello in here increase the size a little bit as well so you can see
better so
now if i say git status here you can see all of a sudden it doesn't say no
commits yet it it well basically it says dad but it also says on track files and
it puts the info text right here now let me then explain what attract file
and on track file is a track file is a file that you've told git about before
so it it's tracking the changes being made to that file
on track file is a file that you have not told yet before about so it says oh
here's a file you're doing something with it but i'm not gonna even look at
it i'm not gonna keep track of it because you don't you didn't tell me to
do so so
and things um i mean yeah a file basically can be in
three states in git right now you've learned two of them either tracked or on
track but it could also be in another state that i will show you soon
so now you can see there's a message here
that it says let me bring actually the terminal a little bit up here so you can
see the terminal in its entirety it says use git add and then the name of the
file in order to include what will be committed so let's do that i'm just
going to say git add info txt and now i'm going to say git status and
all of a sudden you'll see that get understood that here's a new file you're
committing committing this file called info text but you can see
that it still says you haven't committed anything but it says changes to be
committed and all of a sudden this file is green
remember i said a file can be in three states on tracked which means git
doesn't know about it tracked which means it does know about it or it could
be staged so if you see here this file is green
and it says changes to be committed so stage is where
you have made changes to a file and you've told git that you want to
commit it but you haven't committed it yet
now you may be asking okay why would i have files that aren't going to be
committed in some projects if you have some information for instance if you're
working with 10 other developers and you're making some
tests and you're writing some code in the in the directory where your source
code is placed at but you don't you're not really ready with that file yet you
don't want to commit it into a branch where everyone else sees then you could
say oh i'm not going to commit this it is not staged file i'm not even ready
for staging it and putting it into the commit so in that case you're not going
to add it to the staging area okay so remember that
now that you've you've done that you just said git add you can commit it and
a commit literally means that you're going to save this work in git okay
and the way to do that is using git commits
and then you will provide a message using dash m here and then quotation
marks okay so here you will write a message that will be appended to your
entire commit so what we're going to do here says
let's just say add new info txt file for fun okay and
then i'm just going to press enter and see here it says one file change and
one insertions and it will say that yeah it has created this file okay so i'm
gonna clear my uh terminal now and we're gonna do git status
all of a sudden that message that about no commits yet disappeared and all this
is is that is that you're on a branch called main and there's nothing to
commit okay so
what do you do then if you want to see the commit that you just made like if
you want to see okay what are all the comments that were made then in that
case you can say git log and git blog will display
all the all the commits that were made and who they were made by and you will
also be able to see the date that were made and the commit message do you
remember we said git commit dash m so that was the message provided in the get
command and then saved in the repository okay
so that is the message and that's the email
of the person who basically did that commit
now i jumped over a little bit here and um
and to be honest with you that was i didn't really think about that some