we're not going to return a database node anymore and we're going to say it
returns a cloud node and here we expect a parameter of type
cloud nodes optionally that can be passed to our routes
and here we're not going to be working with
you see here we were working with database users before because our
application was actually creating new users in the local database and
associating notes with those users thankfully that now that we're going to
now that we're using firestore um database we don't have to play with
users anymore because remember users are already managed by firebase
so what we can do is just remove that owner
completely and now we await on our node service and
we just say create new node and then we need an owner user id and remember this
owner user id is going to be the actual current user's user id so let's just say
final user id is current user dot id okay
and then in here we just say user id okay and we're storing that note in here
as we were doing before so we didn't change that code at all and then we're
seeing new notes also need to be returned
so now we need to fix the creation of our new node and that's something that
we've already done so that there shouldn't be a separate point really in
the caption so we've already done that nothing to take care of right now
we also need to take care of now our deleting a notes you remember when we go
out out of the node creation view if the node's text
was empty we actually delete that node from the database okay right now and now
we need to go towards our node service and also delete it by using the new
function which is called delete node and let's see what it takes as a
parameter it takes a document id and that's our node's document id okay
so that's for delete note and now we have another function very useful
function that saves the notes and when we go out of the screen if the if that
note if the text for that note is not empty
very similar to delete node but it kind of does the opposite make sure that the
node is present and also that the text to the text editing controller is set if
it's not not empty meaning that the text is set
then we update the current node so let's then await on it and in here we just say
update node
those new parameters the document id is going to be our notes
document id and the text in here let's see
oh we have to just put a comma in there and then we're good to go
so that's updating the save node if text not empty function
okay now we need to go to our note list view
and i'm going to do the same thing in my notes
excuse me
and let's go ahead and do that do we have any errors in here yes i can
see i'm getting an error for update note and i don't really know what the problem
actually is let's see document id is required okay and i can
see that this is something also we need to update so let's go to your text
controller listener function as well and update
the note there as well you can see it's doing this so
now we now have to say update note and we have a note document id and then
we've got text so please ensure that you're you've taken care of the text
controller listeners functionality as well
um
and i'm just making sure that that's exactly what we've done in my notes as
well all right
so that that was one step back um now let's go and do what the caption at the
bottom screen says let's go to our notes list view um
notes list view and as you can see at the moment we're working with a list of
database notes and we don't want to do this anymore we actually want to work
with iterables because that's like the default way that firebase actually works
it works with eye troubles it doesn't work with lists so
and iterables are actually better because they're like lazy lists so let's
change this to an iterable of a cloud node like this and also we change our
node callback to be a cloud node if i can spell and also we have to also
import this so i'm just going to import cloud node so that error is going to go
away i'm going to remove this uh import statement from there
now when you're using eye troubles you can't do a subscript like we're doing in
here you have to say object element at and then you have your index and that's
pretty much what we're doing in here so now if you've made this change in your
node callback you made this change from list to iterable and you change this
from database node to cloud node and also change this function from a
subscript to element add then you shouldn't have any errors in your notes
listview.dart file either
now we're going to go to a little bit juicier changes that we have to make to
ensure that our application works as expected with the cloud
storage
let's go to notes view notes view like here and you'll see now
um actually i can see my notes here uh
we have to do a few updates in here because we're not going to work with
node service anymore since it doesn't exist
but one bigger change that we have to make
is as you can see in the cash offset remove the future builder
why is that here is the future builder the way it is today
you can see the future builders actual future is to get or create a user but do
we really need that anymore and the answer is obviously no because
previously we were using this feature builder to create a user in our database
so that we can associate notes with that user
however since now we're going towards firestore and uh
cloud storage the users like users in your application are managed by firebase
itself so you don't have to create them in that sense when a user
has logged in and landed on the main interface of your application that
firebase user already exists so you don't have to do anything so we need to
remove this future builder so i'm just going to press command dot on it and
sometimes visual studio code can actually help with that to remove it but
it's not helping at the moment so what i'm going to do in this case as
you can see i want to just grab this stream builder in here
just grab the stream builder without the return statement okay
and find the end of that stream builder visual studio code is helping me very
nicely with this line in here and saying this is the end of stream builder so i'm
literally just gonna do that and cut it okay so now
what you should be ending up with is your future builder like that looks like
this and then i'm gonna basically kill that future builder like this okay so
then paste your stream builder in the place that your future builder
was before so now your body the body of your um
of your scaffold should just be the stream builder okay so basically we just
got rid of the future builder all right
so that was that what we need to do then is to make sure also in here that we're
not using that that we're not exposing a user email you see from now on when we
create and notes read notes et cetera we're going to use a user id the user's
identifier so we're not going to work with our um with the email so
i'm also going to go to my note sorry about that so um
as the caption at the bottom of the screen indicates let's go and change
this to user id and we're just gonna go off service
firebase current user and then we're gonna get the id okay so that's our user
id and the rest now is kind of history we
need to ensure that this view now works with our
new node service so let's remove this import from here
and now let's say this note service it is a firebase cloud storage so we're
going to say firebase cloud storage and in here we just add that and
initialize that we say firebase cloud storage which is uh
if you remember correctly um it is now a singleton so we're not creating new
instances basically by doing this although it looks like we're doing that
so inside our stream builder now what we're gonna do is not gonna say all
notes anymore like that we're going to say
all notes but we're going to pass the owner user
id and that owner user id remember we're storing it as a getter call user id
and for all our notes in here remember this all notes is going to give us an
eye trouble if i move my mouse over there you can see it's an eye trouble of
cloud node so it's not a list anymore so let's say i trouble
and it's a cloud node in here okay
and i can i can see it's complaining that
cloud node can't be found so i'm going to import cloud node like that
upon deleting in here we also need to make sure that we call the new one that
says delete node and in this case we just say
node.document id all right
so so that is that seems to be working fine
but what we got here is a subtype of type firebase cloud storage node service
and we're getting that in where are we getting that error let's
see if we can find that in here node 2 and that's okay and
that's because we probably don't have to do a hot restart and doing a hot restart
could kill my scr cpy and i can see that it did that but that's fine too i'm
gonna bring up scr cpy like this
and i'm gonna
do this and i'm gonna run the application now from scratch and this is
simply because i mean this is a state management in your application because
we had a node service from before and we do a hot hot reload but hot reload all
of a sudden says oops this node service that used to be node
service is not node service anymore it's a firebase cloud storage so what should
i do with it so it's just it's like
state residue that is kind of like staying in your application and you
can't clean it until you do a hot restart and when i did a hot restart i
have a problem with scr cpy so i can't i can't do anything about
that problem but let's just run the application from scratch and just make
sure everything is working as expected all right now i can see that i've logged
into the application and i have no notes all right
let me bring up the caption for the next uh
topic to talk about so what we need now you can see notes have disappeared and
this is a good sign because that kind of means that we have moved away from our
crotch storage and now we're not reading those notes that were in the crotch
storage anymore so let's go and create some notes so i
want to press the plus button in here and i'm just going to say note
number one so if i press the back button in here i can see that node number one
is appearing here and let's go create another one and let's say note number
two great note number one and number two if
i press this number two and then change it to note number three you can see that
those changes are immediately taking effect okay
so let me log out from this user and let's log in with i don't know really
which user i was logged in with before i'll log in with this user i can see
that user has no notes i'm just going to say
van dot's first note go out and then say run dots
second note and go out so now if i log out from this
one.user in here and if i say i want to log in with another user
so like this i can see my note one and three are
displayed here so i can just say note number one and two
and if i log out from this user and log in again with vanbot i should be
able to see van dot's notes
through barbaz great so that seems to be working now
what we could do i mean if you're just like me and you're curious how this data
is actually stored in firebase we could do that so let me open up a window in
here and say console and let's go ahead into our project on
firebase console and let's go in
our database and let's have a look in here as you can
see there are four documents two documents per person per user and you
can see these two have the same user id and that's the that's the van load user
you can see it it starts with a and c and the other two nodes they have
another user id which is for pixelity av remember this a and c user what we can
do now is actually go in here to the authentication section and have a look
at this vendor user and you can see the user ids a and c
and the other user actually has erd so if we go back to firestore and look at
the two last notes created by pixelity you can see
that their user id is erd you can see here all right
so very well done congratulations in two chapters we've been able to go away from
local uh crud storage to firebase huge feed so well done
what we need to do now is i was we as we usually do in other chapters is we're
gonna commit our work and also tag it so i'm gonna do some reshuffling on the
screen here and grab visual studio code here
make the size a little bit bigger kind of ginormous but that's okay
and let's have a look at our log and we can see the last step was step 19.
let's do a git status and there were a lot of files modified nothing new
so i'm just going to say git add all git commit
step 20 and push this
let's have a look at our logs we have step 19 and step 20 now and if you look
at our tags we have up to step 19 up to and including step 19. so let's
tag this as step 20 and then push our tags
all right that's great as is tradition again at the end of
every chapter i talk about what we have to discuss in the chapter that follows
and um we've talked quite a lot about now uh
allowing the user to store their own notes in the application but
it would be a lot more fun if he allowed the user to also share those notes with
somebody that they know about somebody that they know like a friend or
a family member so that's what we're gonna talk about in the next chapter
sharing notes so i'll see you there hello and welcome to chapter 38 of this
flutter course in previous chapters we've been talking quite a bit about how
we sync our notes with our firestore database and how we can read
those notes back and update them it'd be really fun also to be able to
share our notes and that's exactly what we're going to take care of in this
chapter in order to do that we need to use a
plugin called share plus and share plus is a plugin plugin as i've
mentioned now so it is not a package where a package extends the existing
capabilities of flutter into new heights a plugin takes a completely new route
and basically
uh goes well beyond beyond what flutter
internally can deliver and a packet a plug-in will need to be developed by
excuse me a developer or a set of developers
and it needs to be written specifically for
various platforms that that plugin wants to support for instance ios android so a
developer has to go and write some code for ios for android web etc etc in order
for that plugin to work on those platforms
now here we're going to use the share plus plugin and the share plus plugin is
developed by the flutter community so what we're going to have a look at here
is to go into pubdev
so i'm gonna do that right now
excuse me for my throat and in pub dev we're gonna search for uh share plus
after you've done that you'll see that you'll end up here and it is by a
verified developer called fluttercommunity.dev so you can tap on
that and you can get some more information about the developer here
and you can see that it supports android ios linux mac os web and windows so what
more could you ask for um so it's a free package that you can
use in your application and you can see that all you need to do is just to let's
go to ins installing and you see you have to say flutter pop
add share plus and that's exactly what we're gonna do
now in our application so i'm gonna bring our app here
and let's go ahead excuse me again
in our terminal and i'm gonna rearrange things a little bit here
okay actually perhaps i could do the same
thing that we've done before so let me increase the size of this
terminal so you see it better so let's just do the same thing that was
mentioned in the documentation so flutter pub ad share plus so flutter
op ad share plus
and this share plus since it's it's a whole new
plugin that you're adding to your application it's very important that you
basically rebuild your application because otherwise it won't be available
all right so what you could do is to do a clean and then rebuilds this is
cleaning is especially important for ios because sometimes when you add a
new plug-in um since flutter uses cocoa pods in order to
handle ios dependencies then your build may not
actually be able to pick up on that new dependency so it is important to do a
clean but for android it's usually not a problem so i'm just gonna
excuse me i'm just gonna uh rebuild the application and see if everything is
working as expected so i'm gonna stop the application here
and i'm just gonna make sure that flutter select device is using my
android telephone and then i'm gonna go to main dart and just say
run run without debugging and it's it says we have some errors so
let's see if we can fix those errors in here
okay share plus plugin as you can as i can see we already have the problem now
in our application so maybe that's why you have to do a clean so let's go ahead
i'm going to go to terminal and i'm going to say
flutter clean
okay that's going to clean the xcode
workspace and hopefully it's going to clean the android as well so i'm just
going to say flutter clean android
do you mean any of these did i not write clean
i wrote clear so clean android oh it's doing the same thing okay
so then i'm gonna do flutter and let's just say pop get
so that's gonna rebuild all our dependencies
so there we go now that those errors have disappeared okay so you may have to
have flutter clean and i was trying to get away without using that but i was
forced to eventually so in main dart i'm just going to say
run without debugging and that's just going to take its time and go to
scr cpy and i'm just going to bring scr cpy to
the screen as well soon i'll just make sure that i have wi-fi access on this
phone because i play quite a lot with wi-fi
and hotspots on this android phone so it could be that sometimes i don't actually
have wi-fi
okay so that seems to be running and here is uh that android phone and i can
see that the flutter application is trying to run great able to run this and
on that phone so we've done that we've done the clean
and rebuild so that's great and
the first thing that we're going to take care of is to disallow sharing mt notes
you see if if you're on a note screen and you haven't even for instance
written anything in your note you shouldn't be able to share that note
with anybody because well it's just empty text in there so let's go ahead
and we need to take care of that scenario by having a dialogue
and we're going to create this dialogue inside this folder
excuse me again i've been talking quite a lot today and that's why my throat is
giving me some trouble so let's go to lib utilities under
dialogues we're going to create this cannot share empty node dialog okay
uh let me change the screen layout a little bit here and
views we have there and we have services
so let's see what we have constant synonyms extension services
utilities and views but we don't have so yeah we have utilities and we have
dialogue so we have to create a new one let's just say new file and i'm going to
say cannot share empty node dialog the dart
and you will remember from before that we already have a
generic dialogue so what i'm going to do is i'm going to say future
of void so the function signature is going to
look like this as i'm showing you at the bottom of the screen so let's say show
cannot share empty notes dialogue it's quite a long name
and then it return it requires a build context so build context context like
this okay then what we're going to do in this
function is to return our generic dialog and this is something
that i'm actually quite proud of that we could create and we are using it so many
times now it's unbelievable so we literally have one dialog implementation
in the entire application and we're just reusing it and it's truly generic and
it's really good so let's in here let's say that we
return our generic show generic dialog
and it's going to also import that for me it's inside utilities dialog generic
dialog so you may have to import that yourself if your
editor doesn't allow you to auto import so the context is already there for the
title we're just going to say sharing for the content i'm going to say you
cannot share an empty note okay
and it's options builder remember it's a function that should return
um a map and in the map we're just gonna
say it has one button that has literally no value
so this is going to make it a a dialogue that returns a void or a
future of void when we call it here
okay so that file is now created now what we're going to do is to go and
add that button as you can see it says in create update note view add an icon
button to actions of app bar so i'm going to go to my notes as well and
create update and let's go ahead and just add that
button and there we go
i can see that we're using a share icon so i'm going to decrease the size of
this of the font is is very big at the moment
one more step i i think you can still see the way it is i mean i can see in
the video output video it should be visible still even though i've decreased
the size so let me go here bring scr cpy i'm
gonna close this safari window
let's go to create update note view and we already have this button at the at
the top i believe let's see do we have any buttons at the
top no we actually don't so
in our app bar so let's go and create something called actions in here and you
can see it's a list of widgets and in here we're just going to say icon button
unpressed we're just going to leave it empty and for its icon we're just going
to say const icon and and we're going to use icons share
remove this parenthesis from there and then put
like that okay so now now that we have this icon icon button there if i press
on any of these existing notes then we should be able to see a little share
button up here at the moment it doesn't do anything because it's on press is
empty but we're going to program that program that right now
so let's grab the current text of our current node so let's just say that this
is equal to our text controller's text and we're going to say if note
is not null and
the text um actually let's just check for null
and the text or actually
or this text is empty then we're gonna display our new dialogue that we just
implemented so let's just say we await on show cannot
what's that function called the show cannot uh
we did it inside the cannot share empty notes so i'm just going to copy its name
and go in here and paste it and
now i'm going to use visual studio code to do the auto importing for me
so it needs a build context and in here i'm just going to pass the context and
you can see it's complaining that i'm using a weight inside an unpressed
function that isn't async so i'm just gonna make this function async okay
otherwise what we're gonna do is we're gonna use share
and share it is coming from share plus and it can be auto imported okay so i'm
gonna just also import that and in here i'm just gonna say share that text it's
really just as simple as that so let's go in here and i'm gonna create
a new note you can see it has no text i'm going to
press the share button and now we see now we're seeing our beautiful little
dialogue that says you cannot share an empty note fantastic and if i go out
that note is deleted but then if i go to a note that does
have text for instance van dot's second note or vandal's first note in in here
i'm going to go to van.firstnode and then if i press the share button then
i'm going to be presented with in this case android's default share
sheet or how you want to call it and on ios you're going to be presented with
the default ios sharing activity so this is pretty much it so we didn't have
to do much more than this it's literally the call is share.share so you can see
it's so simple when you drag in a plug-in especially a plug-in that is
from a verified developer especially from flutter community or flutter team
or dark dev team themselves all right perfect so that was for
sharing there's not much more to sharing than that and we don't have to drag on
on this chapter so let's go ahead as this tradition
we're gonna go and uh commit our work so i'm gonna do some shuffling around here
gonna get rid of scrcpy increase the size of the
screen and the font so you see better
then let's go to our terminal
and i'm gonna have a look at our git's log the previous chapter we committed at
step 20 and we also tagged as a step 20. let's just do step 21 in this case
so get status we have quite a lot of new stuff so if i say get status in here you
can see a new file in here as well so let's commit as
step 21 and push our commit
and i'm gonna go and tag it and say step 21 as well
and then we push our tags as well okay perfect so that's it so if you say git
status right now we shouldn't have any uncommitted files
very well done so um what we're going to do in the next
chapter is very very exciting we're going to delve into a block and
if you're a flutter developer from before you'll
know what block is maybe or maybe you've heard of it and you want to learn about
it so that next chapter is perfect for you if you're not a flutter developer
from before you may not know what block is and i'll explain it more however
i'll just at the end of the chapter i'm not going to go into the details of the
next chapter but what we have to talk about is how at the moment our ui which
is our different views are actually working directly with our services so we
have some services that for instance can store stuff in the um
in the firestore database and we also have some services that are like
for our authentication the uis upon pressing the login button we're going to
the off service and the off service is coming back with results directly to our
ui this is working it's fine however
there's better way of doing this and that's through
separating the logic of our ui from our business logic ensuring that
our ui is doing what is best what it knows best and that's drawing things on
the screen but when it comes to handling logic and like
making api calls and etc the ui shouldn't really know much about that
the ui should just convey its purpose to some sort of a layer that we're going to
create in our application with the block library and that that layer will decide
okay upon this button being pressed i actually have to do this business logic
so i'm very excited actually about the next
chapter so grab some refreshments if you want to
and i'll see you there hello and welcome to chapter 39 of this flutter course
uh in the previous chapter at the end of the previous chapter we talked about
that in this chapter we're going to talk about
the block library and this is quite a hot topic for flutter
developers like if you're a flutter developer and you've just been
using vanilla set state in your application you may have already
heard about block library and qubits before if
you're not a flutter developer from before which i actually think the
majority of you taking this course probably have not been fluttered
involvers from before so you may have may have not heard about block
uh before so i'm just going to start this chapter by explaining what
the block library is and why do we need it
you see the way that we've created our application at the moment is that we
have direct calls from our ui code into our different services in order to
interact with data so
the ui is very well aware of the business logic so for instance the
the create or get existing nodes function
that we have when we actually go and create a new node that is already a word
of the fact that well if you end up in here i expect a user to be present
inside the application so a user should be logged in and that's
a sample an example of a ui component being aware
of the logic the business logic of our application so they're very they should
be very separate from each other otherwise
but they're not at the moment so what is block block is a um is a
library that we're going to drag into our application soon as you'll also see
is a third-party library call i believe it is created by a company called
very good ventures vgv
and there are various flutter developers and software engineers that are
constantly working in order to improve the quality of the block library
which is a dependency that will bring into our application and using the block
library i mean internally is using streams and streams stream controllers
and futures the stuff that's already built into flutter but it's like going
to a next level to make things more abstract so that our application isn't
directly dependent on its business logic with the ui inter intermixed
so
the reason we need the block library is just to ensure that our ui is only
taking care of the presentation of the ui and it's leaving the rest of
the stuff to a business business logic layer
excuse me
so that's why we need block and we're gonna use it soon in our application
excuse me so if that is blocked then what is
flutter block you see block in its in its internals is a very simple library
that works with streams and stream controllers so it allows you to for
instance pass data from here to there and have listeners that listen to
changes that are happening in a stream so it's only working with like very low
level stream stuff however when you come to your ui layer
as you remember i mentioned that block allows you then to separate your
business logic from your ui so
it's taking care of the business logic using streams and stream controllers and
futures but when it comes to the ui part in order to glue this business logic
with the ui it needs to be able to work with flutter
so the part that works with streams and
stream controllers using dart okay and dart asynchronous components but the
part that it wants to glue that with your ui needs to come to the flutter
world okay and that is that library in itself is
called flutter block so fl block is divided into two separate libraries one
is block which takes care of the business logic etc and the other one is
called flutter block all right but don't worry about it i'll go through
these with you one step at a time so you'll learn these
excuse me
so what we're going to do in this chapter
is going to have it literally has nothing to do with our
application we've been working with the notes app and in this chapter we're
actually going to break our application a little bit by just like literally
replacing the home page of our application with a
completely new application is nothing scary i i promise you the changes we're
going to make is is probably only going to be limited to the main.dark file
and what we're going to do is to create a
counter application if you if you've worked with flutter before and you've
started thinking about maybe moving over to
block you may have actually gone to the block library's documentation page and
you've seen a counter application in there where you have a plus and a minus
button and you can increase and decrease the value that's shown on the screen so
that's like the basic counter application
but in this example i'm going to show you we're going to take that example to
the next level and use the block library and i'm going to introduce all the
basics of the block library to you in this chapter but we're gonna take it to
the next level and allow the user to enter some value on the screen and that
value will then be able to be added or subtracted from the current
value that the application stores so it's kind of like a counter application
where the user can actually enter the value that needs to be added to the
previous account or it needs to be subtracted from the previous account so
that's the difference between our simple counter application and what
block libraries counter application in its documentation
introduces you to all right so
let me bring up this caption in here and we're going to talk a little bit about
various components of a block and i'm fully aware that pretty much
everything i'm saying in this chapter up to where we get to the example is
all very much abstract in that it is
literally just theory i'm like teaching you theory here
i personally am horrible at theory like i didn't excel at school when it came to
theory so i'm very aware that a lot of you may also have the same um situation
or maybe in the same boat that i am that are not good with theory and that's okay
i'll just explain these fast and then we'll go to the implementation so you
can put that to practice so for those of you who are interested in the theory of
it i'm going to explain different parts of the block library to you now
so here the first
component of the block library is a class called block
now block really it is a container just imagine a class a class that you add
events to it and every event that you add to it can produce a state so the way
block works is that it it is a class that begins with a state so its output
is always a state for instance a state can be logged in a state could be logged
out states could be
error screen so just imagine different states of the application
so that's the input sorry the output the input to it are your events so
in your block that will develop you will have
inputs that you for instance say log in with this username and password
register with this username or this email and password register oh i forgot
my password and here's my email so these are events that you
produce and give to your block and then in turn your block then looks at its own
internals and say oh what was this state before what is the current event then i
will produce a new state okay so that's the internal of the block class
now when you have a block class when we're gonna
subclass from that block class then you will actually need to create an instance
of that block class and you will do that using something called a block provider
so that's as its name indicates it is a class that creates a um
it creates a block instance for you and then it will allow you to do something
with that block so
i'll see if i actually can
show you block provider uh
perhaps we could bring up a window in here and i'm just gonna
say so block like brarry you cannot see my screen right now but i
promise you i will show you soon so here's the uh
main page for the block library so i'll
increase the font size so you can see it as well
so let's go ahead and you can see it's sponsored by very good ventures and
stream and medo i'm not sure i i may have butchered
this name right now i apologize for that but then if you look at
the various parts of block then you'll see let's see
if i can find block provider for you here
it could be inside the documentation so i'm going to go to get started and then
i'm going to have a look at block package block and let's see provider if
you can find the provider in here somehow
block uh architecture naming convention
getting started is there is something uh inside i have a
little bit of a problem right now actually finding block
provider so let's search for it block provider
and then we end up here
and i mean this is not the best
documentation right now to be honest with you we don't want to look for a
blog provider right here but as you can see it says it is a flutter
widget which provides a block to its children so this is how you would work
with a block provider so it creates the block instance for you and then it will
allow you to return a child all right so kind of like a builder but not really
all right
so that's block provider and as i mentioned you can always go to the block
library.dev website in order to get more information
about block and read its documentation
so the next component you need to know about is
block listener so
what is a block listener as its name indicates a block listener simply allows
you to hook into a um i'll actually see if we have a
block listener i can see that we have a blog listener in this application that
we're going to develop so you're going to learn about it soon but a block
listener as its name indicates it listen to changes to the states of a block
that's it so you can do some side effects so displaying a new screen for
instance or displaying an error message those are all side effects okay so you
can do that with block listener
now let's have a look at what a block builder is uses your block state changes
to provide you with a widget so as we have a block provider um sorry
we talked about block provider before it gives you uh the chance basically to
create um
a child now inside this child you can then provide a create a block builder
that listens for changes inside your block then it allows you to build new
widgets based on those changes so it's very much like a future builder or
like a stream builder i would say and we've already used stream builder so you
should know how they work but again this is just theory so um
i'm gonna talk more about these as we actually build our application okay
so after all this we also have a block
consumer and what a block consumer is that it combine as i've actually written
here it combines block listener and block builder so a block consumer
listens to changes that happen inside a block and then it will allow you to do
both a side effect and it will also allow you to create a widget to display
to the user based on those changes all right
and again i don't want to go too much into details in uh for a theory because
depending on how you learn new things theory may not be your strongest point
just like it is not for me so it could be a waste of time for you
so let's go ahead and start adding our dependencies in our project so i'm going
to bring our notes application to the screen
resize it a little bit so we have place for scr cpy as well
and we have scr cpy right here as i can see and this is our application
okay and the application is running currently
so then what we're going to do is going to
go ahead and say flutter pop add block and then flutter pop add flutter block
so let's go ahead and increase the size in
here then i'm going to go to terminal say flutter pop add walk
so that's going to do its work
and it added one dependency i'm just going to say flutter hub at flutter
block
all right and this is a package so it's not really
a plugin and i don't believe it's a plugin i think it's a package so it
could be sufficient for us just to stop our application in here and just say
flutter clean
that cleans the application that we're going to say fire pub get
this could be sufficient so that's gonna do its work
and then we're gonna go then we're gonna go to our main dart
file and just say run run without debugging and that's gonna just do the
greater build if you're running on android or it's gonna use xcode build in
order to build your ios application so
and i'm just gonna let that do its thing now so
let's just wait okay now the build is done and i can see
the application running on the screen without a problem so
what we need to do as the next step is to do something dramatic and that is to
comment out our home page because we're gonna replace our home page with another
home page which is gonna use block so it may sound scary but it's not that scary
i promise you so let's go into your main dart in here
select home page as it stands right there and just comment it out
and we're going to create a new stateful widget again and we call it home page so
stf and home page the reason this is a stateful widget is because we need a
text editing controller as i mentioned how we're going to do this example right
now to learn block is to create an application that gives you a text field
that you can enter a number into we start with the value of zero
in our block so the block holds on to a number and then when you and then we
will create two events one an increment event and a decrement event and
so when we then give the increment event to our block
then we want to grab the current value inside the text field so if we start
with zero and then i type five in this text field and i press increment button
then i want five to be added to the current state which is 0.
so the result will be 5. the next time i will type 10 then press decrement so
decrement will be 10 and then it will be 5 minus 10 so we end up with minus -5
so that's the ui that we're going to create
and for that we need this home page and the reason it's stateful is because we
need to grab that text from our text editing controller okay so
so that's our new home page and if i now
press command s in here our screen is going to be black because well this this
is a home page with no information no scaffold nothing all
right
so and now let's talk about this absolute beauty that we're going to call
counter state you see as i mentioned every block has two very
important properties one is its state and the other one is an event an event
goes in the block and state is something that comes out the block and so the
state as its name indicates describes the state of your block
so if you think about it what we expect
from our block is a simple integer okay so we could either
say our block's output is integer or we could define a state that wraps around
that integer so that's exactly what we're gonna do right now
so let's go ahead and say we have an abstract
class and we call it counter state
and then here we have a final integer called value and then we're gonna create
an initializer here like that and that's our counter
you could also mark this as immutable if you want to all right so let's do that
and let me also change the screen layout a little bit here so you see the code
better so that's like the basic state of our block okay we're not actually gonna
use the state as it is we're gonna create two sub states for this as you
will soon see now
since we're going to create a text field in the middle kind of like this screen
and the user is able then to enter pretty much any text in this text field
let's just assume so just normal text not even integer so the user just say
hello world and then presses the plus button what should we do in that case
plus button plot plus thing like adding hello world to the previous value of
five means nothing so we're gonna divide our state into a valid state and an
invalid state and then present this to the user in two different ways so let's
go ahead and create a class called as i've mentioned there counter stayed
valid so i'm going to actually grab that code
so we don't have to type it ourselves as you'll soon see
here we have a counter state valid extends our counter state which is this
one and we have a constant constructor that says okay give me a value a valid
value and then i'm going to call my super class with that value
all right so that's a valid state now let's then create a an invalid state
so let's say class i'm going to bring the correct caption
as well invalid state
let's say counter state invalid number extends counter state
in this case we want this state to actually include some sort of um
the value that actually made our state invalid so i'm just going to say that
value is a string and we're going to call it invalid value here okay
and i'm going to say const and let's just bring a create an initializer here
a few required parameters in here and we're just uh
like this so in this case we're going to create two required parameters one is
the invalid value that caused the error or cause the state of our block to be
invalid and the other one is going to be a required of the required parameter of
the previous value so because we may actually need the
previous value uh or something or maybe like the ui needs
to display that to the user so if this is the output of our block the state
remember is the output maybe then the ui actually upon me trying to plus hello
world with five he may want to use this previous value to populate that text
field or populate the ui again and say hello
um this value that you entered is invalid
but the previous value was this so i'm just going to show that okay so that's
why we need previous value and here we're getting an error because we're not
calling super let's call super with the previous value
okay that's our counter state invalid number okay so we've created
our two states that uh come from counter states immutable abstract class
okay let's go ahead then and create our
counter event and remember counter event is very
similar to state so first we actually have to define an event
and let's go ahead and define that event like this
and you can see it's an abstract class called counter event and it just
contains a value so it just says the string that comes from the ui can just
go directly into the counter oven that's it
and let's make this actually immutable as well
and what we're gonna do is to create an event for increment
so let's go and say class increment value
um or increment event
extends counter event okay
and in here we're just going to say const create a constant
constructor for it and we just grab a value in here so a string value and it
should just go to the super that's it and what we need to do is just to grab
this event as well and create a decrement event
so let's call this decrement here
like so and again remember the event is something that we need to trigger and
send to the block from the ui all right so we're gonna pack these increment
event and decrement event with with the string that the user has entered in the
ui and then send it to the block as you'll soon see
so let's go ahead now and do the main part of this application which is our
block and the way to do that is to create a class if i can spell class
and say canner block extends block and you'll see it'll now auto
import it for me because we hadn't imported block from before
and now let's see if block is imported somewhere here and that's the package
block block if your editor doesn't allow you to auto import you will have to do
that by hand excuse me
so the way to create a block is first you define the state of that block like
what type of state does it have sorry events first we start with the counter
event and then the counter state okay so if you look at the definition of block
class itself you can see the two parameters are or the two generic types
are the event and the state so that's here we're saying our events
are of type counter event and our states are of type counter state
so that's that then let's go ahead and say we have a counter block
that's the constructor and what it does is it has to call super
you see and our super actually needs the initial states so
every block has to have an initial state and that's when you pass your super okay
so what we're gonna do is we're going to say we start with the value a valid
value of 0. so we say const
counter state valid and we start with 0 just
like that
okay so that's our
let's see what happened there seems fine to me yeah
okay so that's the initializer in there now what we need to do is actually grab
these events as they come remember the ui is gonna
uh basically pass us these events so the ui is gonna say here's an increment
event with this value here's the decrement event with this value so we
need to catch those how do we do that there is a function called on on the
block itself that you can use so we're going to say on increment value
sorry increment event and then it gives you two parameters so
if you look at the function signature of on it actually gives you you see it
gives you the event and an emit so let's in here just write event
emit and in here we create a new function and
put semicolon at the end so that's how we're gonna handle the increment value
same we're gonna do for decrement so let's just copy that and paste it in
here and just say decrement all right so what are we doing here now
remember the event that comes in now is an increment event because we literally
said on increment event so we're we're then going to get that
integer from our events so remember our increment event actually has
is of type counter event and then it has a value of type string so we're gonna
try to parse that as an integer okay so we're going to say final integer is
int tri parse and we're going to say event dot value
like that so and try parse is a function on integer that
will try as its name indicates it's gonna try to parse a given string and
try to make it an integer and if it can't then that integer is gonna be null
so let's say if uh here if integer
is not null like that
and then we put an else in here and in the case of an else actually so
it means that hey you gave us something that we couldn't parse as an integer
what do we do with it all right then we're going to use our emit
emit is a function on its own you see it's an emitter that allows you then to
pass a state out your block so i actually scared myself with my own
finger so you you have you got your you got your um this
event in now you want to create a state and pass it out that's how you do it
with emit all right so we're gonna then say in this case
if we got uh if actually let's do integer null if we
got null we're going to handle the error here
sorry about that so if we got not what we're going to do is we're going to emit
a counter state invalid number
and we have invalid value and a previous value
so the invalid value was this value that was passed to us in here you see event
value so let's just say that's the event.value
and the next parameter is the previous value and the previous value is always
stored inside your state so let me actually do some cleanup in
here so you see the code better a comma here so let's see what happened
in here you see we're emitting so we're sending a state outside our block
so we're saying given an increment event where the integer where the value
couldn't be parsed as an integer we're emitting a new state saying that hey
your value which was in this event is invalid
so that's invalid value and the previous value that we had is
stored inside our state so your block in all your on functions you have access to
your current state before emitting a new one all right so that's the previous
value inside state and if we could actually grab an integer
we're going to emit a new value a new state and we're going to say counter
state valid okay
and we're going to say we take the current value in our state plus it this
integer like this right
like that so that's for increment
and as you'd guess decrement i'm going to remove this comma
by the way it was annoying me a little bit and decrement it's very similar to
increments so i'm just going to copy this code and remove this decrement one
and paste the increment one one more time and then this time i'm just going
to change it to decrements like this all right
and for the big decrement the only thing you have to do is just to change this
plus to a minus and that's it all right
wow a lot of work a lot of work so now let's go ahead to our
home page in here now we've basically gotten the block
down so the block should be working as uh
as we want it to so so let's now go into this homepage that
we created in here and create our text editing controller
so for that i'm just going to say late final
text editing controller and we're calling it controller as i can see here
let's go into init state and override also the dispose function okay
i'm gonna bring the code so you can see it
i'm gonna bring it up so in in its state we're gonna instantiate
our controller so this is nothing new you've already done this before many
times and in here we're gonna dispose of that
control
uh fantastic all right that part is done so what we need to do now inside our
build function we're gonna basically we have to create um
our main ui so i'm gonna bring the caption for that as you can see we have
to use block provider and block consumer so in the build function right now we
only have a container so let's instead of doing a container say okay we want to
create a block and we also want to just like make sure everything after this
return statement has access to that block so we need the block provider so
let's say block provider and block provider is in a
flutter block package as you can see here and we haven't imported that yet so
let's import that right now in the create
parameter we get a context as you'll see i can get visual studio code to complete
this for me it says i will give you context and you'll give me a block back
so i'll say okay i'll take the context and i'll create a counter block here
okay so that's the first parameter then we're
getting an error here just because we haven't provided a child here so if i
say child in here is a text of hello world
and press command s then we see hello world right there okay so in here our
task then is to create a scaffold so let's create our scaffold just we
usually like we usually do and for our app bar
let's create an app bar in here and say app bar
title is it const can't see anything because the
documentation is all over the place cons text and i'm going to say testing
all right so now we have a blog provider that created an instance of our counter
block and then we have a scaffold with a beautiful app bar displayed on the
screen okay so as the caption at the bottom screen
mentions for uh our child the child of our block
provider is a scaffold but inside the scaffold itself we have body
and for the body then we're going to create a block consumer so remember a
block consumer is it is
the combination of a block listener and a block builder
we need a block consumer here is and the reason for that is upon every
pressing of the plus or the minus buttons that we're going to develop soon
we want to clear the text inside of our text field
so that's a side effect so by us saying that okay whenever there's
a new state coming out of our block we want to clear something so this is a
signal when you want to do a side effect that has nothing really to do with like
a business logic or such then that is your listener so
so we're saying that we need a block listener but also we want to for
instance be able to have a builder so we want to build our
ui based on the current state of the block
well that is block builder so if you need a block listener anywhere in your
application and a block builder you need to instead use block consumer if you're
if you need them at the same level okay so block consumer combines block
listener and block builder so that's why we're using block consumer in this
block consumer it's going to say okay what block am i operating on so i'm just
going to say you're operating on counter block and then it says what state am i
operating on and we're going to say counter state
let's see if they're available counter
and you can i mean i'm not making this up this stuff is present in the
documentation if you go to block consumer as well
let's see in here what it says it says uh extend state state streamable so
that's the the b here b for me means the block and
s is the state so it's not so clear because it's working with a lot of
generics but you can read the documentation about that okay
so let's go in here and in here let's have a look
and it's complaining that some named parameters aren't present as you can see
named parameter listener is required so let's go ahead and say listener
and i'm going to get visual studio code to help me clean this up and upon any
new events or sorry upon any new states produced by our blog i want to clear our
text editing controller so let's just say text controller
uh what do we call it do we call it
controller yeah so we're going to say controller
clear so we're going to clear the text that is displayed inside the text field
soon okay then we need the builder function so in
this builder function as you'll see the
it will give you the current state and you need to return a widget back okay
so what we're going to do in this in this is first we're going to grab
like um to see if there's an invalid value so
let's just say final invalid value is and we're going to say if this state
is a counter state invalid number
with a question mark so we're using turner here and we're going to say get
the states uh let me bring the code up uh invalid value
otherwise we're gonna say empty string so
if i then in here say invalid value as you can see it's now a string okay
and the reason behind this to be honest with you is so that we can
basically display
the a little error message to the user should there be an invalid value so if i
have if i have entered some information in the text field instead of a number
i've entered hello world and then our block produces a counter state
invalid number we're going to display an error to user and this error is gonna
disappear the next time actually the user enters a valid number in the text
field okay so we're gonna use a new widget that we haven't used before
called visibility and this visibility is gonna be based on whether there is an
invalid state or not so you'll soon see actually how we're gonna
implement that so let's go and as our builder's main like
return value create a column okay and column has to have children all
right so what we're going to do is to first
display a text field sorry a text in here so let's just say text
and we're going to say current value is equal to this state value
all right so that's going to be the current value of our
state and if i do command s you can see that it says current value is 0.
so that's the current value then what we're going to do is to go ahead and
create a visibility widget which in case the
current state is counter state invalid number is going to display an error
message to the user so let's say we're going to control the visibility of that
error message using the visibility widget
like this and it's childband is going to be
a text that says invalid inputs and then we're going to
add the invalid value in here as you can see as we've constructed that up there
already and the visibility flag you see we have
to return a boolean okay so how do we know that
we have to display
this widget with visibility and that is if you can
grab hold of your state and say okay this state is actually counter state
invalid number so let's just say state
is counter state invalid number just like that okay so that's how we grab
hold of that invisibility and you can see at the moment it's not
displayed all right even if we even if we put some
um actually let me just say is not
and then save it and you'll see now it says invalid input so it's just
displayed right there okay but if you say state is then it's going to
disappear because the current state is not invalid number
okay that was for visibility now let's go and add our text field
so where the user can actually enter some information in the ui so let's just
say text field as the first parameter we're going to
say the controller is our controller
okay and what we're going to do is we're
going to give it a hint text so let's say decoration is a const inputs
decoration like that i'm going to put the code a
little bit higher on the screen so for the hint text i'm just going to
say enter and number here
like this okay and also let's just enforce the keyboard type
uh text input type of a number
all right but also remember if you oops
the controller has not been initialized really i thought we initialized the
controller yeah maybe you have to do a hot restart
there we go so now we have enter a number here okay
great stuff now all right this is what i was going to say even though we have a
text field here and we actually said that the keyboard should be numerical
but i can still paste non-numerical numbers in here so if i like use the
paste functionality in android or is so that's the reason we have that invalid
state in case someone else someone actually enters another value except for
a number and there are also input formatters in flutter that you can use
in order to for instance um avoid users entering non-valid values in
your text fields but that's a whole other subject that we're not going to
discuss in this chapter so
then what we're going to do is we're going to have two text buttons for
increment and decrement so let's after this text field create a row so
a row is like the opposite of a column whereas a column displays those
components vertically one after one after each other a row creates its
components horizontally from left to right and left speaking languages and
right to left right
speaking right side speaking language i believe
i think actually row changes it's uh it should at least change is uh
how it arranges components based on the language but i'm not quite sure about
that so let's say row it has children
and it's two text buttons okay that have unpressed at the moment empty
and um it's a child it just says cons text just
minus like this okay so that's first that's the first button
and then for the next one i'm just gonna copy this text button and i'm gonna
paste it right here and in here i'm just going to say plus
all right so in here when the minus button is tapped i want to convey this
information to our block so i want to say grab the controllers text and make
sure that you send this increment where is it here
increment event to the block so we kind of need to grab hold of our block
how do we do that the way to do that is using a convenient function that
the good people at good very good ventures have created on
context and it's called read and in here you can actually say i want
to read my counter block like this okay so this gives you access to your block
that has been created by the block provider
so let's go ahead and in here let's say after we read that we want to add a new
event to it like this and we want to add an increment event that has the value of
our controller.txt
like this all right so this is how you send events to your
block and the same thing since we're actually sorry about that this should be
decrement so let's just say decrement like that and we copy the same code and
we bring it to our increment function as unpressed button here and instead of
decrement then we're going to say increment
right perfect okay so let's see now let's test
this application so at the moment we have current value zero now if i press
the plus button as you can see it says invalid input
all right but if i say 2 and press the plus button you can see
the value of 2 is entered there if i say hello world here
i press minus and it says oh invalid input hello world is invalid and as you
can see it clears this text and that's because of this listener here
uh this listener because a block consumer is also block listener remember
so it's a combination of a block listener and a block uh
builder so that's the clear working and the part
that is handling this invalid input is this thing so visibility if the current
state is an invalid number then this is becoming visible but if the current
state is not an invalid number so let's say three four plus two
it's going to be three six then the current state is actually not an invalid
number is uh the current state should be
valid it should be counter state valid so then the visibility is hiding that
error message so so that is pretty much it i mean um
huge congratulations if you could stick with me throughout this chapter it was
very heavy i understand it was a very heavy and very like technical chapter
talking a lot about business logic but believe me if you didn't understand like
most of the things i talked about you just need to practice
i'm no genius nobody who knows how to work with block or stuff like this is a
genius everybody has practice put it into practice done their own
applications done this test just go and create this counter application that i
just created try not to look at the code that i've written or rewritten
in this just try to remember the stuff from your memory and
after exercise and practice and practice and practice and you will get it and you
will get the idea of what a state is you'll get the idea of what events are
what block is and read documentations and you'll get this eventually i promise
you that
as is tradition we're gonna now uh since we're done with what we prom promised in
this chapter we're gonna go and commit our code
so let me change the screen layout a little bit and go to uh
terminal and increase the size get rid of the crcpy
and let's have a look at our log last
chapter we committed step 21 so let's see git status
and there were just a few things changed so let's add everything and just say git
commit step 22 and let's push our chase
and then i'm just going to say git commits sorry it's
a tag to see our last tag and i can see it was 21.
so let's tag this as step 22 and say git push tags
there we go so now step 22 is also tagged and ready
so what is to come this is also a tradition
we have at the end of every chapter we'll talk about what we're what we need
to discuss in the next chapter and what we need to discuss in the next chapter
is and we will convert our auth process to using block so
we've now talked we've act we actually got our auth
logic inside our application and that was our auth service i don't know if you
remember from before but we need to convert this auth service
to block and uh so in that way we're actually
putting our knowledge about block into use and combining it with what we've
already developed to make our application better and our logic not so
spread around everywhere in the ui so if you want grab some refreshments tea
or coffee and i'll see you in the next chapter hello everyone and welcome to
chapter 40 of this letter course in previous chapters we've been talking
about um our aus process and also storing um
users notes into a firestore database and in the previous chapter we also
talked about block so um i'm very aware that block could be an intimidating um
topic for some developers and that getting started with block could just
be conceived as like an extra step that you
think you don't need however i can assure you when you get
more into professional software development
and which is which may not be your goal i completely am aware of that but when
you get more and more to professional software development you'll understand
that you need to separate various layers of your product and that
the um the presentation layer where you're taking care of for instance
displaying stuff on the on the screen to the user shouldn't really have to talk
with your authentication directly um or for instance your authentication layer
doesn't necessarily have to depend at all on other parts of the application so
block is gonna allow you to in a very clean and concise way to
separate the various uh layers of your application into their own concern
layers so and the services are going to be only concerned with services and then
your ui is going to be only concerned with ui and so on so and so forth so
um it could be beneficial if you could actually before starting with this
chapter to go to the previous chapter and maybe watch it again or maybe even
practice yourself with block um i understand i know for sure that the
block libraries website as we looked at in the previous chapter they have quite
a lot of examples and i highly suggest that you go through some of those
examples at least and develop and implement those examples also yourself
to get a bet to get a better hang of what a block actually means and how
you're supposed to use it so if you've taken care of that and you
understand like the basics of block then we're we're we should be good to go
for this chapter so let me bring up the caption for what
we're actually going to do in this chapter you see the way we have our
application at the moment is that we have our
authentication service and our authentication service let me just bring
that to the screen here and let's have a quick look at it so if
i go to our auth service you'll see that we have
quite a few function functions in here we have
create user and we have uh we are exposing the
current user we have login logouts and email verification and initialize
now this is all good however we are it's very raw the way it is in that the ui is
literally making calls to our auth service which in case which in
turn is making calls to a provider which is our for instance um
firebase provider author provider so if you go in here you'll see firebase auth
provider and that is talking directly with firebase so
in a way you could say that the ui is talking pretty much directly with
firebase it's just going through some functions to get to firebase but that's
what pretty much it's doing so what we want to do in this chapter is to
try to make sure that our authentication is
behind a layer of block meaning that all the logic that has anything to do with
authentication is hidden behind a layer which we're going to call off block
so that's going to be our off block so it's like the and as you remember from
the previous chapter every block has two parameters one is what is
what comes inside the block so what's entered and what is the output
the input to your block are your events so you pass for instance your ui upon
pressing a button then you you pass an event a packaged event that
we call our auth event you're gonna pack package that up with any parameters that
that particular event is required it is required from you you take that event
and you give it to your auth lock then your off block is then gonna have some
time to process you remember we have these on function functions on
your uh off on your blocks when we talked about the counter block we had on
increment event on the command event etc so these are the events that come in so
we're going to package those events up from our ui and pass them to our off
block then our off block is going to have some time for itself to process
those events and based on those events that it has
it has received and based on its current state it's gonna either output the same
state or it's gonna output a new state so
events come in and states go out and the off block sits in the middle so event
off block and estate and these are three components that we're going to develop
in this chapter
so let's go ahead and
take care of our state and remember again state as its name indicates is the
state of authentication either you're logged in or you're logged out okay and
you could also be logged out with an error remember so you're either logged
in or logged out with an error so
we're going to start looking at these off states so what we need to first do
is to create a file as the caption indicates
under lip services auth block off state so
let me do some reshuffling on the screen here
maybe decrease the font size a little bit because it's just ginormous the way
it is right now so maybe this font is a little bit better
i'm going to put visual studio studio code in there
to the left and then i'm gonna bring scr cpy to the right
okay so i'm gonna close all these tabs that i have right here how we left the
application in the previous chapter and let's go ahead inside lib let's let's
see actually what we have in here we have lib and we have services
and under services we already have auth but we don't have a folder called block
at the moment we have auth provider etc etc
so let's go in off and just create a new file in here and say block
slash auth state state like this dot dart
okay so that's our off state
now if you remember from the previous chapter when we talked about
the counter block um
usually states are immutable and that they're also they're like at the generic
states that every other state in your block
inherits from is usually an abstract immutable class
meaning that it is a class pretty much almost with no logic at all it may have
a constant constructor but in and on itself it does nothing so it
just is dictating that hey every state that comes out of this off block is of
this type okay so let's go ahead and create our off state
so maybe i should actually increase the size of that font
so we're going to start by writing um our
states as you can see so we're going to code that in auth state.dart file
so i'm going to go ahead and just say abstract class auth state okay
and let's just create a constant constructor for it as well in case one
of our states needs to also have a constant constructor so this is this is
a pattern that you may have already been used to
by creating abstract classes and if you have like sub classes that conform to
your abstract classes and those subclasses actually want to have
constant constructors then you need to have a constant constructor in your
abstract class as well so that those subclasses can actually call that const
constructor in the abstract class otherwise you won't be able to have
constant constructors for your subclasses so for instance if i say
abstract class blah
extends off state and if i say const blah like this you can see it says a
constant constructor can't call a non-constant superconstructor and that
is the reason that i usually create a cons constructor for my
um classes for states and for um the events
okay
okay now we have our abstract class off state now let's go and make it immutable
and for that we need to import material or actually it is foundation let's
import from foundation in that case and we could just say show immutable
can we do it like that yeah that works as well okay
so that's that we have a generic off state so um actually i don't mean
generic in terms of like a dart generics which i just mean an abstract class that
every other off state can conform to
okay so we have basically a low i mean we have quite a few states so
i'm just going to start doing and doing and creating those off states one at a
time so while you're authenticating for instance
while you're let's say that you are
you've just opened the application and then we need to basically tell our
authentication um provider which is firebase to initialize itself while it's
doing that then our auth state is in the state of loading or initializing
whatever you want to call it but we kind of need have to have a state that
indicates to the application that hey something is happening with the auth
process and it is in the in the process of loading so let's go ahead and define
that so let's just say off state loading extends off state just like that okay
and this could also have a const constructor so let's just say like that
okay so that's the state of loading and we can
actually use the state of loading and i believe we're actually going to use it
while the user for instance is has just opened the application and the
applications is initializing and we can also use it for instance when
you tap the login button in order to log into the application and we're
communicating with firebase and that is also a state of loading okay
so you will see soon now these states are very important how the ui then
reacts to various events that are or various states that are happening in our
off block
so let's say that we have the loading state let's just
define a a logged in state so when the user has already logged into our
application then that is its own separate state so let's go ahead and say
off state logged in and it extends the off state
and now this is important to see okay when
you're logged into the application what does the application actually need from
us well the only thing the application needs from us when you have logged in
with the user is the current user at the moment we are going to our auth provider
and or our auth service and grabbing the current user but if we're gonna move
over to block and like blockifying our entire auth process then it makes more
sense for us to grab the current user that has logged into the application
from the current state of our auth block it's it's i mean to me it's really
beautiful because it makes sure that we can separate
the auth service and the auth provider from the ui by putting a block in the
middle so
i mean the name kind of it may sound like you're blocking the ui
but that's not how block is written as bloc it's not block so
but that's that's what we need to do so let's just say we have the final off
user and it's going to auto import it for me if you're using vim if you're on
linux and or if you're using subline that it's not able to auto import things
then you'll need to auto you need to import off user yourself okay
so let's say that a state of logged in or always carries with itself the
currently logged in user okay so we're just going to say user and i'm going to
create a constant constructor then for this class as well which in turn is
going to cause automatically for us on off state okay
so that's our state of logged in now let's say that we're going to define
also a logged out state and but also we want
to um we
actually before we go to log out maybe we have to talk about talk about login
when you're trying to log in a user in our application today if we go to our
login view you'll see that upon pressing the button to log in then we're doing a
try a weight of auth service firebase login so we're literally going towards
firebase directly and then if anything goes wrong then we're doing like a user
not found off exception wrong password off exception so we're handling our
exceptions in this way and the way that we need to do this now with uh fire with
block is that we need to produce a state you see the ui needs to only talk with
that block so it says hey block here's an event go log in
and then it says and then a blog is going to do some processing and then
maybe it says oh incorrect user incorrect email
or password is wrong or whatever so that needs to be its own state so
at the point where an exception has occurred during login
that is a state login failure we're going to call it login failure so the ui
is then going to react to that particular state in order to display for
instance an error message to the user like we are doing today so
let's go ahead and say class off state log in
failure and we're going to extend our off state
in here and what we're going to do is that upon
a login failure we need to carry with that state the actual exception that
caused the failure so let's just in here say exception exception just like we're
doing we're carrying the user with us when you log in we carry the exception
with us as well if you couldn't log in okay so that's how you should think as
well so your state should carry with them all the information the ui or the
consumer of that blog requires in order to be able to
fulfill its requirements
so in this case upon not being able to log in
the ui is going to require the actual exception that occurred so that it can
switch on it or do some if statements and see what kind of exception it was
and display the correct correct message to the user
so let's go ahead and then define that and since we've expected an exception in
here i'm going to create a constant constructor here as well
like that oh actually we got a warning here it
says prefer declaring cons constructors on immutable classes that's actually
beautiful yes sorry constant fantastic okay so that's our login failure
then what we need is you remember also i mean at the moment since we have our
counter block uh in here and the counter application that we did in the previous
chapter i can't show you the ui of the application but if you can recall what
we also had is if you try to log in with a user and that user's email is not
verified when they were actually gonna what we are what we were doing is that
we were sending the the user to the needs verification view or something
that we call it let's say let's see very verify email view right so we sent the
user to this view and we need to also we need to also produce that state so
upon user pressing the login button and if our off block realizes that hey this
user does exist but here she hasn't verified their email address then we're
gonna produce a state telling you ui that hey this user needs to verify their
information so let's go ahead and implement that so
we're going to say class auth state needs verification
extends off state okay and then here we're just gonna grab this
as a cons constructor like this all right
so that's that and also after doing that so now we have
login and login failure we have needs verification and we have the loading
state if we're in the middle of for instance making an api call that could
take some time the other state that we need is also
logged out if you're in the log out state then we need to produce that so
let's just say class off state um why is everything yellow
class state logged out
okay and this is going to extend offset as
well let's then make a constant constructor
for this like this great all right so log out when you're logged out you're
logged out there's nothing that the logged out state actually has to carry
with itself it doesn't have to carry the currently logged in user or anything or
even the current user in firebase even if even if you have anonymous users the
logged out state for our application doesn't have to carry with itself
anything okay and last but not least we also have to
define our logout errors and so upon logging out you could also
encounter some errors like if if a firebase for some reason is trying to
make an api call and that api call doesn't succeed then it is going to give
us an error so let's just define that as well let's just say class you see we
have that already for login failure let's go and actually copy that and
paste it here and here instead of login i'm just going
to say log out failure and copy that name and put it in the consonant
constructor as well great so we have one two
three four five and six
um off states so that looks actually really
good so our auth states are now defined okay
and please save this file as well
now we need to define the inputs you see the
states have been the output of our off block which we're going to write soon
the off block we haven't written it yet but these have been the outputs now what
are the inputs imagine in our off inputs we have to think about what the ui what
the ui is actually going to call so the ui is going to send packages of data
to this off block and these packages of data are the events so we need to make
sure that the events can contain with them the data that the
ui can package and send to our off block for instance during logging in what
event is it okay it's let's just say off event login what should it contain well
it should be the email and password something like that okay upon log out
okay that's a log out event what should it contain
no it's nothing it's just a log out event it shouldn't even provide the
email and password it should log out the currently logged in user from the
application so we need to think about events and
their consumers and also the states and their consumers so you have to pack
enough information both into your states and into your events
so that the consumer of your blog can actually both receive enough information
and be able to pack enough information to send to your auth
let's start to your block okay now what we need to do is just go
and define our auth event right here in lib services auth block off state
we have written our off state so i'm just going to close that file and let's
go in the same folder called blocking here you see lib services auth block
we're going to create a new file called auth event so right click new file off
event and marked
all right and now we have our off event and we need to do something very similar
to what we did with off state in that we need to define
a um a super class an abstract class that
basically engulfs all other um auth event so every
auth event in our application is going to be of this type so let's say
immutable and we don't have access to it yet so let's just um
let me just write it for now let's just abstract
class of events and a constant constructor which you now
know why we're creating
an immutable comes from foundation we've already done this so import immutable
okay uh
oh use show
sorry i programming quite a lot of languages python and rust and swift and
you name it javascript so it's sometimes a little bit messy in my head about
imports so um
there are quite a lot of different ways of important things in different
languages so i sometimes mix them up and so now we have our aus event
which is an immutable abstract class so now what we need from the ui is upon it
wanting to initialize our auth you see at the moment let's see actually what we
have in our main dart file this is just us having a
look and you can see here
and that's that's the counter block but how we had it before is if you remember
in our home page we had upon the entire home page being loaded we were saying
auth service firebase initialize so this is a signal from the ui that needs to
now go to our auth block and say hey initialize yourself so
let's define that signal or event let's say auth event initialize
extends off event [Music]
and it has no parameters it's as you saw in main darts it's literally just a
function being called so we're going to represent it with an event that has no
parameters but it has a constant okay
that's that's that okay we have now our auth event initialize
what we also need is an auth event for logging in and as i mentioned it's very
simple it's just with an email and password so let's just go ahead and say
off of event login something like this
or log in with a capital i extends off event
and we need we need two parameters to be passed in here let's just say final
string email and we also need a password so let's
just type that here password and now we have the email and
password we're just going to create a constructor here and make it constant
just like that okay so now we have our login event
and so login event should carry with itself every piece of information that
the auth block will need in the future in order to log in that user into the
into our provider which in this case is firebase okay
so after defining login we also need to define log out now if you have a look at
our um there are so many files in here so views
and we have notes and then we have excuse me we have notes view if you have
a look at notes view if you have a look at this and log out what it's doing as
you can see it's a weight of service firebase log out so
so this is a clear event with no parameters it's just telling the off
block then or in this case the off service that hey you need to log out no
parameters log out the current user okay so let's go and define that as well in
here so let's just say class of
event log out extends off event and it has no parameters as i mentioned
so let's create a constant constructor for it which in turn is going to call
the constant constructor of the abstract class called auth event
all right fantastic those were the only events that we had to define initialize
login and log out so these are the inputs to the block and then we had our
auth states which are the output our outputs of our off block which we're
gonna write uh right now actually
so we have the events and the states the only thing that's missing is the
uh auth block itself so let's go ahead inside this block folder create an off
block file so off block oops block um
dart so
now we need to actually write our auth block and this is for me at least this
is like the most uh this is the most fun
um so
because we're going to put together three pieces of uh two pieces of
information the states and the events and now we're creating the actual login
the logic of our authentication block so this is
very exciting so let's say class off block like this extend block now
it's going to complain saying that well it doesn't exist yet
so let's go ahead and import that import that as you can see here now remember
block if you go into source code it has two parameters there's two generic data
types in here event and state our events are called off event and it's
going to auto import that and then we have to say auth state
like this which also is going to be auto imported
so just like our off service if we go back
to our off service in here you'll see that our auth service at the moment is
taking in as a parameter a provider so we're going to do the exact same thing
in our auth block it's going to say give us a provider to work with is it a
firebase provider or what is it so
but we're not gonna directly go and say give us a firebase provider we're gonna
say give us an auth provider remember that we had an abstract class called
auth provider here
which pretty much defines the uh
the logic or defines the interface for every auth provider whether it's a
firebase auth provider gmail auto provider facebook whatever
that's how the interface should look like okay so what we need to do is to
create a um a constructor and in here what we're
going to say is to give us an auth provider so
we expect an auth provider auto import okay so if you're getting errors here
it's because you have an imported off provider the way visual studio code just
imported it for me right now and let's say that we get
that we call the provider in our constructor and if you remember
correctly from the previous chapter we need to also make sure that auth block
always has an initial initial state so
that's what block as a super class requires so let's see you see that's the
constructor of the block libraries block class that
says it should have an initial state so our initial initial state is going to be
in the k in the state of loading so let's say off state loading
like that and we create a constant
okay so and i can see right now that i'm not using scr cpy so much so i'm just
gonna minimize or yeah i'm just moving it to another
screen so we don't get bothered by it and that
enables me then to increase the size of visual studio code in width so it's a
little bit easier to read so i'm gonna go create a constant here
and then we're gonna create our curly brackets in order to go to the actual
initializer or the constructor of this auth block okay
all right now your job in here inside the auth block is to actually handle
various events and then based on those events produce a state
what is the first event remember this event initialize so if the user tells us
to initialize our uh auth block what should we do well we
should go to that provider and actually tell it to initialize okay
so let's go ahead and do that so i'm just going to say on off event
initialize and remember every on function you see
it takes the the event let's see actually yeah it's
the event and then an emitter it's not so clear from this i mean
from looking at this it's quite generic it's i would say it's
too generic but uh but that's that's the way it is so we
take the event that came in so in case you need to extract some data from your
initialize in this case initialize is an empty
class so it has no data but it when we actually start loading for instance and
we start handling the login event we do need the events to actually come in so
that we can extract this email and password okay but in the case of event
initialize the event is pretty much useless so we could literally ignore it
by just doing something like this okay but we're gonna take it in anyways
so now that we have that event we the second parameter in here is called emit
and emits then allows you to um actually emit and send states from your
off block out to whoever is watching the stage changes in your off block
which is going to be our ui okay so emit is your way out is your communication
channel to the outside world so let's make this function asynchronous
because we are actually gonna call our provider and call some
asynchronous functionality on it so let's go ahead and see if we can do that
so the first thing that we need to do in here is to call our provider and say
initialize okay and initialize you can see is it returns
a future of void so i'm just gonna wait on it all right so then what we're gonna
do is to say okay after doing that we're gonna say
final user is provider current user and that is an optional off user if you
remember from its function signal or from its getter signature you see
now if the auth user is
null after doing an initialize then we know that the state should be logged out
it means we initialize the provider but there is no user you are logged out okay
so let's just say if user is null then we're going to emit a new state and
we're going to say auth state logged out like this
as a constant okay
however if there is a user so so now we have a user we're sure that
we're not coming into this block here that says auth user is null if there is
a user but that user is not email verified then we're going to produce
another state so let's say if
else if uh user
is email verified not so it's not email verified then we're gonna emit
um a const off state uh needs verification
okay so that makes sense as well otherwise we're going to say where our
state is bought state logged in and remember the logged in state actually
needs your user okay so
um that is actually working quite well right now
and now it says user
that shouldn't really happen because the user actually isn't null
so we have already checked the user so we could put let's see what is it
actually complaining about user value of type null can't be
assigned to a parameter of auth user in a cons constructor try using a subtype
or removing the keyword const and i mean i understand this part to be
honest with you and that's correct that's a mistake that i've made in here
and that's because i said a constant constructor is being called with a user
which is a variable so you should also know that we can't do that all right
because user in itself is not const hence we can't call a const constructor
on a on a state that uses a variable user okay
great now we've handled the initialize events
all right what we need to do is to handle the
login event so let's go ahead after this i'm just going to put a comment in here
and just say initialize just to make things a little
bit separate from each other and then log in
i'm going to bring the code up so you see it sorry about that it was a little
bit hidden when i wrote this comment so now you can see how it looks like
then we're going to handle login events so remember again an event is something
that the ui is going to send us and that event if you remember it has a username
sorry an email and a password then we're going to unpack that email and password
provided to give it to our provider and provide it to our provider give it to
the provider and then react to the various results that come back from the
provider okay so
so we're gonna say then on off event login oops yeah login and we're going to
say event and then emit and we're going to say this is an async
function and it goes in here all right so okay
now this is the beauty of a blog using emit you can let your consumers know
what you're up to let's say someone says login what is the
first thing that we're up to yeah we are loading we are in the state of loading
because we are going to start loading and make api calls and that's exactly
why we have these off states in here remember we have the auth state of
loading so let's change our state as soon as you tell us to log in we're
going to say oh now we're loading okay because we don't have a state that says
logging in but we have a general state that says
loading if you want to you could remove this
loading state and just say
i have a class for instance auth state logging in that's also acceptable but
then you have to have a um
something something in uh state for everything like even if
you're logging out you should say off state uh logging out
uh so then you have to have a loading state for pretty much all the states
that do something asynchronous and that's why we haven't done that we
have a generic or a general loading state that indicates to the outside
world that hey you are doing something okay
don't worry about all these saved operations that have been in this off
state file i pretty much i mean i didn't change anything in this file okay so it
is how we left it when we finished off stage
all right so let's in here then emit a an auth state loading
just like that and upon logging in what we need to do
is just to grab the email so we're just going to say email is equal to the event
email and password is equal to the event password okay
and then we're gonna do a try and catch
like this and tell our provider
so we're gonna say await provider um i believe we have let's see what the
problem in here avoid okay that's fine
let's then create a user so let's say final user is equal to provider dot
we have a login function on our provider excuse me
and here we're literally passing email and password to that function okay and
remember login function at the provider level it could
throw an exception but that's fine because we have a catch in here so if we
go to the login function in our auth provider let's see if we can find
firebase auth provider inside the login function let's see if
we can find out here we have various exceptions that are going to be thrown
user not found wrong password generic auth exception so if any of those
exceptions happen we're going to come into this catch block all right
so now that we have a user if nothing happens if no exceptions
happen then we're going to emit and we're going to say const or actually we
can't do a const because a user is a variable so we're going to say auth
state logged in
and it's just going to say give us a user and that's the user
should any exception happen we're going to emit a login failure and we're going
to say emit auth state
oops log
what's it failure login failure i can see yeah
and in here we literally pass the exception there
can't be assigned and then so we probably just have to see i can i mean i
understand this exception as well it's because exceptions in dart maybe this is
a little bit of a side talk but exceptions in dart can be
anything i mean i posted something on linkedin on twitter a while ago saying
that well you can even throw an enum value as an exception and that's
why in dart exceptions are of type object and
in this case i believe they're even object optional object no it's actually
an object so here the error is that you're saying that off state login
failure that needs an exception but you're passing it an object so let's say
on exception if an exception happens then
uh
and that's because we know that our login function is not act let's have a
look at the login function and see if it can throw anything other than an
exception and we see now that it has a general catch
block which throws a generic auth exception which in turn is an exception
so in our application right now as it is we're not throwing anything that is not
an exception so every exception is coming from the exception class
all right fantastic now we have our login um
event in place and we're emitting the correct states logged in or login
failure now we have to handle log out so let me bring the code up and we're going
to say log out and this is very similar to login a little bit less code so let's
just say on again we're going to handle inputs okay
so off event log out so if someone tells us to
log out like this then we're gonna say okay we
take the state oh so much documentation everywhere um
sorry the event and then the emit and then we make this
function asynchronous like that and the first thing that we have to do
again since in log out we're going to call the
logout on our provider which is an asynchronous function we need to tell
the ui about that we need to tell the ui that upon you requesting
log out from the off block you have to do some loading what better way of
indicating that to the output to the outside world by actually changing our
state using emit so we're going to say off state loading okay so that's us
indicating to the outside world that we're doing something
all right so uh let's then do a try and catch in here
cat on exception catch e
like this if an exception occurs then we're going
to say emit
off states failure we had a log out failure and that expected an exception
so i'm just going to put the e in there we could also put this image in try it
doesn't matter because this doesn't really throw an exception it can never
throw an exception but we're going to put it in try catch
because i believe just it's a little bit cleaner it's it's like a transaction
so what we're gonna do is to say await our provider
and log out in here all right and should the logout actually go through then
we're going to go to the next line which is line 40 for me maybe another line
number for you and then in this case we're just going
to emit a const of off state log out
fantastic all right so
that was it really i mean it was just a lot of talk a lot of creation of like uh
classes but um we've now gotten there so now we
have an off block and then we have our auth event and off state so now that we
have those i'm going to close those tabs after you've saved them so make sure
that those files are also saved then what we're going to do is just to
get rid of that ugly counter block that we created in the previous chapter which
kind of is like dirtying down our main user interface so
let's go to main dart and let's grab this
home page the way we have here let's see so let's go in this new home page that
we created for our counter block and just completely remove that everything
that is related to that counter block okay
and then let's go ahead and bring back our normal home page like
that right fantastic uh we have flutter block and block in there
and that is causing a little a little bit of a problem but that's okay
too so what we need to do now is to actually
go and
let me bring up the next captioning here as you can see now we
need to use block provider and block builder and we're going to do that in
our main dart file so i hope you haven't
jumped over the previous chapter because i talked a lot about in the previous
chapter about block providers block builders block listeners block consumers
and what they are how they're different from each other and there's a lot of
information and material available online that you can read also
about all these things online but if you've skimmed over that chapter and
didn't understand really how things worked what we need in here just think
of it that our main application needs to offlock the auth block is responsible
now from this point on to handle everything related to authentication
it is not the ui part remember the ui part is
completely separate that's the goal of block in its core to separate business
logic from presentation logic so your presentation logic everything related to
the ui for instance displaying dialogues displaying exceptions handling etc etc
etc that's all in the ui has nothing to do with all of what but the off block is
going to be responsible for actually initializing the authentication process
and also with with firebase and also allowing us to log in and log out et
cetera we need the auth block so how do we get
off block in our main application since the entire application is dependent on
the auth block even when you're in the main ui of the application you should
still be able to for instance log out then we could literally say that oh
everything inside our application in the main function is gonna be dependent on
that off block so what we're gonna do is in our home page
let's see in here here we're right now saying we have a home const homepage you
see actually let me command s this and bring uh scrcpy bag back here
so now we see our notes back so home page is fixed now
so what we are going to do in here we're going to instead of a const homepage
we're going to replace this with an auth provider okay
now we could do this as you can see we have
um do we have sorry with a block provider
i have the block extension in visual studio code which then gives me the
ability to wrap things with various block
components and flutter block components and you can go to extensions and install
the block libraries extension for visual studio code
if you're if you're using another uh development environment if you're for
instance using sublime you may not have that ability so
what you'll need to do is to write this by hand so i'm gonna take advantage of
wrapping this homepage with a block provider meaning that
my home page now let's see here let's say this is a const as well
is a home page before its creation is
dependent on the creation of a block okay
so let's go in here and say the block provider is also using our off block
which i believe now visual studio code is going to auto import you may need to
import that by hand if you are not using visual studio code or an or text editor
or an id that has this feature now in the create
parameter of our block provider we actually have to create the uh block
that we promised we're going to create and you can see that being created here
so and i can now see directly in here it's
creating a const provider but we can't have that simply because
our auth block if we go back to our off block in here i believe that our
constructor is not a constant so if you put const in there
you can see that it's not allowing us to do that simply because
block itself as a library as a class here it has no constant constructor so
we can't have a constant provider so let's remove that const from there okay
now in here we have to say it should create offlock
and if you remember offblock requires an auth provider so let's go in
here and say firebase off
fire and that's going to be auto imported as well
perfect now we have our
block provider that's fantastic so now what we need to do is to have a look
in here and see what else we have to change in
our main functionality well
what we have at the moment i mean we have
of course we have this functionality here to create the
auth block for us in the main function but we're not actually really using that
in inside here we're using future builder okay
so what we need to do is instead of using future builder let's use our um
what we're going to do is we're going to use block provider
i'm sorry block builder and block builder is kind of like future builder
but it's going to use but it's going to use our
block which is defined here now this may seem
all very complicated to begin with and what you need to understand is that
there is a lot of magic happening behind the scenes in block in that when you
create a block provider in here and then it gets a context and then it goes here
to create the block what's happening internally in block is that that context
itself is gonna get injected with your off block so when you create the auth
login here this context from this point on inside the entire application is
going to be it's going to be populated with an auth
block that you can read from okay and i'll show you now how
so in the build function of your homepage what you need to do in here
we're going to say
see we have this future we have the switch
of the snapshot and that's all fine
so let's just then go ahead actually what
we need to do to be honest with you is to um
we're not going to use so much of this code so it's perhaps makes more sense
just to shift it down a little bit to make room for our
block provider okay so in uh sorry a block builder
so our block builder has a builder function but we also are going to get
hold off our um actual block in here in the block
builder as you'll soon see when you come to your home page what the
first thing that we need to do is to tell our os block to initialize itself
do you remember our auth block has this um event handling for initialize so
somehow in this build function we need to tell our author like hey
initialize yourself so how do we get hold of that
i talked about this how do we hold off how do we get hold of the off block in
here since we don't have access to it here but i just mentioned that
when you create an auth provider sorry a blog provider that blog provider is
going to inject your off block into the context so the the auth block is hidden
somewhere in this context and the way to read that is you just say context dot
read and then there's a you see there's a
function in here and if you go into this read function you see it actually comes
from a provider here so
flutter provider provider dart okay so in context read let's just say that
we're looking for auth walk and what we're going to tell it to is to
tell it to initialize but if you put dot in here you see there is no function
called initialize or anything and that's because the way you communicate with an
auth block as we saw in um or the way that you communicate with a block
generally is that you send it messages using its add function so add is your
way of communicating with your block or your blocks about various events that
you're sending okay so in this in here we're going to say add and then we're
going to say auth event
okay if you're getting an error about this
auth event initialize not being in context it's probably because you don't
have an auto import for this uh file in here which i had so
we have now we are sending initialize events um to our auth block
now that that is done we need to do our block builder so in this builder
function let me go here and get help from visual studio code to complete that
and you can see now i get a context and a state so
so let's go ahead and handle various states that could happen during this
period during the initialization period okay so let's say
if the state is off state logged in so if we are actually logged in then we're
gonna return const notes view like that so that is this view all
right else if state is auth state needs verification
then let's see what we were doing we were returning this verify email view so
let's go ahead and do that here as well now if
excuse me if the state is logged out excuse me again
it's off it's logged out
then let's see how we were handling that before
um if we were logged out we were going to the login view like like here
so if we were logged out then we should send the user to the login view
otherwise if it's not those states
so what can we do let's say that in the
future you're going to add some more states that this
block block builder right now is not able to handle
so um what you want is still an application
that is in working condition you shouldn't crash or anything so
let's just in this case return a scaffold
and make it constant and let's in the body of our scaffold
create a circular progress indicator just like that all right so it looks
like that also you could mark your block builder as well to say that it
has the off block and also it has off states you remember
block builder has these parameters in you see
the builder and sorry the block itself and the state that's why i've marked
them like this okay and now as you can see state is not an uh it's not just a
normal object anymore it's an off state before writing that state was just an
object but now i've marked it as off state and you can see it's become an off
state here as well great stuff now let's get rid of the
future builder that we have from before so i'm going to remove all that code
excuse me and now you can see we have our off
our block builder here and a block provider up there
so that's all we have to do um now it's great actually we're getting this issue
um and you can see it's i love these errors i mean a lot of developers are
scared of stuff like this but it's so important to actually read what's inside
this what is what it's telling us is this happens because you use the build
context that does not include the provider of your choice and that's
because of this you see is this thing context read auth block so
so what flutter is saying that hey you're expecting me to extract an off
block from the context but it's not there okay why is it not there it's
simply because the main function i've mentioned this quite a few times in the
course but i believe it's so important that i want to mention it again the main
function does not get called during hot reloads and i just did a hot reload by
doing command s so there is no block inside the context
because the block is actually created by the block provider which is inside the
main function so if i want this auth block to be injected in the build
context then i have to do a hot restart so
now the application is working as it should all right
excuse me so we've now taken care of our main dart
file removed the stuff that we have for the counter application which we created
with auth with which we created with block and now we've moved to using our
first two components from block which is block provider and also block builder we
have a few unused imports so let's just remove those
okay just to make sure that this file is quite clean
the part is that it's done now what we need to do is to use as you can see in
the caption we need to use our off block in the login view and the only thing we
really need to do is upon pressing the login button we need to send the off
event login to our auth block that's very very simple so let's go
ahead and take care of that this is just easy from
go to login view as the caption indicates and where we're calling this
login functionality here as you can see we're saying
um we're taking the email and
password and we're just yeah calling a login so
let's see we also have is email verified so we're not gonna take care of that at
this point so we're not gonna really
uh take care of email verified so in this in this try statement here verify
email route we will fix that soon so let's just
remove this try everything in the try block
and what we need to do in here we need to read our block our auth block and
then convey an event to it okay how do we read the the a block and that is
using context dot read or what was it called read i believe actually yeah but
remember autoblock and three function is not available
until you import your provider and i can see in here says
package provider src but in the in our main file we didn't actually
import provider so we've imported our flutter block so let's go ahead and do
that as well in here so inside login view dart please import your flutter
block so now all of a sudden we're going to have access to the read function okay
so in there what we what we're going to do is just to add an event to
our let's see if we can get access oh for
that we need probably to import block as well so
package excuse me block
and then okay
let's see if then all of a sudden we're gonna get the add functionality in here
context read oh sorry about that it's because this is a function i need to
call the function so add and i may then get away by removing block from here i
apologize for that we didn't really need to import um
block library as such
okay i understand this is a little bit jumpy that's okay though so all we're
doing is that we removed everything in the try uh block and we're removing
we're replacing that using context read we're reading our off block from the
build context and now we want to tell it to
log in so you remember we had a l off event login
so let's go ahead and do that and as you can see it's going to auto import it for
us so i mean here we have the email and
password fantastic
so that's that all right so that's gonna send that
event and then we have the rest of the exemptions now remember
i understand you may think oh exceptions though how are we handling
them well
we are not at the moment our exception handling is
completely broken by going towards using auth block everything is broken
as far as exceptions go because um you can see the way our auth block
actually throws exceptions is by emitting them inside states so you see
it says a state login failure and then there's an exception in it so we're not
handling those at the moment so you're right exceptions are completely broken
for the entirety of this chapter and that's okay because we're gonna fix them
exactly right after this chapter so now you know what's coming in the
next chapter as well all right that's that's for uh our
login so i don't think we need to do more to be
honest inside our login so let's go into our imports and just clean up the
imports as well
great stuff so that's for login um what we also have to do now is the
caption indicates we have to go to our notes view
um and make sure that we can log out using our
auth block as well so let's go to notes view here
and right now what we're doing is saying we're awaiting on the auth service
firebase logout so we're not going to do that anymore
so we're just going to use our off block in order to log out
so in here let's remove that and just say
that we're saying to where we want to grab the auth block first okay so let's
say context and then we're gonna read our um
autoblock like this and if he asks visual studio
code it's gonna it wants to import um oh yeah it wants to import auth block so
let's grab off block to bring it in it also doesn't know where read comes
from so um
so what we need to do now is to import uh the block library in here so
i'm just gonna
copy that code from my notes so importing flutter block and then
flatter block guard and here i'm actually drilling down inside flutter
block and just seeing that i'm interested in read context okay and read
context is as you can see in the code is that is the function
reading here oh my god there's so much documentation here you see
all right so that gives us the read functionality that we can use in here so
that's the function all right after grabbing our off block now we have to
convey the message of logging out in here so we're going to add an event to
it and then we're going to say we add the event of off event log out just like
that and this is a constant constructor as well so let's just send it send it
through
and after doing that we don't really have to do so much more so
um and we're also not in this case we're
not actually gonna go to to the login view so
what is gonna happen in here i'm actually gonna remove that and we're
gonna start testing a little bit so you'll see how things work okay
so um i'm gonna do a hot restart in here
and see if everything's working as it should so yeah what i'm going to do then
let's test log out okay so in here i'm just going to say this
log out and it says log out or cancel i'll say cancel so
that's working as it should and i say log out and then log out and
all of a sudden we came to the login view but hey wait a minute what happened
we removed this code this code that was here
why is why are we going to the login view without that code so this may look
magical but what is happening is that since the entire application is now
using off our auth block an auth block upon it
receiving the log out event let's go to the off block
so you get reminded of the log out event but what it is saying is that it first
goes to the loading state and then if it could lock the user out and it actually
says that i'm logged out now remember in the main function here we are actually
listening to various events that come from our off blog and when the events
that comes in is logged out we are showing the login view so it is the main
uh is the home page that is doing this work
so it's it is to me it is absolutely beautiful
because we are like removing
uh logic from our code and one step at a time
so inside our login as well uh so what we need to
let's go to the login view here
uh let's have a look in here at login you see after login we're not telling
the application that you have to go to a screen x or screen y
and so we can actually test this so i'm going to say my email address here and
foo bar bath and then log in see it comes to the main screen how did
that do that and that's again because of the main dart you see it first said um
if it's in the state of loading let's see are we handling
loading somewhere no we're not using that um but if if it actually becomes uh
logged in then it says display the notes view so that's how these screens are now
being shuffled and displayed to the user without us
having to do push routes or push name routes so
fantastic very well done we've taken care of everything that we said we're
going to take care of in this chapter so and what we usually do at the end of
every chapter is now that you're familiar with everything you've come so
far almost 40 40 chapters in this course so you should know that we need to tag
our work so that we don't lose them so
let's go ahead and have a look at if i can bring terminal up in here and
we see bit log you can see the last commit was step 22 so let's say git
commit get status first actually a whole new folder was added so we're
going to say git at all and let me increase the size of the
screen as well so we're going to say git commit and um
step 23 okay and push these changes
and we have a look at our logs get to step 22 and step 23 and there is nothing
to commit at this point so let's also tag our work and we say
step 23 and get push tags okay
fantastic so if you look at our tags now we have
20 21 22-23 okay
fantastic as this tradition at the end of every chapter we talk about what
we're going to discuss in the chapter that is coming and um
as i mentioned just briefly as a little note while i was talking
about exception handling we've now broken our exception handling
in that you see when we send an ad
signal to our block our auth block um that in itself is not gonna produce an
exception but right now we're treating that add
function and we're putting it inside a try block and then there's on exception
blah blah after that so none of those exception handling uh
catches are gonna be caught so uh we're gonna handle that and fix
that in the next chapter so grab some refreshments and i'll see you there
hello everyone and welcome to chapter 41 of this philosophy course
in previous chapters we've been talking quite a bit about uh block and
um i suggested that everybody who's taking this course to have a look at
block on their own time as well and to read the documentation because
um i understand that block could be something intimidating for especially
for those who haven't done for us this reactive programming before
however it allows us to create a good separation
and between our ui and our business logic as that's the point of using block
in a flutter application for instance so in this chapter we're going to build
up on top of what we've already done but we're
from this chapter onwards we're going to spend a little bit of time to clean the
logic up i mean even though things may be working the way they are right now
but and there is like a saying in software
development which i usually strongly disagree with that
people say if it's not broken don't fix it however we've seen over and over
again that things that work don't necessarily continue to work or things
that do work right now aren't necessarily working to the best of their
abilities so
in order to make things uh a little bit better in our source code we're going to
spend a little bit of time to make the logic more thorough and we have to
think it more through um we've gotten started with block but we are not really
there yet so in this chapter as you can see in the captions we're gonna handle
off block exceptions during login so there's gonna be
um quite a bit of um moving around between different files
and we're gonna like basically clean things up so we have to jump around
between files and i'm going to do my best to explain
when i move between files as well and like what we're adding what we're
removing and what we're modifying so i hope you can
um you can also follow along
all right so the first thing that we're going to do as you can see in the
caption here is to remove our off state login failure
so what we're going to do is um first of all i'm going to bring the code to the
to the main screen here so you see it as well and i'm going to
perhaps not even bring up scrcpy because i don't really think we need scr cpy
right now so if we look at our um
auth state
the way it is right now i don't even know which file i opened
um if i say command p off state so let's go to the off state dart file okay
and as you can see in here if i if i make the size a little bit bigger
you can see that we have for instance at the moment
um a off state login failure and then there
is an exception in there and also we for instance have off state logged in so it
seems like this is kind of like a pattern that we're following so we have
off state logged in and then auth state login failure with an exception and then
we have off state logged out and then a log out failure
however we're going to clean this up a little bit here and make sure that
we don't have just like except like
too many um off states that we have to handle in our
application okay so what we need to do is to go into our
logged out in here and add an exception so
the point of this is that if you for instance um
are logged out at the moment in the application
then there may also be an exception and you you you probably are asking like how
can a state of logout have an exception well
what we're going to do is that when you try to log into the application let's
let's say you're a complete new user and you haven't logged into the application
before okay you download the application what you what is your state your state
is logged out now let's say that you make up an email
and a password and then you write that in the login screen and then you press
the login button there are no users let's say in the system with that with
those information that you provided then we're going to give you an
exception we're going to give you an error saying that well you couldn't log
in what is your state at that point well
you're still logged out okay but now you're logged out and then the screen
also has to display some exceptions so that's why we're going to build a build
exception right into the auth state logged out okay
so let's go in here and just create an optional exception in here like that and
just call it exception okay and i'm going to get help from visual studio
code to add that parameter into the initializer
and let me do some reshuffling on the screen as well so you see it better and
perhaps decrease the size of the font as well okay
so that was the first thing that we had to do and you can see here
that i've written we don't really need auth state loading in auth events login
so what we're going to do is to go in
our off block so let me just save this file and let's go to off block
and in here we have this logged out with an exception and we're going to assume
fix that actually let's see in here yep let's just say
logged out at the moment and let's pass a null exception in here as well
so i'm going to go to my notes as well to auth block to ensure that i have all
the necessary information to pass through to you
so let's go in here and also fix that so now we're in our off block dart file and
we fixed the error that was caused by us adding an optional parameter
um to our off state um logged out all right so we fixed that now
then the next step as the caption indicates is we're going to remove the
emitting of off state loading from auth event login so
let's go ahead and do that so we're going to go ahead and remove this image
from there okay so we're not gonna display any kind of like a login screen
or anything
okay so um
as you can see in here we're now gonna start using block listener
um i've talked about block listener block provider block builder block
consumer before but for those of you who are not aware of what a block listener
is a block listener as its name indicates and it's only going to listen
to changes in the state of a block for instance our off block and it is going
to allow you to issue some side effects so
a side effect is for instance displaying of a new screen or displaying a dialogue
or removing a dialogue or removing a screen
from your navigation stack these are side effects okay
so they don't necessarily create a new widget
to be for instance uh to replace the current widget that's on the screen
instead they can create something that is on the side as its name indicates so
listener is perfect for that so the listener property
or the listener parameter of a block listener doesn't return a widget except
it's just a void block so it allows you to do something with the incoming state
okay so what we're gonna do now is we're
gonna start using block listener in our login view for
this chapter in order to basically handle our
exceptions because if you have a look at our
login view right now you can see that we have this
text button which reads login and in there we're sending an
event of login to our auth block but we're also handling exceptions in
this way and as we mentioned before these exceptions are never going to
happen in this flow because adding a new event to your
block or any block doesn't necessarily have to throw an exception the way it
works for us if we go back to our auth block and have a
look at our login you can see that if there is an exception what we're going
to do and what we're doing at the moment is like we're saying off state login
failure and what we're what we also need to do
actually is to clean this up because login failure shouldn't really be there
so i'm going to go to my notes as well and make sure that that yeah that seems
to be completely removed so let's go to our off state actually and as part of
what we did in here logged out that we added the exception
let's go and remove this login failure completely okay so now i'm in off state
dark file and i removed off state
where was it um off state login failure because as i
mentioned a login failure is now expressed by the auth state logged out
all right so you're either logged in or logged out
that's how i'm thinking and if you're logged out there may be an exception
which was therefore for instance caused during the
login process so now that we've removed that state auth state login failure in
here we're going to replace that in our osblog dart file we're going to replace
that by auth state and
log out and then an exception in here okay
so that's that
so now we're talking about uh auth listeners so let's go ahead and try to
fix this up so in our login view so i'm just going to go into my notes as
well so if you have a look at our login view
right now we have a text button at the bottom of the screen
which looks like this this is a text button and it has an on press with an
async okay so that is the actual login button all right and this login button
is the one then for now that is going to take care of the exception handling
using our
block listener so as you can see in the cache it says our login view won't be
rebuilt since the state is the same but with an exception
so this is very important to actually understand so let's have a look again at
our auth state in here and auth state logged out
so even if we put an a block listener and
wrap this button this text button here with a block listener
and you see once the application launches in
our off block you can see that first we are logged out okay so when the
application launches there is no user then the state is logged out and then
when you press the login button with invalid credentials for instance
then the state is still going to be logged out but with an exception
however this button won't be able to render or do
anything with those exceptions because from our off blocks perspective it is
the same state one within without an exception and the other one
with an exception right so it is the same state or it is the
same state class at least so
we we are actually going to fix that um but for now we're just going to go ahead
and do some cleanup in here so let's go ahead and as the caption
indicates we're gonna handle some exceptions in our text button in here
so let's go and wrap our text button um with a block listener okay so i'm gonna
do command dots on this and then i'm gonna say wrap with block
listener and as i've mentioned this previously i have this these wrap with
block etc because i have an extension in visual studio code call call block that
is from felix angelov i hope that i'm pronouncing pronouncing his name right
from um very good ventures who are the people who are basically sponsoring
block library so
that is the reason i see all those wrap with block etc in visual studio code if
you don't have that you may have to do this part by hand like to create a block
listener in here but i'm just gonna take advantage of having that extension in
visual studio code and just say wrap with block listener okay
and here you can see it says okay what type of a block is it and i'm gonna just
say it is the off block and it says what state does it have then
i'm gonna say off state all right and then here it says okay do
whatever you want to do now
so um
that was the wrapping of our text button with a block listener so that's that's
just that just went smoothly now what we have to do is as you can see
in the caption is to handle three separate exceptions that might happen
during login let's go back let's take a trip back to our
firebase auth provider um so firebase author provider dart file
and have a look at our login code as you can see in here
and you can see that there could be three exceptions that might happen that
are called firebase auth exception user not found wrong password etc
so we need to handle these off exceptions so user not found wrong
password and generic auth exception okay so let's go in here and just say that
okay if state is um off state logged out like that
so remember inside logged out we could have
an exception an optional exception and that's exactly what we're gonna handle
right now so let's say if
that was you see we said now if state is logged out so now in this code block in
here dart is going to understand that okay anywhere in here state is
auth state logged out so you have access to exception right here okay
so then we're going to say if states exception is
user not found off exception
and we're gonna display a weight show
uh error dialog so let's make this a
listener also async and then we're gonna say show error dialog
and which we've coded before remember this uses the generic dialog so i'm
going to go back here to login view dart and for the text we're just going to say
user not found okay then we have to also handle wrong
password off exception so else if state exception is wrong password off
exception then copy the text here and then in here we're just going to say
wrong credentials
and remember in anything that has to do with username and password it's quite
important that you don't tell the user which part of their credentials actually
incorrect because if i mean if there is a hacker who's trying
to get into the system and just using the ui then if you tell them wrong
password they'd be like ah so i got the email right it's just a password that's
incorrect so try not to tell a user even if it's for
good reasons like if it even if you even if you think well i have no hackers in
my application it is still better just to say wrong
credentials because the user themselves probably already know that their email
is correct or incorrect so they're first going to check their email so if the
email is correct then they are going to know that the password is incorrect and
as you'll see we're going to later allow the user to
reset their password so so just say wrong credentials in my
opinion at least so and then else if state
exception is generic auth exception then we're going to display a dialogue
and in here we're just going to say authentication
error okay
so that's that part done so now we've handled those auth exceptions in our
login view for our text button that says login
all right
so now that we have that what we need to do is to remove the uh exception
handling from the button itself so at the moment we have a huge try statement
not a huge actually we have quite a long try catch statements here that we have
we're catching three exceptions which are now actually being caught here with
our block listener so let's go and not
actually do that so i want you to grab this complex read
and where we actually pass the event of log into our block and remove this
entire try and catch block and just do the context read at auth event login so
your unpressed event or sorry on your on press
parameter of your text button should look very simple just like this email
password and then you pass that event to your auth block
all right so now that that has happened let's actually check this out and see if
everything works and remember this is like the beginning of us moving towards
a better approach of handling our authentication and
routing with blocks so things aren't going to be smooth actually we have a
lot of problems we have to fix but this is just like the beginning so i'm going
to bring scr cpy in here and let's just test this so
i'm going to do a hot restart
and now i'm on the login screen so okay i'm
then gonna go ahead in here and like put my email address
and then i'm gonna put some inquiry credentials in here okay and i'm just
gonna press the login button and now you can see that our block listener is
taking care of that so it's saying oh you're logged out and then it's wrong
credentials okay so i'm gonna press ok then i'm gonna just put an email address
here that doesn't exist and then press the login button and now you can see
user not found okay and to be honest with you if you wanna if you wanna do
what i actually said before that it's better to
not tell the user whether it's their user that is wrong or password you may
want to actually wrap both the state exception of user not found and wrong
password and just display the same message so you could do that by saying
war in here so or that
right so
and then you can just display the same message and then you could just remove
this statement from there so that could also work i'm just gonna leave it like
this but just so you know it is actually better to do that approach which i just
showed you momentarily all right so it seems like our block
listener is working fine in the login view so this was just the beginning and
we have a lot to fix so we're going to fix those things in the coming chapters
okay now that the code seems to be working
for login view let's just go ahead and do what we usually do and commit our
work so that we don't lose the the code if anything happens so
i'm gonna minimize scr cpy make visual studio code a little bit
bigger in here and increase the size quite dramatically
let's have a look at our status we've modified three files so let's just
say it's a git commit and in here
let's actually let's do it at all and then we just do a normal commenting here
that's step 24 okay now that it's done let's just push our
changes to the remote and then let's just also gets get status nothing to
command so everything was committed successfully and then let's just tag as
step 24 i believe right so that's our tag and then we push our
tags and let's have a look at our tags to
this point 23 we have where's 24 and there is 24 so we have everything tagged
successfully great so um as you can see and as is
tradition we always talk about at the end of every chapter we talk about what
we need to discuss in the chapter that's uh to come
and um so you can see our routing and dialog
handling isn't isn't block based at the moment we still have quite a lot of
places in our application that we're seeing for instance navigator of context
push name and removed until or we're doing push names so
so we've handled some bits and pieces of our application and we're using block
but for instance we aren't handling stuff in the register view or the verify
email view stuff like that so we have a lot of work to do and the next
chapter is actually going to be a heavy one but it's going to be such a key
chapter in this entire course that if you could just stick with me
throughout the next chapter then you're gonna see your applications architecture
actually become more and more robust so grab some refreshments if you want to
and i'll see you in the next chapter hello everyone and welcome to chapter 42
of this letter course in previous chapters we've talked quite
a bit about cleaning up our application logic and our authentication logic we've
come a good bit forward with that and we've
um we clean up quite a bit of stuff in the login view and now we're using block
listener in the login view if you follow all the chapters chronologically up to
up to that including the previous chapter
so you should already know about block block listener block consumer block
provider um and block builder of course
but we have quite a bit left and i'm actually proud to say that this chapter
and maybe the next one or two chapters are gonna be like the
glues that bring the application to a lot more tighter point where it will be
ready for releasing to the app store and the play store so if you stick with me
throughout these few chapters that are left
we are going to basically create a lot more cleaner product that is not only
usable by the end user but it's also but it's also architecturally sound so
you're going to be proud of actually releasing this application or maybe even
showing this code to your friends and colleagues so
as a caption in the case in this chapter we're going to talk about moving to
block for routing and dialogues because right now you know routing what we have
in our application is kind of like a hybrid in the main dart file and i mean
we don't have to talk about uh so like abstract concept concepts we can
actually look at our main dart files so if you look here what we've done in the
main dart file we're actually creating a block builder and depending on the
states that are being output by our block we're displaying the correct view
so this in itself is quite fine so there's nothing wrong with this but
we're also mixing this up with custom places in our application where we're
saying for instance context of um let's see actually with navigator off
and you can see we're doing actually that's fine but you can see in our login
view when you press the not registered yet register here button in order to do
the registration of the user then we're doing a navigator of push blah blah blah
so there's quite a few bits and pieces left still in our application that we're
either directly talking with our auth service which we shouldn't be doing we
should be talking to the off block or and we're talking with navigator of
something to do push name so in this chapter we're going to clean
these things up and make make basically our auth block and
the consumption of our off block a lot tighter all right using block and
listeners block builders and um we're all also going to use block
consumers i believe so let's go ahead and do that
so this is i mean
as the caption indicates i mean i've already talked about this maybe i should
have displayed this caption a few seconds ago
but we've already talked about this we should basically tighten up how we're
working with our um routing and our
how we work with off service
and you can see in here we need a few more auth events in order to be able to
achieve this so let's go ahead and open our um
i need to probably do some reshuffling on the screen here so you see the code
better so i'll do what i usually do here and then let's go to our off event
in here so these are the events that we have at
the moment we have log out login and then we have an initialize but we also
have quite a few other ui events that the application is doing in order to for
instance interact with authentication such as
um sending a verification email all right so when you're in the verify email
view and the user presses send the verification email again then that is at
the moment talking with our auth service directly and we shouldn't be doing that
we should be asking our off blog to do that or when you for instance um
ask the in in our verify email view so if you go here you can see that we had
this um log out button or the restart button
so let's go ahead and i'm going to bring scrcpy in here and let's
actually to be able to show to verify email we have to have a user who hasn't
been verified but if you remember from before if you've created a user just
recently or just just now for instance and that
user hasn't verified their credentials then they're gonna always be moved into
this verify email view in which they have to for instance say that yeah um i
am i did they had the ability to send a verification email to their email again
or restart the whole process meaning to log out and just go to the registered
login viewing and so that is at the moment happening directly
you can see it's off service directly to the auth service and we should be doing
that and then there is a navigator of push name then removed until which we
shouldn't be doing either so in order to tighten these things up
we need a few more events in our auth event dart file and that's what we're
going to do right now so let's go to our auth event file and
i'm gonna do the same thing in my notes so um the first
new event that we're gonna create in here as you can see it's called auth
event send email verification all right so let's go ahead and do that i'm going
to get rid of this bottom view in here and also the project structure
so i've already written that in my notes so i'm just going to bring it here to
the to visual studio code so i don't have to write it manually but the event
name should be called off event send email verification the goal is for our
verify email view to send this event to our off block in order to request a new
verification email to be sent to the currently logged in user okay
we also need a register event so the goal is that inside register view so
let's go have a look at the register view right now and you can see when the
user presses the register button at the moment we're saying uh firebase create
user so we're going directly to firebase auth service
and we're saying create user and then immediately we're saying send email
verification so we shouldn't be doing any of these so these three things that
we're doing here are pretty much wrong from the architecture perspective so we
shouldn't be talking with these services directly we should clean this up okay
in order to achieve that we need to go back to our auth event and create a new
oz event called register so i'm going to bring that at the bottom
of login here so let me go ahead and create a new
off event we call it class of event register
and of course we're going to extend our auth event
and for register we need two parameters if we go back to the register view you
see upon registering we're always sending the email and the password so
let's go ahead and do the same thing in here so we say final string email and
i'm going to copy this and i'm going to say just password and get help from
visual studio code to create this constant constructor okay you may want
to make these required name fields using these but i'm not going to do that so
i'm just going to leave it like this with email and password okay
so that's our off event register excuse me
so the other thing that we need an event called should register so um
basically that means for instance if you um haven't really registered a user yet
then we need to send this event i'm actually gonna have
a look in my login view and that is if you for instance go to a
login view in here and then you have a look at this button
that we have in here not registered yet register here that is basically the
event that we're going to implement right now so we're going to tell the off
block that hey you should register user okay and then off block is then going to
change its state to a state that the application is going to understand and
automatically send the user to the register view okay so
that's the use case so um let's go ahead i'm gonna just
check my notes as well let's go ahead and develop this should register and
i've already done that in my notes so i'm gonna bring it at the bottom of off
event register but you will need to write this yourself so it looks like
auth event should register extends off event and it just has a constant
constructor so it's very simple okay so that was for our auth um event should
register
so at the moment if we go now as you can
see it in caption we need also and now we've done the auth events like this
stuff that we had to create in order to be able to handle various
um events that come from the ui but we also need to fix up our states so let's
go to our off state and have a refresher in here you can see we have the state
loading logged in needs verification logged out
and log out failure but we're going to clean this up a little bit and make sure
that we have every state that our application requires in order to be able
to for instance display dialogs or do routing okay
so in at the moment in our off state what
we need to do is to create you see we have this loading state and what we're
going to do is to actually remove the loading state and we're going to create
an auth state called on initialized all right so
um let's go ahead and actually remove this
off states loading and create a class in here say auth state
on initialized because when you land in the application
for the first time you may actually want to for instance
display some sort of loading screen or whatever and we're going to indicate
that the application hasn't really initialized firebase or its
authentication system using this off state uninitialized it's just this is a
cleaner way of indicating to the two the call side which is ui that hey we
haven't yet been initialized so you need to call the initialize function on our
off block okay or sorry you have to send the auth event of
uh initialize auth event okay so let's go to off state so
just to recap i removed off state loading
and now we're going to put in our off state uninitialized so we're going to
say uninitialize extends off state and let's just create a constant
constructor for it as well like that okay
so the other thing that we have to implement as well is to
obviously we've talked about login like here login logged out and then log out
failure etc and and now we actually have to start
talking about what happens when the user presses the register button when the
user presses the register button we also have to handle
the case that yeah we are registering at the moment so it's a process that's
ongoing but we also have to talk about what happens if the registration
fails so we're in the process of registering either it goes fine and then
we say you're registered or we say registry registration failed so let's go
ahead and create a um a state in here right after
uninitialized let's just say class of state
what are we calling it registering extends off state okay and let's just in
here as we're doing in here for instance in
the state of logged out let's just copy this
exception and bring it into off state registering
and then let's create a constant constructor here for our off state
registering and i'm just going to say constant here okay so now we have
registering like that so now we have registering logged in
and we also actually need to remove off state logged out failure
because we well excuse me
we have logged out with an exception
um so let's go ahead and do that right now let's just remove off state log
log out failure as well all right so
excuse me again so that's for off state registering
so as you can see in the caption it says
loading of the logged out state we need login screen to have a loading dialog so
we need is loading in the auth state logged out so let's have a look at
our logged out here and
previously we had this loading state as a separate state so it was off state
loading and we were gonna generically use it everywhere but now what we're
gonna do is to build this loading state into
or to build this loading flag into existing states themselves so
let's then go ahead and say well when you press the login button what
we're going to do first is just to say um actually wait let's go one step back
let's say you just landed in the application but you already have a user
which you haven't logged them before okay so your state is logged out and the
exception is null and we're going to add a flag in here
and say final bool is loading and let's add that is loading to this
parameter in here and make both of these required parameters okay like this
and put a comma there as well like this boom so
when you land in the application exception your state is logged out there
is no exception so exceptions null and is loading is false because we're not
loading anything then you write your credentials and you press the login
button then what happens state is still logged out exception is null but loading
is true then let's just say that you entered the
incorrect credentials then what we're going to do in our block auth block is
going to say ooh you're off state logged out there is an exception and is loading
is false and then you'd be like okay now i
entered the inquiry credentials then you're gonna correct those and then
press the login button again now what are we gonna say we're gonna say okay
all state logged out exception is nothing and then is loading is true
and if then we can log you in that we're gonna
produce another state for you so you see this is how we're using states to convey
the cur like the correct state of the
application to the consumer which is the ui okay
so and this is not like you may think oh how does he know that this is the right
right way of doing things well there is no rights and wrong in here it
is just how you reason about your application
and when i say there is no right and wrong
what i mean is that some things are more right than the others and some things
are more wrong than the others but what you need to find is like the sweet
spot in here which is which is exactly
good for your application and at the same time is not incorrect okay and that
is the definition of write for your application and in this case this is the
definition of right for this application so you just need to find a sweet spot
for your application okay
so now let's have a look in here a little
and talk a little about a little bit about equality um
and what i mean by equality in here is that
you see what i talked about is three different logged out states logged out
with exception null is loading false logged out with exceptional is loading
true and then logged out with an exception and is loading false for
instance so you're producing three different
types of states all of the same class so how will
how will uh your application understand that these are actually different states
so you kind of need to differentiate
between various states of your off state logged out so you kind of need to tell
your application that hey although the previous state was also off
state logged out and the correct like the one that i'm producing right now is
also off state logged out but these two states could actually be different from
each other and in what they contain so you need to kind of create like an
equality and
logic into your states to tell the application hey this
although it's the same is like a new instance of the same state class but
internally is not the same thing and for that we have to implement equality all
right now there is a good package that allows
you to do this in order to implement equality in your applications and in
your dart code and it is called equitable so let's go ahead and import
that and don't be intimidated by all these logs in here it's just because we
have a lot of problems that we're fixing at the moment so let's go ahead and um
i'm gonna change the screen layout a little bit
increase the size and let's just go ahead and say flutter
pop add equitable
stuff like that and you can read more about that so i'm just going to bring up
my safari in here and let's just say
flutter or just pop dev
and let's just say equatable excuse me
and you can see it is actually developed by flutter community dev in here okay so
it's a verified developer in here and you can also actually follow flutter
community dev on twitter as well to get some updates about their packages okay
so we're now importing that into our application and we should now be able to
use that so i'm going to get rid of this bottom bar
and change the screen layout again decrease the font size
okay so in here now let's go and import equitable so i'm gonna just import that
i've already imported that in my notes so i'm just gonna paste that in here you
import equitable like this package equitable slash equitable dart okay
so what we need here is we're already extending an existing class so what you
can do is you can bring in equality in your classes using a mix and so we're
going to say mixing e quotable mix in just like
that sorry with okay so now that we're doing with that mixing
now we have to implement a few functionalities in here as you can see
visual studio code helps me it says create one missing override okay
so i do that override in here and it says okay now we have to override
this property and you can see in here what you need to return is a list of
properties that have to be taken into account when the equitable package can
basically calculate equality in your class and in here what
we're going to say is that we have two properties in here called exception
and we also have is loading so take these two properties into account when
computing equality in the instances of auth state logged out
all right very well done so that's that's what
we've done in here so we've made our off state logged out class equitable and the
reason again for that is that we need to produce various
various um mutations of this off state logged out
and those different mutations with various exceptions and is
loading need to be distinguishable from each other okay and that's why we're
using the equitable package in here
so um this thing we've already talked about
and we don't need the off state logout failure so we we've removed that already
as part of the cleanup that we were doing earlier but if you forgot to do
that please just look at the caption at the bottom of the screen just to make
and just make sure go you go to offstate.file and remove your off state
logout failure and the reason behind that since i explained before is that
now logout failure is actually built in and baked into off state logged out
class inside an exception all right
wow all right let's go to the next section
now
well you see at the moment we have no loading
screens in our application so when something happens when we're doing
an api call for instance or we're um going to our off provider and say login
or send an email verification we have no loading screen inside the application
so there is nothing that indicates to the user that something is actually
happening and we're gonna go fix that up soon so as you'll see we're going to
create a new dialog which does some loading for the user and then using that
dialog users going to understand that okay something is happening i just have
to wait for it okay but the user experience that we have
right now is kind of sub-optimal in that the user presses the login screen and
dependent on their sorry the user presses the login button
and depending on their internet connectivity and the speed of their
internet internet connection that operation could take
anywhere between a few milliseconds to a few seconds so
if you're making a user wait a few seconds based on their internet
connection speed then you have to kind of display to them that you're doing
something well the the usual i mean way that you
could do that is to display some sort of a small loading indicator for instance
on ios natively you have a little loading
indicator that sits on on the status bar that just moves a little bit and it's
very tiny i would dare to say it's less than
20 pixels wide and 20 pixels in height kind of it could even be like 17 pixels
width on height it's very little so it's a subtle indication that something is
happening but that's usually i mean i find that
quite annoying because when something is loading you kind of need to
block the user from trying to press the same button thousands of times so
if you display that little loading indicator on the top on the status bar
then what you also have to do you have to add some extra logic to your
application to block for instance the current register button or the loading
button and you usually don't want to do that but because that's just extra logic
what would make more sense is upon a user pressing the login button or the
register button you want to display like a blocking screen
that tells them that hey i'm doing something okay so don't do anything else
while this screen is is visible on your mobile display so let's go ahead and do
that
so we're going to code a loading screen as you can see in the caption says we're
going to do it in lib utilities dialogues loading dialog so let's go
ahead and do that and bring up my notes as well
i'm going to close all these files just to make sure we've also saved them
because if you close a file in visual studio code at least which we haven't
saved before visual studio is going to display your dialogue saying are you
sure you want to close this file without saving it so it's usually good practice
to close your existing files before you move into doing something new
so that you at least are sure that you've saved those changes okay
um now let's i mean we have some errors don't worry about that so
you should now be comfortable with having errors in your application
because you know at the end of every chapter we're going to tighten things up
and fix things okay so let's go to lib utilities dialog
lib utilities dialogues and we're going to create a
new file in here as the caption indicates called loading dialog dart
and you see this loading dialog what we also have to have in this loading dialog
is to allow
to allow the caller to display this dialog but also to allow the caller to
dismiss this dialog so it's very important to be able to dismiss a
dialogue when the application actually needs for that dialog to disappear so
what we're going to do first is to bring a create a type f in here and we're
gonna call it closed dialog let me just increase the size of that font as well
and we're gonna make sure that it's equal to a void function in here okay so
what we're to do in here we have we're going to create a function that displays
a loading dialog but it also returns back a function that the caller can call
to dismiss it so it may be a little bit of a shift in how you think about
programming if it's the first time you're doing something like this but i
promise you it will make a lot more sense as we develop it so let's say that
we have a function that returns a close dialogue um and we call it show loading
dialog okay and it has two
required parameters so let's put curly brackets in here
and then let's just say we have required build context
and we call it build context or let's just call it context and then
we have a text to display so required string text okay
excuse me
so and now you can see you get this required build context
try changing its name and i'm going to get help from facial studio code to
import let's say material okay
now we have just one error saying that you're not returning anything in here
so the first thing we're going to do is we're actually going to define our
dialog how is this loading dialog going to look like so it's the only thing it's
going to do is just to have a little loading indicator a bit of spacing and
text that is going to be using the text widget to render this
string so let's first define our dialogue so i'm just going to say final
dialog is equal to alert dialogue like this
and let's just go to the next line semicolon
all right and then we have to define the content
for it as you can see content should be a widget so the widget we're developing
is a column because we want like a vertical list of widgets the loading
screen a little bit of a size box spacing and a text widget so you can
render that with column easily and remember column what what column
wants to usually do is to grab as much space as it needs so it could be like
the entire screen long we don't want that what we want for the column to take
as little space as it needs to render its content correctly so we're going to
say main access size oops exercise it should be of type main
access size and we're going to say main exercise of minimum all right
and its children are going to be an array of two constant
widgets of a circular progress indicator like
that and then we're going to say a constant
of size box we haven't used size boxes
before but size box is really good for um creating spacing so
as you can see in here it's just an empty space with a height of 10.
and then what we're going to do in here we're just going to say display also a
text that renders this particular text parameter
in here so like that
now we're we have a little problem here with how this thing is rendered and you
can see they're in the same line and that's why it kind of looks strange
let's put a comma in here and then save the file to get the
formatting correct and let's put a comma in here as well
like that okay so now it's working as it should or
at least it's formatting as it should so then what we're going to do in here
we're going to just say we want to display that dialogue so
let's say show oops
show a show dialog okay
and let's go in here and the context of this dialog and i'm going to bring it
here so you see it the context is the context that we are providing to this
function and a barrier or dismissable and i'm
going to show you the documentation for very dismissible and let's see if we can
actually find that oh
it's not helping me with that but that's okay um
what barrier dismissable allows you to do is to say that if the user taps
outside this dialogue either allow the dismissal of this dialogue or don't and
we don't want the user to be able to tap outside this dialog in order to dismiss
it because a loading screen should be dismissed when we want it to be
dismissed not when the user wants it to be dismissed and also
for those who are ux designers who are watching this course he may be actually
tempted also to for instance um provide a cancel i actually think
having a cancel button in most loading screens is a good idea
because sometimes for whatever reason an application may
not be able to handle for instance different errors and exceptions that
could occur while making an api call and i personally have been in this situation
where a dialogue was displayed to the user and it was just never dismissed
because something went wrong the application wasn't able to handle it so
i personally as a user had to go and force kill the application and restart
the entire process in order to get things working so if you want to have a
cancel button in here it's fine but um i'm not doing that right now it's just
for the sake of simplicity so that we can move on with this code as um as fast
as accuracy as fast and accurate as possible
so now you know what barrier dismissible false does
and for the builder function that's what this um error is here we have to just
say okay we get a context and but in here what we do is just do we
remove we we return the dialogue in here okay so now we're saying show this
dialogue and and then we're just going to say
the return value see we still have this problem with the return value that we're
not returning a closed dialogue and what this close dialogue is just going to be
is we are going to return a function from our function so when the user then
calls that function we're going to pop this dialog it's it's beautiful
so let's just say we return a function an error function
upon calling which we are going to say navigator of this context and we're just
going to say pop okay so that's how you return a function that can be acted upon
and invoked by others so now we save this and you can see we
don't have any errors i'm going to just
resize this a little bit make the font a little bit smaller so you see the code
in its entirety
so now let's talk about loading and
exception handling during the login process so
let's go to our login view and you see here we have already some
exception handling and we also have this off block but we also have this text
button that is doing like manual navigation it says push name and remove
until and we need to clean these things up okay
so let's go inside our login view and so
i'm going to also do it in my notes
and let's have a look at how we've done
things you can see in here we have a block listener at the moment that is
wrapping itself around this text button so we're
not gonna do that we're gonna have the text button exactly the way it is and so
meaning that we're gonna remove this block listener from here okay
so what we could do is as the caption indicates we're just gonna go here to
the scaffold and just say okay we have a new block listener and remember this
should be the off block itself so i'm gonna say off block and this should be
the off state like this so then inside the listener what we need to do is to
bring what we had already
um inside
our text button in here so we have the
exception handling okay excuse me so as the caption indicates
we're going to do this exception handling now inside our new block
listener on top so remove all the code from your block listener for your text
button all the exception handling just cut it
and bring it please up into this block listener which is at the top level all
right and make this an async listener so that you can await on your show or
dialogue okay so that's the first step however we still have this empty block
listener in here so i'm gonna remove that now so all of a sudden you see now
we have the text button in here all right that was fantastic
so then what we need to do is to start handling our
loading screen basically so that is going to be
a bit of code so but don't be scared of that we're going to handle that soon
so in order to be able to display our loading screen we also have
to kind of like keep hold off this um
close handle what do i mean by that let's go back to our loading dialog you
see every time we call this function this is going to give us a function back
so that we can close the the dialog we have to keep hold of this
so that when the states change inside our login view we're going to look at
that previous handle and be like oh we have a loading screen
displayed to the user we have to first dismiss it okay so let's go where we're
keeping hold of our email and password in here and keep hold of a
close dialogue and it's going to auto import that you see so if you don't have
auto import you may have to import this file yourself
so let's say it's an optional and we call it close
dialogue handle okay
so we keep hold of that we haven't assigned to it yet but we're gonna do
that soon
so let's stand in here in the state of logged out and right here just add some
space and what we're gonna do we're gonna say
um do we already have a closed dialog handle so let's say close
and dialog is
close dialog hana
and what we're going to do now is we're going to have a look at our states and
also if we have a closed dialog handle and we're going to display correct
behavior basically so what we're going to do is we're going
to say if state is loading if we're not loading at
the moment meaning that maybe we were loading before
then our goal in here is that saying that if we are not loading and
excuse me close dialogue is not null and sorry
and so
in this case what this conveys to us saying it says that we're not loading
now but we were loading before and that the bot part is coming from
here what we need to do in here then is just to close that dialog so let's just
say close dialog we call that function you see and then we say
close dialogue handle is null
so we're just cleaning that up now okay and then we're seeing now
if what we have to have so what we've
handled right now is closing the dial up but we also have the hell of showing it
all so we're now going to say if the state is loading
and we don't have a closed dial sorry we don't have a loading dialog yet on the
screen then we have to show it so excuse me so let's say if state is
loading and
close dialog is null
then we have to show the dialogue so let's just say close dialog handle is
equal to show loading dialog we pass the context
let's do some formatting in here and let's just say loading
just like that okay and we leave the rest of this stuff in
the code exactly as it is
the next thing that we need to do now is to
as you can see in the caption on the screen we have to hook the register
button to our auth block when register button is tap send the auth event should
register to the block and what we're going to do then is go to
and find this button in here at the bottom of the loading via sorry login
view.dart file and upon pressing it let's just make
this and yeah i don't think it really has to be
any asynchronous code at all so let's just in here let's say that we
grab our off block so let's say context read
and we are looking for off blog in our context and then we're gonna send it an
event and we're gonna send const auth event
should should register just like that okay
so and i believe add event is not async or anything it's just a void so this
function doesn't have to be async so if you had it as async you can just safely
remove that i'm just gonna save this file as well
all right a lot of work we've we're kind of now
almost done with uh our login view so what i'm gonna do is i'm gonna close
all these files that are on the screen right now and we're gonna start moving
towards also blockifying our register view so
let's go as the caption says let's go to register view
and having a look here
at the moment we don't have and i can see in here in the previous
chapters we've been working with cleaning up the login view so
blockifying the login but we didn't do the same thing in register view and
that's fine we're going to take care of that and i can see that by just looking
at our try and catch statements in here you see these things shouldn't be
in the text button so as like but one thing at a time as the
caption of the yeah as i capture the bottom screen indicates we're going to
wrap the scaffold inside a block listener so it's going to be very
similar to how we did it for our login view
command dot and grab a wrap with block listener here and i'm
just going to say this is going to be the off
block and it's going to auto import it for me so very important if you're
getting errors for the auth block not being found in this context it's
probably because you haven't imported off block so and in here we're going to
say off state and that's going to also import it as
well and block listener is not available in this context either because we don't
have a flutter block so that's also going to be all too important so that's
three so that's the three um auto imports and
they're all available i believe so that's
auth block auth state and flutter block so
you could actually bring it next to each other if you want to so you know which
ones to import it's these three
wow okay um so what we need to do that that was the first thing that we had to
handle so
we also as i said now we have to go and start handling
exceptions so this is very similar to how we did and
did it in the login views so we kind of need to get rid of these
so now what we need to do inside this listener of our block listener we have
to handle the exceptions that we are at the moment handling here at the bottom
so this should be very similar process to how we were doing things in the login
view from if you remember so if we oops if i go to our login view you can see we
have this uh block listener and then we're doing this
kind of pattern in there so we're going to do something very similar to that
except we're going to do it in register view okay so
inside register view the state is i mean all the exceptions all the
problems that could arise are going to be inside the um registering state so
we're just gonna first make sure that we're in that state okay so let's say
state is off state registering
and we're gonna say if state exception is weak password auth exception
then let's make this listener asynchronous so
we can do an await on our show dialog so we we say await
and show error dialog and the text is just going to be weak
password okay and then we're going to do another else
an else statement with another if and we say if state exception
it's email already in use auth exception and then here we're gonna display
another dialog then that says for instance email is already in use okay
and um so let's then go to another else
statement so i'm going to just copy this i'm a little bit lazy and i'm just going
to say generic auth exception and then we're going to say
failed to register so these are the various exceptions that can occur
while you're registering for a user okay and you can see in here we have three
uh exceptions we're handling weak password email already in use and then
we also have invalid email auth exception so maybe we could actually
handle that as well so let's just go ahead and add another else statement in
here and just say invalid uh invalid email auth exception so we
just say invalid email okay
so now we've handled those four exceptions all right
so what we need now is to make sure as you
can see in the caption that in register view the register button to send the
auth event called auth event register so let's find that register button that
we're talking about here and that is this text button you can see
it says register okay
so what we need to do is perhaps to clean this code up at the moment there's
just so much information in here that we don't really have to do so go to your
register button please in the register view and just pretty much just nuke this
entire try and all these cad statements the way they are
so now we have a clean slate so now we have just email and password and let's
grab the auth block in here and ask the auth block to do the registration okay
so i'm just going to say context
and let's just say we grab the off block in here
okay as a function
context if i can spell and then i'm just going to say add in
auth events of register
here with email and password just like that
okay so your code should kind of look like
this and put a comma in here to make it a little bit cleaner so just like that
all right
okay that was for register now we have also a
login button in here which right now inside our register view do you remember
if you end up in the registry view and incorrectly so you just tap on some
button and enter them in the registry and be like oh i'm in the wrong place i
want to log in actually instance so we have this already registered login here
button and at the moment that's doing custom navigator or push name and remove
until and it shouldn't be doing that so let's go ahead and fix that up so let's
go in here and remove that code and just say context read auth block
and we're going to basically add an event in here of con of type const auth
event log out just like that okay so that then
is going to send the user to the login screen all right
all right let's move now to the next point as you can see it says send
verification button and verify email view dart
it should send an auth event and when you press it it should send the auth
event send the email verification to the blog so i'm going to go into my notes as
well as well and just find that button and now let's
go in our code in here let's go to verify email view
and have a look at that button that we're talking about which is right here
and at the moment as you can see it's doing all service firebase and email
verification but we shouldn't be doing that
um we should ask our block to do that so let's just go ahead
and first of all remove that code inside the
buttons unpressed and then this button doesn't have to be async anymore
and what we're going to say is just going to say context and read
and but we don't have read remember because we don't have we haven't
imported auth we haven't imported block or flutter
block into this file yet but we're going to fix that soon so first of all just
say read the off block and that's going to also import off block for us so
that's the first part and now you have this error let's get visual studio code
to import the same provider but i actually want
flutter block so let's go ahead and import that ourselves
so let's say package flutter block and flutter block dart
now it's fine alright so let's in here and then add an event we say const off
event send email verification just like that
all right so it's done now
so the next thing we have to do is you can see inside this restart button at
the bottom of the screen at the moment it's doing quite a lot of work
it is basically first logging out from our auth service and then it's doing
navigation so this button is like all over the place it's taking care of
authentication it's taking care of i mean i'm actually very i'm laughing here
because i'm kind of laughing at the progress that we've made so far and that
we've gone from very very raw programming to
now very elegant handling of exceptions alien handling of
routing etc so it is actually really fun to be here to be honest with you
so in here let's remove that code and kind of grab this thing that we have up
here in our send email verification button and bring it down here instead of
sending the off event send email verification we're gonna send alt event
log out like this
excuse me all right so that part is done
so what we need now let's go in now let's
close this file and go to our off block so we have quite a bit of work now to do
in our off block as you can see it's just all over the place so
i want to do the same thing in my notes as well so off block
the first thing that we need to do is make sure that we are not using this off
state loading because we don't have that anymore what we have is off states on in
each light so please take care of that as a first name
so we also have now an auth event send
email verification and we haven't handled that yet so let's go on top of
this initialize i'm just gonna send say send email verification okay and let's
create a new on to handle auth events and email verification because we
haven't handled that so we have event animation here and
let's just go and say this is an async function and then open it and then a
semicolon at the end to get the format uh formatting working
the only thing we have to do in the auth event send email verification to
actually call and tell the provider that hey um we're gonna basically send an
email verification all right so let's just let's just say a wait provider
and email verification and then what we're gonna do we're gonna emit the
exact same um state so by coming into by sending this event
we are just going to do some work and emit the exact same state that you're in
so we're not actually changing the state of the application because remember when
you're in the verify email view and then you press the button to actually send a
new verification email what happens on the screen nothing we're not like doing
anything it's just we're sending the email verification that's all so we're
not sending you to a new screen or anything like that so that's why we're
emitting the exact same state as we had before
all right now we have to actually handle a
our auth event register so let's go ahead and do that so that is
completely new so let's just say on off event register
and we say we have the events and the emails and an asynchronous function just
like that all right
so when we have the auth event register if
you remember from before this authentic include the email and password in itself
excuse me so we can grab those and that
information right now just say email is advanced.email and let's just say final
password is events.password oops
all right so then we're going to put this into a try and catch block so we're
going to say try on exception catch e
when an exception happens we're just going to emit our
off state registering with that e um
so we talked about this before but just to
refresh when you're during the process of register we actually can emit a new
state in here just called registering and then it can it can contain an
exception all right so that's what we're emitting in here saying that you're in
the process of registering but something bad happened which is an exception all
right
so in here then let's just say await provider and we're going to create a new
user with the email and password they just fit right in so that's really great
and then if you remember from the registration process that we had before
so um in our register view during registration
here upon doing a registration we didn't just
register the user with the provider but we also send an email verification just
to make sure that the user doesn't have to go and send an email verification and
manually so we're going to do the same thing in our off block okay
so let's also wait on the provider and we say send email verification just
like that all right um and then after doing that since you
registered a new user well what is the states if you remember from our
off states off state
we have this needs verification we know that when we register and use a new user
that user is always going to need verification right so let's go in here
and just emits that state so uh auth state needs verification just
like that and that's an empty state so it doesn't have any parameters and such
all right
all right um then we have to handle our auth event
initialize so let's have a look in here and see how the code look looks like so
in here what we need to do at the moment we have logged out but you can see we're
not providing that is a loading parameter and we're not providing
exceptions so i'm just actually going to click clean this and write it by hand
manually so in the emit let's just emit a const
off state
uh logged out
all right so
when you initialize the application from the beginning when the application
actually runs we're just gonna say by default you're logged out all right
so let's go ahead and do that if the user is null of course
so in the exception we don't have any exceptions and we're not loading
anything as such so that's like the default state so that's it comma in
there and a comma here just to get the formatting working
all right so that seems to be fine but
we also have the initialize in here sounds good logged out
it's email verified and that so yeah that looks that looks fine to me
okay now let's have a look at logging in as you can see we have to take care of
our login and logic a little bit and make sure that we're loading so when you
say i want to log in we're going to say okay you want to log in that means
you're logged out but you're logged out and there's a loading screen okay that's
why we created that loading dialog which we're going to put into you so
so upon the user asking to log in let's just say okay we're going to emit our
const off state
log out and there is no exception and the
loading flag is actually true so like that and right there and just
like okay so
that's the loading part and let's have a look at how we're doing
things in here so we have our login um
and we also as you can see in here so that that was that part we've taken care
of and now what we have to do is to disable disable the loading screen if
email is not verified so um at the moment we have this user in
here you can see final user okay and then we're just saying
state now is all of a sudden logged in but that is not complete
because we're not checking whether the users
verified their email address or not so let's go ahead
and say as the caption indicates if email not verified then disable the
loading screen by sending a new logged out okay before sending the needs
verification so let's take care of that so we say if um user is email verified
not and we emit
a constant of auth state logged out like that
and we say well no exception and we're not loading all right
so that disables essentially the loading screen okay by saying it's loading false
remember here we sent is loading true now we're sending is loading false
and then right after when the email is not verified we
actually say then emit a const of off
state needs verification just like that all right
otherwise if the user's email is verified then we're gonna say we're
gonna first disable let me bring up the correct caption so
we have to do the exact same thing in here we're gonna disable basically the
loading screen like that
and then we're going to send this login
states right here okay
all right and also in our exception handling we we don't use this uh um yet
we're gonna use off state logged out but we're gonna clean this up so inside emit
we're gonna say auth state logged out and then there is an exception and we