say context block auto import
and we're going to call it password reset it's one of the keys i define and
in here we're going to say context lock password reset dialog prompt okay
and we have an ok button so you now by this point that we have an ok key as
well in our in our arb file
so now we've done basically we're done uh localizing the show password recent
dialogue uh uh show password reset sends dialogue
okay the next uh dialog is um forgot password so let's go to
that screen that sorry this is not a dialogue this
is actually a view so we're going to go to forgot password view
here i mean when it comes to views our job is a little bit more difficult
because up until this point we've pretty much everywhere
used constants like if you look at this is a constant string here's a constant
text here is constant so everywhere that
we're going to localize our strings and we were using const before we have to
remove that cons now because our localized properties inside arv funds
are unfortunately not defined as const and i don't really know the reasoning
behind that simply maybe because there are
getters and maybe getters can't be constant or there are some
other problems with the generation maybe that um the flutter team decided that
well these can't be constants but that's something that's the truth that we have
to live with at the moment so let's go ahead and find all our strings
and we're going to start localizing them one at a time before i got password view
so here in this show error dialog and i've called this key forgot password
view generic error so let's remove this string and just say
context lock let's auto import log
and we say forgot password
view generic error and i'm going to put a comma at the end so it's formatted
nicely so let's go to this forgot password title itself so i'm gonna
remove the const remember i just explained that so we're gonna say
context log and we're gonna say forgot password that's the key i've defined
and you can also see its description here and you can see it says forgot
password okay in english this message translates to
forgot password okay so this thing i've called it forgot
password view prompt so let's remove the const remove the string itself and we're
going to say
context log forgot password prompt forgot password view prompt and put a
comma at the end and let's have a look at the documentation for this as you can
see it says if you forgot your password simply enter your email and we'll send
you a password recent link okay so that's one thing and then in your
email address um it says input decoration your email
address because that's a forgot password screen let's go here and have a look at
it see how it looks like here i forgot my password so here's that
little input decoration so
i can see i've called it email text field placeholder so let's remove this
const and in here we're going to say context log email placeholder text field
okay let's go ahead and have a look at this
one so let's remove the const it says send me password recent link and i can
see that i've called that forgot password view send me link so
context log for god password forgot send me link here and put a comma at the
end so the dart formatter gets busy with formatting the code and
in here back to login view i can see that i've called it forgot
password view back to login so context
here context lock forgot
back okay so and this is this is a technique that you can also use like if
you want to get like a property like this that's quite long name and you want
to get the name immediately right you could just write a few keywords of that
name for instance i know that for god and back are quite unique names so if i
say forgot back it it's gonna show me that so
it has this like partial search kind of in its intelligence which is very very
useful the next thing that we have to do is to
go ahead and localize our login view so i'm going to close the screen forgot
password view and go to login view login view right here and we're going to
start at the bottom at the top of the screen and
we'll remove this unused import right there in login view
and let's go ahead and start by uh localizing our dialogs so the first one
is cannot find a user with the entered credentials and i've called it cannot
find user or login view cannot find user so i'm
just going to say context.log let's auto import log
or it was already imported okay that's great and let's just say it is called
login error cannot find user cannot find user okay
the next one i'm going to put some commas in here get dark formatter to do
its job correctly and i'm going to press command s to save the file and that's
going to format the file for me for wrong credentials i've called it login
error wrong credentials so context log and wrong credentials
next one is authentication error and we just call it login error author so
context lock author okay so that's that one as well now at the top of the login
login view we have this little text that says please log in your account in order
to interact with and create notes and this one i can see
i've just called a login view prompt but i wonder what
happened to our title as you can see we have this my title now that we're in the
login view it is a good time to actually go and get rid of that okay so i'm going
to open um intel
e and arb and i'm going to kill this basically my
title and i suggest that you also go to the swedish file which is intel sv and
kill this title as well okay so we've removed that and i'm gonna get rid of
that then i'm gonna hot restart so that the code generation
kicks in and as you can see in here my title isn't valid anymore and in this i
mean this title is called now login if you can look at the documentation in
here you can see in english it just says login fantastic
so let's remove this constant here from the prompt as well and we're just going
to say context lock and let's just say login prompt so i'm going to do a prompt
okay so for the enter email um
text field placeholder here enter your email here we're gonna remove the const
and let's just say context lock and we're gonna say email placeholder
okay and we also have an enter your password
here placeholder so let's remove the cons in here i'm just gonna say context
lock password
placeholder okay password field password text field placeholder that's the full
name and we have this uh login in here so
what we need to do is just to change this text as well so let's remove the
content here i'm just gonna say context dot walk
login and i forgot my password so i'm going to
say context lock and i believe it's called forgot password
login view forgot password okay it's not a constant anymore and put a
comma here it's just good practice to put comma at the end of your parameters
even if it's just one argument that you're passing to a function i mean my
reason this is a little bit of a side though but my reasoning is that any time
in the future anybody anybody wants to add new parameters to this text widget
then they will have to go and put that comma in there but if you as a
programmer who wrote this code in the beginning you put the comma in there
you're kind of like acknowledging the fact that hey i appreciate your time you
may be wanting to add now you may be wanting to add new parameters to this
and i've already prepared this for you so if you don't do this if i want to as
a programmer add new parameters in here i have to go and say oh well okay comma
commandments go here blah blah but if you'd added that already i'll
just say enter and then write my parameters
okay great so what we can do now is to scroll forward here and localize the
rest of these properties and it can't i can just see here that we have one
property left here which at the moment says not registered yet registered here
so let's go ahead and remove the const as we usually do then and say contacts
lock and i can see it's called not registered
so let's use that and a comma here so we prepared for the next programmer so to
say and we could just say now that we have
successfully localized our login view at the moment so we could just close this
tab the next step is to localize our
register view so the register view also has quite a few things that we have to
localize so let's go ahead and go to register view
and while we're here i mean this is what i'm again i
when i started this course i wanted you to become a software engineer even if
you were like a designer a ux or whatever or project
manager and you have to put yourself and your yourself in the shoes of a software
developer software developer you're always in like time constraint usually
our time concern to deliver but at the same time
when you stumble upon something that is quickly fixed please do it on
right there uh at that point because if you leave these things they're gonna
pile up and many small things that could be
corrected on the fly if you just leave them they're gonna become a big pile and
then you're not gonna be able to have enough time to fix them all so while
we're here we have two unused imports let's just remove them because that's
just good practice not to have unused imports
now let's go to our register view here we can see there's quite a lot of errors
there are four errors so the first thing i'm gonna do is to put commas at the end
of these right there and i'm going to press
command s on macintosh or control s on windows linux and that's going to do the
formatting the first one is called weak password so
let's just say context lock and also import this
and this message is register error weak password so weak password
like that the next one is called context log and
it's called an email already in use okay fail to register i've called register
error generic
so context lock generic
here it's register error generic and this invalid email is called context
lock and register invalid email okay so those are our errors we didn't have
to change anything with constant because these messages weren't constant when
they were passed into this constructor
then we have to fix this register's title and it's just called a register so
i'm going to remove the con const i'm going to say context log register
here and then we have enter your email and
password to see your notes and i've called that the register view prompt
so context lock register view prompt we have this input declaration again
we've done this before with the email and password so it's nothing surprising
so let's just say context block email placeholder and this one is
a password placeholder so let's remove the const
a context lock password placeholder all right so that's that
then we have the register button that we also have to
localize and let's remove the constant here and just say context
lock register and already registered is called already
registered so let's remove the constant const as well
and we say context lock already registered
all right and a comma at the end as well and we could do the same thing in here
with a comma at the end just to do the formatting right okay
so this seems to be ready we've now localized the register view
and the next step is to localize the verify email view so i'm going to close
this file and let's go ahead to verify email view
and again we have two unused imports let's remove those and let's go ahead to
verify email in here and we've just called it verify email so i'm removing
removing const saying context of lock and
let's say verify email okay and this is one thing that i've also fixed and you
could see that in how we've developed the application so far we have two
texts on top of the verify email view and they kind of look like this if i
bring it up let's go to
try to log in with a user who hasn't verified
his email
and you can see we end up here we've sent you an email verification please
open it to verify your account and this is like there are two text
fields but what i've done is i've made it one text prompt so let's just remove
the second text field and the way i've created this it's um if we go to our
intel en rb and if you look at the verify
prompt you can see i've written we've sent you an email verification please
open on your open it to verify your account and then
the rest of the string it just follows along so it's just one paragraph
and so that's why we're removing the second text in here
so and we're gonna remove this const i'm gonna remove the text
and then we're going to say context lock
verify prompt okay and a comma
we have this a little text button in here that says send email verification
and this looks like this let's change that as well and here we're
gonna say context lock
and it is called verify send email verification put a comma here
okay and for the restart button we have a
restart text so we're just going to say context log restart
and a comma at the end all right so that's the localization of this
screen as well so we could say we're pretty much done with the verify email
localization as well and while we're here to be honest with
you we could also clean up a little bit here in this verify email while we're
basically cleaning up the view itself you can see that this text doesn't have
any padding what we could do is to in this whole column actually
maybe pad this text so we're going to say this text is padded wrap it with a
padding okay and we could just say padding of 16. so
you can see now it is a little bit cleaner it's just a very little uh
effort to make the the ui look a lot cleaner okay
so we're done with that screen and what we need to do um we need to actually
localize the create update node view so let's go ahead to create update note
view another unused import let's remove that
and let's have a look at what exactly we have to
localize in here it's probably the the views title so if we scroll down to
where we're displaying the new note so if i log in with the user who has
verified his email address this user
our baz horrible password please don't use that
password at the moment you can see in here
we're basically saying um sorry new note here
we're saying new note and that's this thing so let's just change that and say
context dot lock auto import disk oops how to
import this and then we're just going to say note
okay and you can see in the documentation it
says it just in the english one says note so here we're not saying new notes
and the reason behind that is that up until this point our application is
being say new notes but what happens if you tap on an existing note
it still says new note so that's the reason i've decided to basically change
this text just to say note and put a comma in here to prepare for
the next person as well and what we're going to do and is also
to change this text decoration and which is here it says start typing your note
okay so remove the const and then in here we call it start typing
your note so context log start typing your note
all right great so we're going to save that as well
and we're done with that so now we're going to go to localizing our
notes view and this is i would say this is like the most exciting localization
part because we need to do some more coding it's not
as easy so for just two just to because remember in
the beginning of this chapter i mentioned that arb files are more than
just normal json in that they can have logic in them and at the moment if we go
back to our let's see if i bring scr cpy here at the
moment you can see it just says your notes
and i wanted to kind of demonstrate how arb files can be quite dynamic and can
have logic in them and i thought okay how do i demonstrate that to you and
what i decided to do is um
that if you
land in this page and you have no notes like in this case at the moment it says
your notes but what we're gonna do is to say okay we have some some key in our
localization file that is called your notes okay or sorry it's called notes
title is a key but this key is going to have
some value that has actual logic in it and this logic has to do with the plural
pluralization of this key if you have no notes
in english we're going to say no notes yet
if you have one note it's just gonna say one note
and if you have other number of notes such as two three
four then it's going to say x
notes for instance x being three notes four notes so it's just gonna say four
notes so no notes yet one note or x notes
so it has pluralization built into it and how we have to do that is to use
something in arb called placeholders and i'll show you how to do that right now
so let's go ahead first into our intel en
and at the bottom of the screen here what we're going to do is to first
create our key so that's the most important one okay so we're going to
call it notes title and in here we know that we're going to
have some value and let's see we have also a semi sorry a colon there okay
so we have notes title how do we put our logic in here
we just know that we need to have some sort of a
account you see your localization arb file doesn't know
anything about the count because it's the application that knows how many
nodes are available in the in the fire store database so
somehow we need to pass this count to our application
sorry to our arb file and you do that with parameterization so you go ahead
and create curly brackets in here and you would say okay hey i want to have a
parameter called count this count needs to be passed to this
um notes title in order for it to be able
to calculate exactly what it has to return so it's just you
saying that hey application if you want to get the notes title localized string
you have to pass a parameter to me call count okay
now what we're going to do is to go and call and basically and create discount
as a parameter so what you have to do is to go to the next line and just say adds
notes title this is how you tell arb that hey
this notes title key has some extra logic in it okay
then there is a key in here called placeholders
so you have to write placeholders okay and in here basically you say
placeholders and then every key is the name of the parameter itself so account
all right and then you basically start that and then what you have to do is you
have to define two keys in here one is a type
and the oops type and then the other one is an
example
like this so let's have a look at how this actually looks like
so basically what we're telling and
arb is that or dart in this case we're saying that hey this notes title key in
our arab has a parameter called count and in in here we're saying hey
these are the placeholders the name it's count and it's type now you have to
define a type you have to actually tell dart that hey
what data type is this using is it a string is it's an integer is it a
boolean what is it so in here you just say it's an integer and then as you'll
see soon the code generation then has a look at this and says okay i expect you
to send an integer and it's going to create a function called node's title
with account a parameter of type integer so this is very important it's the data
type of that count parameter okay and an example is just for you to know
okay how is this going to be used so an example is for instance three nodes okay
so we're just going to say here's an example of how the result of this thing
can look like right
so what we need to do now is to tell this um erb and dart code generator here
that this count actually has a logic about it being plural so it has
pluralization logic and the way to do that is you put a comma here and you say
plural and a comma after that because then you have to specify the logic for
that pluralization so and look
as a side note i completely understand that this is so weird i mean it is a
strange syntax i don't feel comfortable with it i sometimes use i sometimes look
at the documentation just to be a reminder of this
logic but the way i look at it is that it's the best thing we have let's not
hate on it let's just use it let's understand that it has power there are
reasons for it being the way it is and even though we are not 100
like in
in we weren't involved in the reasoning of this we don't even know what the
reasoning is but this is what the format is and this is what we have to basically
go with so the way to create this is for you to
uh have your logic in here so we're going
to say equal to zero and let's just do it like this and then
we're gonna say equal to one and then we're gonna say other
okay so this is how you create it so you're
saying that if the value of this count is zero
then we are going to do something here if the value of that count is one we're
gonna do something here and if it's anything else denoted by other we're
gonna do something in here so let's say when it's equal to zero we're gonna say
no notes yet okay so that's the string
we're gonna display if the count is zero if it's equal to one we're just going to
say one note and then the important thing is if we
end up in this situation if it's other then we want to say in this case we
actually want to get the count so if you pass the value of three we want to say
three notes so the way to get that count is with another curly bracket pair and
you say count and then you say notes okay
so that's how you create these things so um and i think we're actually missing a
curly bracket and that is the the curly bracket at the end yes
this curly bracket which belongs to like if we
if you look here if i remove these
the other has two curly brackets and
it's two curly brackets and here other one curly bracket there one curly
bracket here one ends here and one ends here so this last curly bracket here is
for the curly bracket that started here so again i i don't know what to say this
is the format the way it is we just have to live with it okay so we've created
the notes title and what we're going to do is to go ahead and do the same thing
but for swedish and i've already prepared that so i'm just going to go
ahead and grab that string from the swedish one that i've
already made so we don't have to type all that again
so let me go and grab that and bring it into
l10n sv which is for swedish and then bring
it at the bottom of the screen and paste it right there and with a
comma at the end of that line so you can see plural and it says no notes yet
for one it says one note and for other it just says
x notes all right
so i'm gonna save this i'm gonna save this and i'm gonna do a hot restart
let's just hope that scr cpy doesn't crash and it didn't
so what we're gonna do now is i was as it was planned we're gonna go to our
notes view and i'm gonna go to my notes as well
here let's go to notes view and have a look at our title in here
and you see we at the moment we're seeing your notes but what we really
want is to be able to display the number of notes that are
inside our um inside the nodes provider so if we have
a look at how we're reading the num and the notes you can see we're using the
note service and then we're saying all nodes and this is a stream
of an i triple of cloud nodes so we kind of wanted stream builder we want a
stream builder to create our title our app bar and we're going to exactly do
the same thing so we're going to have a stream builder that creates our app bar
okay but
or actually it's going to create the text but how do we get the count of
the notes and the way to do that is with a little handy extension that i'm going
to show you how to create so let's go in here in our notes view and
we're going to say extension and we're going to say count
and we want to create it on a stream so we're going to say any stream has to be
able to like any stream that has an iterable in it
that its values are iterable we want to create a
property called length for instance that it gets the length so
let's go in here and say okay this stream has some value but we want that
value to be iterable
okay so here we're basically saying that we're extending any stream that contains
uh i troubles as its value is gonna have this extension
then we're gonna say okay the value of this is gonna be an hint
and we're going to call it get links okay
and what this is basically going to do is to
say it maps the stream's values so let's say event
and in here we just say it returns the event's length so i understand this may
be a little bit cryptic for you to understand but um
you have to know that every stream is a generic function like if you sorry
it's a generic class you can see it's abstract class it's it has a parameter
called t which is it's generic type so what we're saying here we're saying that
okay we're creating an extension on any stream whose parameters or whose types
are and i treble and iterable has a length
and that means that we can then extend and extend any stream that has an i
treble and then we return its property called get length okay
so what we need to do now is to go ahead and inside the app bar in here
we have a const text when we need to remove this const first actually let's
keep it and i'm gonna see if we can wrap this with a stream
builder now okay so in here what we're gonna do is we're saying here's a stream
builder and we don't yet know what it is it's stream is
note service like this and we have all notes
and the owner user id is our user id okay as exactly as we have it here
okay but here the stream we don't actually want the notes we want the
length of notes so let's just say get length
where is it here get length okay and now we know that snapshot can then
return that uh value for us so if i press command s in here let's put a
comma here as well you can see nothing has changed it just
says your notes because we're still seeing your notes in here okay but what
we want is to grab the data out of our snapshot and this snapshot is an async
snapshot of an integer
let's see undefined class it's called async snapshots yeah just like that all
right so you either could tell a stream
builder of int and then your snapshot i believe
automatically will be as facing snatch out of it or you could
just say stream builder normal stream builder and an async snapshot of it so
you could type it in two different ways and i've just chosen to do it this way
all right what we need to do in here is to see as
soon as snapshot has data then we grab that data which means it has the length
built into it okay so we're going to say if snapshot has
data which means it has length otherwise we're just going to return
const of text nothing meaning that well well we don't have anything to display
at the top of the screen if this snapshot has no text all right
and then in here we're going to say it's going to say final note count
is snapchat date okay
or zero because it just says yeah i may not have data
just strange because you're actually saying has data but these two properties
are kind of like they're different from you i mean
they're not different but they're separated from each other just because
you're checking something has data doesn't mean necessarily that the next
line should understand that it has data the data type
of this data property is still final t so you can't change that okay and that's
why we have this um elvis sign kind of here
or a question mark question mark just to say if this doesn't have any value just
use zero okay now that we have node count we have to
get that context block
and we oh we don't have log let's import that
and remember the key that we used intel me and it's called notes title let's say
notes title and now all of a sudden you can see it is a function that takes in
an integer hello that's the count integer that we built into our arb and
it returns a string you can see here that's perfect because then we can pass
the note count in here okay
and this will be our text
and then we could just say return
a text widget with that text in it just like this
all right and then we can save this and as you can
see now as soon as i hit command s it says no notes yet
if i say and if i press the plus button here you can see i can type something in
here and i go back it says onenote if i create another one
on top of the screen it says two notes and that's it pretty much that's the
logic that we built into it so now it says onenote delete that note and it
says no notes yet perfect so that logic seems to be working fine for us
so that's that part and we also have another string at the bottom of this
screen which says log out and we have to change this as well so
we have to say context log out button
and this error is because we it says invalid constant but you're like oh but
this is not a constant well the problem is a little bit higher up in that when
we created this array of pop-up menu items we said that is a constant so
let's remove that okay so that's fantastic and that is i mean
now we're pretty much done in the entire application we don't have
anything any string that is hard coded and if you look at our problems
section there are no problems to fix for instance no unused imports so we've
taken care of those as well and just to test this what we could do is just to go
to the settings screen here and i'm going to bring swedish up
and let's go back to our application here and have a look and it says no
notes yet i'm going to press the plus button and i'm going to write some
string go back here it says one note
create a new one and it says two notes delete this one and all the you see all
the dialogues are now in swedish yes delete this note
yes let's try to log out now and it says log look at it
and it says look go to add a second by the way look at it are you sure you want
to log out yes log out and you can see all our strings here basically are also
um everything in this screen is also
localized so that's fantastic we basically did what we
were supposed to do and what we promised to do and that is great congratulations
if you then and do what we usually do at the end of every chapter we
commit our work so i'm gonna have a look at this and let's have a look at our
good status and have a look at our git log as well
i'm gonna change the screen layout a little bit sorry about that so you see
the code better remove scr cpy make this full screen
okay i'm gonna make this a lot larger so you see better
and have a look at git log again and you can see the last one we did git step
sorry step 31 so let's just say git add
all hit commits that 32
okay and get status
great and then we're also going to get push our changes
and let's tag it as well get tagged step 32
and if you look at our tag all our tags we can see 20 blah blah
let's see if we have 31 30 31 and 32 great and then we have to push our tags
as well fantastic so
um what we've done so far is i mean we've
done a lot of work and in this chapter even more we've localized our
application we looked at how localization works how code generation
for localization works and also we had a look at some
important extensions that you can create in order to make your localizations even
work better for flutter and we also had a look at adding some logic to our arb
file with pluralization so congratulations for going through this
chapter i believe personally that is very important to localize your
applications you're going to reach a lot more users if you localize your
applications correctly for your for like your target markets
and um it should help your users also feel more connected to your application
so um with that said i may actually then
see you in the next chapter hello everyone i can't say welcome to
this chapter now because this is not really a chapter on its own rather it is
the outro to this course and i don't know it's a kind of a bittersweet moment
because uh i've had so much fun putting this course together for you and now i
have to say goodbye and um
i don't want to get emotional but it is kind of sad uh as it is a great moment
of appreciation for you having gone through
this course and also i want to really extend like
and congratulate you for having gone through
this course and having learned as as you've learned because it's it's not
an easy thing to do to go through such a lengthy course but as i mentioned in the
beginning of this um course if you remember in the
introduction i mentioned that um a lot of videos basically jump over
quite a lot of information and i didn't want to do that in this course and
that's why this course has become as
lengthy and long as it has so
we've gone through a lot we've talked not only about
flutter development but we've also got our hands dirty with some
native ios and not really development but all actually going to xcode and
fiddling around with some properties in info plus an excel project we've also
had to open android studio to create our virtual devices we've worked with
figma and design tool we work with app store connect and google play store
console so we've gone through a lot so and i want
to congratulate you for sticking throughout all this with me and
um hopefully you've also learned a lot now while designing this course i also
knew that it has to be a living material it can't just be something that i drop
out on the internet so i'm very much planning to keep everything up to date
but there's lots and lots that i've already planned
more to be added to this course so i can't really go into details about
what they are i haven't finalized them but just as i did with this course i
need to plan them correctly write all my scripts to know what i'm going to talk
about and plan even the code that i need to write to tell you all about so
just know that there's a lot more to come
and you can just subscribe to my youtube
channel if you want to keep up to date talking about up to date um
things are moving all the time we've been working with firebase for instance
and firebase in itself is a moving product so it's an update like ever
it's just always updating so new versions come out new versions of
flutter might come up come out and new versions of dart might come out so even
figma for instance that we've been using a lot the interface might change
erratically so since i put so much effort into creating
this course i don't want it to die and i'm not going to let it die so it's
always going to be updating every now and then i will be putting
and not only updated content out like maybe i need to replace some old content
with some new but i'm also planning on adding more to it so
let's just say that this course is gonna hopefully always be up to date
as i mentioned in the introduction of this course i have zero dollars
in a budget for marketing this course and marketing is
probably the wrong word because i don't actually earn any money by having this
course the only thing i earn is joy of having
um like people like you going through this course and telling me on social
media perhaps about oh hey i did this course and i learned this and this and
this and i've released my first application so
since i have um no budget for that i would really appreciate it if you could
spread the word about it and tell like if someone asked okay i need a course
for learning flutter uh it would be lovely and i would really
appreciate it if you could just tell them about this course
and um i've mentioned this also in the introduction but i would really
appreciate it if you could follow me on social media twitter at van.np and also
on linkedin because i produce quite a lot of content
and as infographics for instance also adds videos related to flutter
javascript python django react native swift you name it so even typescript now
these days so uh i would really appreciate it if you
could follow me on social media and uh i've been told in some places
that um by some some of you that maybe some people can actually support
me and if you want to do that this is the way to do it just going to
buy me a coffee.com but remember it is completely
optional it's only if you can afford it so with all that said i don't want to
drag on this outro i just want to say again a huge congratulations to you for
going through this course with me and spending your life during these so many
hours together with me and i've had a blast recording all these videos and uh
i'm sure this is not a good buy but rather an official end basically to this
course and keep an eye out for more content and i'm sure we'll talk to each
other on social media