um so let's say switch
you put parenthesis open close and then open close curly brackets and in here
you would put your narration so you say animal type okay
and the way to handle these different branches then is with the case uh
keyword you'd say in the case of animal type
money print
uh money sound like this okay
case animal type a cat
print cat
and case animal type
og print dog
just like that okay now
this is i'm great i'm actually grateful that we're getting this uh error so you
can clearly see what it says is the case should not complete normally try adding
break or return now what this is saying that you see in
many programming languages just like dark when the program comes here to the
case statement it kind of like falls through to the next line and dart tries
to avoid that so it says okay if i handle bunny then i'm doing some stuff
but it kind of feels like i'm like falling down to the next line after this
because you didn't tell me what to do after the print statement so you either
tell me to like completely go out of this
function go out of the test function by putting the return keyword here we
haven't talked about return really yet but you could do that you could just say
okay return right after all of these so i'm just going to press command s
and you will see cat being printed to screen which is here okay
but if you didn't have this return statement statement here you would get
an error okay so
you either say return or you would use the break keyword now
there's a difference between these let's put a print statement here and i'm going
to say function is finished okay so i'm kind of expecting that
by executing our
our code here our test function here passing the value of cat at the moment
that we fall into the switch we check that this is cat and then print
the cat and then we return okay this is kind of
what it is doing it means that it kind of skips over this print statement and
you'll see soon if i say command s it will just say cat and then we'll return
from that so this is not really what i wanted i
wanted this switch statement to be executed print cat and then continue
after switch okay and that's where you use the break statement so
or the key word here so if you say break it breaks out of the switch statement
and then continues with the rest of the function as it as you would expect so if
i press command s here you say cat and then function is finished all right
so switch is the preferred way of working
with um enumerations especially if you're doing
branches so you could also like um
for instance if in this case he said uh pray make sure
this is is a cat
you could also in this case say if animal type
is not animal type chats
and you would return okay you could do this as well so this is kind of like
a conditional statement that you're putting in the beginning of your
function making making sure that any code executed after line 10
is completely sure that the animal type is
a cat okay so in that case you may just use a typical if statement so you don't
have to do switches okay but if you're trying to execute spec special pieces of
code depending on which value this enumeration contains at
the moment then i highly suggest that you use
switch statement instead of if statement all right so kind of depends on your on
your use case all right okay i'm just going to mark this item as
done in my notes now let's talk about classes all right
which is one of my favorite topics to talk about actually
um well classes in
uh dart and in many other languages let's actually bring this back to how it
was before make it a test function all right
and remove the animal type from here and remove them i can actually continue and
we can actually as well okay
so classes in dart are are grouping of various functionalities
into one packageable piece of data and and by that i mean for instance
let's say that you have a function called run
another function called breathe and then you have a person's first name
a person's last name of course you could go and define these
things like this you could say khan's first name
yeah something and khan's last name is something
like this okay
um just like that and then you could have a function and sorry you would say
run um and then you'd have another function
called breathe
you can do that but these are functions that are kind of like for us in this
particular case or at least in my head at the moment i'm imagining these
functions to be related to a person
and that person can run that person can breathe that person has a first name and
last name so the grouping of these related things
is done with a class
in dart at least so the way to do that is you would say for
instance class which is a keyword in dart
let's say the name of the class now for the
naming of classes and enumerations and any other
entity except for variables and constants
you should use um just normal casing you would i don't actually know if it's
called pascal casing or i think so um
but you would just use your upper case the first letter of every word okay so
let's just say person okay this is how you would say a person
class all right so i don't think actually we can put const
in there i'm just gonna grab these two functions and just place them
inside this person class all right and let's in this say print
running run function and with reading we're
going to say breathing all right
and in the test function you would want to
create something called an instance of this
class now instances are objects and objects are
created from classes so you need to understand how
instantiation works in software development and this
is for any programming language such as dart
rust swift python javascript where
they allow you to create classes
and now that you know what a class is in order to use a class you need to
usually create something called an instance of that class that means that
you tell the programming language that okay here
is the class i know about that but give me a copy of it
so every class
can be instantiated meaning that the dart compiler will create a copy of that
exact class with its data its functions its properties and give that copy to you
all right so that is called instantiation and it
works by using the equal sign and creating putting a parenthesis
at the end of the name of the class as i'll show you here so let's just say
final and we say person
which is the name of our variable in this case is equal to as i said equal
sign then we would write the name of the class and parenthesis just like that
okay so now you said a person variable in
this case is an instance of that person class
now you'll understand using dots and notation you could say person.run you
see that function is now available on your
instance of the person class and you would say person
dot breathe okay
so these are functions that are available at instance
level of the person class i know there's a lot of words that i'm just talking
about but i think you understand the point here so
this is how you instantiate the person class and this is how you invoke various
functions on that class so if i press command s you can see it says running
and if you said in this case person
and then without instantiating using their
parenthesis if you said breathe you will get an error here instance
member breathe can't be accessed using static axis
okay and that's i mean that is kind of like
instance member is an important term also to remember an instance member
means some functionality that is only available at the instance level meaning
that it's not available at the person class level but you have to make a copy
of person in order to be able to access that all right
so that's
the basic of classes you can do a lot with classes as we will
talk about soon so i'm just going to leave that person class right there
and then just going to mark that as talked about
in my notes as well and let's now talk a little bit a little
bit about objects well
objects are actually quite easy to explain an object is an instance of a
class so you wouldn't like
when someone says oh here's an object of type string it means literally that
there is a class called string i've created an instance of it and
and that is an object so the word instance the words instance and object
are usually used interchangeably uh but if you hear someone say instantiate a
class then you would say okay what's the class name oh it's person all right
and person is now i created an instance okay and in
this case you can see i'm just creating an instance of person without actually
doing anything with it so that's got kind of like a useless object all right
but if i put i say foo as a person then this
foo now is an object of type of person and actually you can write its name here
and you'll see that it tells you that this is a person okay
so that in short is what um
objects are
and i can see my notes that objects need are kind of like in the wrong place i'm
gonna bring it to the right place sorry about that um
okay now
let's talk a little bit about um constructors
and i can see constructors also at the wrong place in my notes so i'm going to
bring those also to the right place okay sorry about that
um now what a constructor is at its name as
its name indicates is a special
logic in a class that constructs or initializes or builds that class's
instance all right so you may say that okay let's go to our
function here as to our class here person
and let's say every person has a first name or name okay so let's just
define that we say final string name all right as you can see now dart is saying
okay you said that every person has a name but
and it's a final meaning that after the person has been instantiated or after
that person has been initialized or created an instance from you cannot
change that name because you said final all right
if you said like string name is foo that would be different because it means
every person instance that gets created has the default value
foo for its name that's a completely different way of saying
uh what the name of in this case as you can see we're saying
that there every person instance every person
copy that we create has a name now dart to say okay where is the name then you
didn't tell me how to create it and that's where you would want to use
something called constructor okay constructors are sometimes you uh called
as initializers depending on the background of the programmer they may
call it constructor initializer uh or maybe some other names that i don't know
about but if you if you hear that a constructor then you will now know what
i'm talking about soon actually
so now what you can do at least in visual
studio code when you get this error is to just hover hover over it and then
press command on mac or control on windows on linux and press dot
now you will see you will get some suggestions here
and it will the second suggestion at least for me here says create
constructor for final fields okay and i can just press that
and what happens here now you see it's that it creates something that looks
kind of like a function but it doesn't have a name
its name is implicitly set to the name of the class okay
so basically it says i'm a special function with the same name as the class
and i expect a value to be given to me which i will then in turn assign to the
name property of myself it's kind of like a strange way of doing
things but it is quiet clean as well okay
after you do that so this is how you create a constructor after you do that
then at the call site where you're calling this person class to create an
instance of it it will complain saying that oh i'm expecting an argument
but i didn't find any and that's where you have to pass the
name so let's say in this case is foo bar okay
and then on the next line you can just say print foo name
all right and press command s and then you can see foo bar being printed to the
screen so that is like the basic of a constructor
that's how you construct instances of your class all right
now you may be saying that all right i don't want
i mean you can do many fancy things with constructors you could say okay
this name for instance by default must have a special value you could do that
there's lots of things you can do with constructors which i'm not going to go
into the details of but right now just know that a
constructor is this special kind of function that has the same name as the
name of the class and then parenthesis and then you put
your values in here all right
okay that was
constructors um
now let's talk a little bit about um
methods all right and
what methods are i'm actually going to go here and say
we're going to talk about methods and those at the wrong place in my notes
as well sorry about that a method of a class we've talked about
already to be honest with you and a method of a class is
um a function on the class
which is usually referred to as an instance
method meaning that the function is available after you've instantiated that
class all right as we're doing in line number 14.
name is an instance variable so is a variable that is available at an
instance level is not an instance method an instance method should be a function
all right so let's go and create a function here that doesn't return any
value denoted by the void return type and we say print name all right
the functionality of this function is only
just to print class all right that's all it all it
does and in dart you're also now that we're
talking about this i'll just mention also in dart it's usually
better not to prefix your instance variables or instance functions
inside the class itself using this
keyword this keyword in dart
that this this or that this keyword
basically refers to the current instance of this class all right
so you could either tell print name to print this dot name or it's actually
better to remove this and refer to it as name that's the recommended way of doing
it okay so avoid the keyword this as much as you can
unless you have to and we'll come to those points hopefully
later in this in this course why you may have to do
that while you may have to use this all right now we have the print name
instance method all right so let's just use it instead of this
print function that we're doing here let's just say foo
dot prints name all right command s or control s
on linux and windows and command sun on the macintosh and then you get the
flutter foo bar printed here or you could just
say print
i'm going to i will now print the name of this person
in single quotes we don't need double quotes okay command s and you will see
that message being printed here followed by the actual name of that
instance so if someone says method or instance
method you will then know what we're talking about is a function created at
the class level that does some stuff all right so that's short and sweet
um okay
now that we've talked about that let's talk a little bit about
inheritance and subclassing i'm gonna bring a caption here so you know what
we're talking about now
inheritance and subclassing are so so important in dart
and in any other object-oriented programming language that i don't think
anybody should like jump over it or um like for instance i know
developers working in various programming languages that are object
oriented but they kind of steer clear of the object oriented aspects of that
language and maybe they don't need it and maybe they just feel like it's
unnecessary or they feel like oh it's just too complicated but in dart if you
want to become a good flutter developer or a good dart developer you need to
know about um classes and um
inheritance so so let's
talk about inheritance what inheritance in dart is is that
it allows you to define a class
and then to add more functionality to that class
into a new class so
let's for instance say we go into our test function here and
remove that okay that code and also remove the person
class now let's create a
class livingthing all right and then we say funk
sorry void breathe
and then we say print living thing is breathing okay
so we created a class living thing and we're saying that anything that lives
needs to breathe now this may be an assumption but anyways
anything that lives and is above the and it's above the ground and it's
basically alive is breathing okay so that's our function on the living
thing now you may say okay
any living thing may also have the ability to move okay then we have a
function called move i'm going to say print i am moving all right
so now you may say okay now i kind of want a class called uh cats all right
cat is also a living thing one way to do that to go about creating
a class uh the cat class is to say class cat
and then you say um i kind of need these functions and you'll go and copy it and
then you paste them here all right and then you say okay i'm good to go now
but one of the absolute paramount paramount
qualities of a developer is the
developers do not like to repeat themselves
and it is such an important concept in
programming that you need to avoid repeating yourself that you need to just
coin that down now get it straight so that you don't
make this mistake as we're doing in this code right now so
the first thing you want to do as a developer say how can i grab this code
and and it's obvious that the cat is also a
living thing so that's where you want to use the extends
um keyword that allows you to inherit the functionality inside the living
thing class into your cat class so in this case i'm saying cat class
extends or read it in english as inherits
living thing all right so
you can see that the cat class in itself is empty right now but if you go to the
test function and i say final
fluffers is a cat
and then i can say fluffers uh you can see that now that the cat
class has breathe and move uh functionalities or functions actually
so although cat itself didn't define these functions but they're available
for the instance in this case called fluffers of type cat to use so you could
just say move and then you can say fluffers
okay so if i run this code if i delete
everything in the debug console and run this code you can see that the cat
instance called fluffer is the same move or i am moving and it will also say
living thing is breathing okay now
you could also i mean we could also talk about now that we're talking about
inheritance and subclassing um
actually maybe i shouldn't call a subclassing but i also think it's
important for you to understand what subclassing is subclassing is literally
the same thing as inheritance subclassing is saying that you have a
class and you're creating a sub component like a sub
thing of it which may actually have
it's a little bit of a strange naming sub because sub means kind of like a
subset of things available in that class but it actually is like a superset
because it will
grab everything like the cat at the moment has every functionality in living
thing right but it may not necessarily do that
it's kind of complicated to explain but if you hear subclassing or inheritance
know that that is what we mean
you use the extends keyword usually okay
all right now we've talked about inheritance and subclassing
so i'm gonna
move a little bit uh my notes around sorry about that that i'm looking away
from the screen and uh now we're gonna talk about abstract
classes all right there's good documentation about
abstract classes and
what we're going to do here is to just change this class living
thing at the moment to abstract
and you see that everything works as expected
well an abstract class
is very similar to a normal class and there's good
documentation about what an abstract class actually is from a dart
perspective and you can see it says use the abs abstract modifier to define an
abstract class class that cannot be instantiated all right
so an abstract class is just like a normal class that can't have instances
so in this in this case once we made living
thing an abstract class if you then go and hear say
thing is a living thing
right and
it says oh abstract classes can't be instantiated
so an abstract class is a class that groups logic into itself
with the sole purpose of other classes using its functionality okay
so if you mark something as an abstract class in dart you what you need to just
know in your head is that this is a class that has some utilities that has
some code that is supposed to be used in other normal classes all right
and no one is supposed to just go and create an instance of living thing in
this case instead
at the call side you need to instantiate classes of that type so
now we can say cat as we did before and we can say thing breathe move or
fluffers
so that's what an abstract class is
it is just a class that cannot be instantiated
it's usually like a utility class that other classes are supposed to inherit
from all right
okay um i can see now in my notes and i'm gonna
take that we've talked quickly about abstract classes
and i'm going to bring the next topic up which we're going to
talk about which are factory constructors
so i absolutely personally love factory
constructors to be honest with you
let's remove our abstract class i'll explain to you what a factory
is let's see now we have a glass cat all right
um and then in here let's give the cat a name
of type string command dot or control dot
for linux windows on the name in visual studio code at least to create a
constructor you can do that and say create constructor or you could manually
create a constructor so you say cat this name okay that's a constructor
and also know that um you could make this a const because it is actually
using a final field but we're going to talk about that later
now we have a cat class here that has a constructor called just cat meaning
that in here you can say final
fluffball is cat
and then you say fluffball all right so now you're creating an
instance of the cat class and the name of the variable is called fluffball
and the name of the cat is fluffball right
so then you can say print
off ball
dots name all right so
that is just normal constructor it has
nothing to do with a factory constructor but what a factory constructor actually
is is a way for you to construct instances
of your classes and using convenience functions
so what that means is that if you in your code see that
you are creating instances of this class like 20 times 30 times different places
in your application using this exact same name fluffball
then you need to then create a factory
constructor that is a clear sign that your usual use case for create an
instance of class is through
the same name of fluffball so
that's where factory constructors are useful for and as their name indicates
is a way to create
a product like a factory does uh super fast for you okay so it's the speed at
which you can create an instance of a class that the factory constructor
shines at all right so let's now look at a factory
constructor that gives us an instance of cap whose name is always fluffball all
right the way to do that is you would say
factory and you would say cat dot fluffball
so you say any class called cat which is this class has a function called
fluffball which is this factory constructor and then you would put your
parentheses in here and then what you need to do is to kind
of set up your class instance in this case
like if you say curly brackets and say this name
is fluff like that that's how you're basically
creating an instance of your class but the usual way of doing that is you say
this name
dude let's see uh factory cat fluff ball
and then you would say name is fluff
see that i've kind of like forgotten the um
uh syntax for factory uh so let's go i'm
gonna bring up safari here and let's go and say guard factory constructor
i'll bring bring up here factory constructor so let's say factory
and let's go and see an example and you can see here it says factory logger like
that okay and there's a factory logger blah blah like that so
are basically so what what it's basically saying in here is saying that
this in this function you need to return something okay so let's close that
safari window and what we're going to do in here we're going to say return cat
and as the name we're gonna say fluffball all right so that's how you
would create like a factory constructor so what you're doing here is saying that
i have a constructor called fluffball whose return value is a cat
but inside i have some special logic that kind of packages it up just like
you do in a factory so let's go in here instead of doing cat
fluff ball like that then you can just say cat dot fluffball okay so it kind of
like became a um
it became like a convenient function in that you can just say cat fluff ball and
then you say print fluffball
dot name and you can see by default it is
or whatever you put here fluffball 2 print and it gets printed to
the screen ok so that's how you would create a factory
constructor and a factory constructor is really really important when you're
talking about class clusters we haven't talked about class clusters
and to be honest with you i don't think that we're gonna talk about that in this
course i don't think anywhere in this course
i've actually talked about class clusters
but know that in the context of dart and abstract
classes a factory constructor does not necessarily
have to return an instance of the same class all right so it can actually
return an instance of another class
but i highly suggest that you actually go and read about factory constructors
as i just did just google factory constructor
dart and you will see some examples of it
um they are really useful if you're working
with a lot of data and you're doing like data parsing
json parsing etc but
i don't think it's so useful right now for you to know
but know that it is there available for you to use but
i leave it up to you to go and read more about it yourself
okay and we've now talked about factory
constructors and um now let's talk a little bit about
custom operators so i'm going to bring custom operators here okay
now a custom operator in dart is
an operator such as an equal sign or equal equal sign for for instance
um checking equality um of an instance of an object with another instance of
the same object um a custom operator allows you in dart
to override the ability of your class to be compared to or added to or
subtracted from multiplied with something
with your own logic now let's see what i mean by that let's say that
you have final uh cat one and that is equal to cat with the name of foo
then you say okay i have cat two now with the exact same name
and then you'd say if cat one is exactly the same as cat 2 prints they are equal
otherwise say print they are not equal ok
so these two instances have the exact same
name foo
and if you run this code now you will see
that dart is said it says that they're not equal although internally you may
think hmm for me in my project anytime
two cats have the same name i want them to be considered equal and
this is like where things get interesting because then you
can override this particular function or operator at the language
level only for your class so the way to do that is you would go and start by
writing override with an ad sign
and you say bool operator equal equal covariance i'm
going to explain all this don't worry about it cat and you say cat and then
here you say um other
name is me okay and then we get a problem with the hash
i'll add that as well so don't worry about all of this um i
will explain it in details um
all right so okay so let's start by looking at what i just
did here with the override
notation here overwrite is very important term for you
to understand in object-oriented programming and that is
wherever you have um
a class and you are
inheriting from that class in in our case for instance class cat you can see
that it doesn't have any extents but by default in dart every class
inherits implicitly from the object class so you could just say extends
object and that is the exact same thing as
omitting writing that those two words so
just know that cat comes from object an object internally already defines an
operator called equal equal that returns a boolean
a boolean is a value that can either include true
that can either be true or false and it's great just for saying that is
this this or is this that is this this or not kind of like that
so a boolean is a data type all right so that operator an operator is a keyword
as well in dart basically saying telling dart that we are going to change
change as in override the functionality of this equally equal
operator that is defined at the object level with our own
implementation all right let's actually bring the extents here
and go into this object definition just select it right click on it and say go
to definition all right and search for operator equal equal
you'll see that it is defined right there for you okay
and there's lots of documentation about what it actually does
so that's this syntax we're overriding we're changing the definition of that
function all right so
then since this is a simple function an operator in itself is a function it
actually you can see it starts it has like a
parenthesis here in the parenthesis you get the value
that that operator is comparing your class with okay so
it's that that value that your class is being
compared to also needs to be a cat because you cannot in dart is not
recommended that you compare tune classes of different types with each
other so here we say covariance covariance
is a keyword that you merely use in dart but i think it's important for you to
understand what it does is that it tells dart that although
at the object level we said that the parameter that comes in
is of type object but in our case we are sure that the value that comes in this
function is actually a cat all right so covariant tells dart that
forget what the super class which is object defines as the parameter type for
this parameter because if you remove covarian you see it says cat
an object as a parameter but if it's a covariant you're kind of
like overriding even that assumption all right so we say okay an
equal so we're mean compared our instance of cat is being compared with
another cath instance and what we're doing is that we need to
return a boolean saying whether they're equal or not and you can see i'm just
comparing i'm just comparing the name which is our
name with the other instances name all right
now when you do that as you saw then we get a problem here which is kind of like
a warning that tells you that okay now that you've you've overwritten this
um operator you also need to override the
hash code all right now
to honestly i don't think like hashcode is such an important thing to talk about
right now but just know that hashcode is a special number
that you assign to your or a special identifier that you
assign to your instance of classes that is
then used inside collections for instance if you put your instance of of
cat inside a
dictionary then or sorry or inside a map as it is
called in dart which we talked about i believe in chapter
four yes in chapter four so if you didn't
watch chapter four i strongly suggest that you do that
so if you put instances of your
of your cat class inside a set
or inside a map then the way dart
knows that the the keys inside its map or the values inside the set are
actually unique it's using this hash value all right
so if you see if i go here and say command
dot to get a suggestion how to fix this it says create method hash code
that is what is required to fix this word
so you can see that it's an override which means that this hash code
getter was defined on the object class if we go to object and look for that you
can see that it is actually defined there
and we're overwriting its value and here it says i'm going to go to
super and get that value super is our object so as super class
that sits up above us all right but if you want to overwrite that in
case you in this case you can just say okay don't get the supers hash code just
get the name hashtag and to be honest with you this is just a
very technical stuff which i don't think belongs right in this chapter six but
just know that here we're creating an identifier for our cat class
which allows dart to understand that if this
cat classes instances are placed inside collections such as a map or a set
then it will know if they're unique or not okay
all right so now that we've done all of this we
can rerun the code and you will now see that it says they
are equal that's that's all we wanted that's
really all we want but there was a lot of code actually i
don't know it's like four lines of code um
this is not even considered a line of code it's kind of like a
is a hint to the analyzer but uh so
you could just say it's pretty much just two lines of code but it is quite a lot
of new things to be honest with you for you
to grasp
so i leave this here so you can have a look at it
um and i think
for this chapter to be honest with you we've talked a lot now in this chapter
about enumeration switch statements classes objects uh constructors
factory constructors
abstract classes inheritance a lot so it was quite a heavy chapter this chapter
six but i suggest that you
go and read the also the official documentation for dart because as i said
we don't have the possibility to talk about everything
um otherwise this course will just be
enormously big and that's not what i want to do so
please go and read the documentation about the things that we talked about
especially especially object oriented programming in dart so
and with that said in the next chapter we're going to talk
about some advanced features in dart such as
future async operations streams and generators
so
please have a look about at the documentation and i will see you in the
next chapter hello everyone and welcome to chapter 7
of this flutter course in this chapter we're going to talk about advanced dart
concepts things such as extensions futures
streams um
async await generators and um generics as well
so uh i'm kind of assuming that you've
already set up the project that we've talked about in the previous chapter so
i'm not going to go through that again and then i'm assuming that we have like
some sort of an iphone simulator so or an android emulator or any device
that you may be able to test your project on so
i'm going to bring up my project here so i'm going to place it right there
this is how we left the project in the previous chapter
and then i'm going to do command shift p on mac or control shift p in linux and
windows in order to select the device and i'm just going to say iphone 13 pro
which is a simulator that i have here um
right there and then i'm just going to go and say run
run without debugging okay so this is going to take its time and i just
thought to then use this time to explain a little
bit about extensions um
as you can see here extensions are the ability for
the programmer and dart in order to er are there the ability for the programmer
to extend
or add functionality to an existing class in chapter six we talked about
classes and objects so i kind of um would
wish for everyone who is in this chapter to act actually have followed that
chapter as well uh i'm actually going to go here and go
to do not disturb yeah i am actually there so let's have a look at a simple
extension in dart and how we can use that i can see that the programming
program is running i'm going to delete the old code that we had and i'm going
to bring my face to that bottom right and i'm just going to be a little bit
aware of these um captions that i'm displaying on the
screen and that they're blocking the screen so i'll just make sure that you
can see the contents as as we go on so
um let's also remove all of that and then let's just say that we have a
simple cat class here who has a name and we can go in here and say final
meow is yeah an instance of cat and i can say
print and me
actually we have to provide a name i can see here and let's just say fluffers
and save meow dot's name okay so we print that name
and i'm gonna say command s just like that and um perhaps gonna
bring up visual studio code so you can actually see the output so command s and
you can see that um where are we getting this there are
equals oh that's an old command so command is and you can see fluffers is
printed to the screen so that's because we have the name here okay so i'm also
going to get rid of this caption right now so you can see the entirety of the
code so like that bring it down here i'm also going to get rid of my
simulator and bring it to another screen okay so now let's say that you want to
add a functionality to this or a function to this class
that allows a cat to run or allow the cat to jump so one way to do that is to
actually go to the cat class class itself and create a
function in there but what you can also do is to go and say extension
for instance run on cat that's the syntax for creating an extension what
you're saying is that you're extending the
class call cats with
a new functionality that is called run now this is not the name of the function
itself it's just the name of your extension
and you don't have to really know about the name right now so much it's just
when you can go and become more advanced in dart and you for instance create
libraries for yourself that you
create extensions on different classes for instance in your library and then
people or programmers who use your library then they can in
basically include specific extensions that you've included
in your library in their code or they can exclude them
and so just know that it's just a name on the
extension so it doesn't mean so much right now okay so then you can just
create a function that has no return value called run and then you can say
print and cat name is running
and you know this syntax from the previous chapters that this is how you
format a string and then in here you're basically doing um spring interpolation
interpolation i think it's called and you're including that name inside
your own string so the result is going to be cat
space the name of this cat instance
space is running okay so
using that then you can every cat instance in your
project is gonna get that function called run so you can just
say me out run and command this and you can see that it
says cap fluffers is running so just know that extensions are
they're a great tool for you to use if you believe that there is a
functionality that you're adding to an existing class which it doesn't really
belong in that class itself
but it may for instance belong in the
current source file that you're working with so
extensions are very very useful and but i also believe that they need to
kind of be used with care kind of like sparsely so when you really need an
extension you could just go and create an extension and they have limitations
and as you get more used to programming in dart you will understand
their limitations a little bit better so just know that they're there
and can be used another example of an
extension is for instance if you had a class
person let me say first name
property okay so this is an instance property and then
you would say uh last name and then you say command dot individual
studio code on mac or control dot in linux and windows and you create a
constructor for your personal class okay so that's how you create an instance of
your person class then you can go in here and you say
um final fou is person whose first name is
who and whose last name is bar okay and in here let's say you want to be
able to calculate a person's full name all right so what you could do is to you
could say extension for me
one person and then here you could just say i have
a i want to calculate the full name so that the result type is going to be a
string and then you want to create a getter now
we haven't talked about getter so much but just know that it's kind of like a
property it's a property that can only be read forever but it cannot be written
to so you just say get and then you say phoney
as the name of the property and you will say that is equal to
dollar first name space dollar last name okay
so what you're saying here is that i have a getter whose return type is
string and whose name is full name and it returns the first name and last
memory with the space in between and then in here you could just say print
foo for me all right
and command s then i will bring the i'll remove the caption so you can see
that foo bar is printed to the screen okay
so that's for extensions and i'm gonna note that here in my i'm gonna mark it
in my notes that we've talked about extensions all right
now the next thing to talk about the next topic is futures
and as you can see here future is a data to be returned in the future as its name
suggests so um
and that is part of something called asynchronous programming if you haven't
uh been doing uh programming before you may not be so
familiar with the term synchronous or asynchronous um
a synchronous task is a task that happens when you ask for it and it
returns with the data that you ask for immediately
for instance if you say um what is 2 plus 2 and then we'll say
okay it's four that's the synchronous task but if you for instance say to your
um spouse or your friend go to the grocery store today please and
get some milk that is not gonna happen in this instant
it's i mean even if you even if you're the grocery stores right next to your
house or your apartment then your friend has to go
get get ready put put on shoes go to the store get the mail can come back so
um that that is an asynchronous task so an asynchronous task is basically a task
that whose results are not returned
immediately okay so
up until this point we've looked at functions that i'm actually going to
remove all of this code from here so that we don't have all of that
now we only have the void test function in here okay
so
all the functions that we've written so far have been synchronous functions in
that for instance you would say string multiplied by
two and then it gets an integer of a and it just says a multiplied by two all
right and actually sorry hint so it returns an
integer the function call the function name is called multiplied by two it
takes an integer as a parameter and just multiplies that integer by two and
returns it it's a synchronous operation okay however in dirt if you wanna work
with asynchronous operations that you have to
use a class called future so let's have a look at that um let's say
that you have a function multiplied by two it which it may take
some time in order to multiply a value okay this is hypothetical because yeah
the multiplication is going to be done immediately but we're just going to
assume that yeah this is a complicated multiplication and it will take some
time all right so let's say future and then you would say what is the actual
future what does it contain what data type can we say integer and then we say
heavy future
okay and it takes a value of int a heavy
future that multiplies by two something like that
okay so it says i return a future okay now
in here then your your um
responsibility is to create and package up an integer and return it inside a
future so if you for instance in here say okay
return 10 okay you see that it says l10 isn't
compatible with the future of integer because 10 is a synchronous value it's
right there it's present so what are you doing here then you could say
okay what i do return is a future and then you could say oh i'm going to
delay this future by a duration of three seconds okay
and then you'll see there's a second parameter to this delayed function
um you can see it let's see
uh if we have a look at delayed function in here you see there is a second
parameter called future or a computation so
in here what you're what you need to do is just to say okay
my second parameter is a function i'm going to ignore its return value well
i'm just going to return the value of a okay
so let's actually see if we say future delay duration seconds and then
we say the parameter is let's say e and then i'm just going to say return a
what is this value going to be then you know what we could actually look at
the documentation for future delayed so i can also refresh my mind
so i'm going to go and open a new safari window and i'm going to say future
delayed this is the type of stuff that usually
happens anyways if you're programming with dart i'm also going to increase the
size so that you can see it a little bit better
and let's have a look at a future delay here
and here we can see how it's constructed uh
how to use future okay so you can see here that there is a
function that it doesn't basically take anything any uh value so
i think the problem was that i may have just created like a function that um was
expecting a parameter so this is how you would do that and i mean
it is a little bit strange argument like i'm actually going to clean it up a
little bit as well and then make this a constant as you can
see it's suggested here and then return so i've written a lot of code i haven't
explained really what i've done here but i will do that now so let's see
uh we're saying that we're returning an integer in the future so
it's not going to be returned immediately it's going to take some time
for it to do its calculation okay so and then here let's say a multiplied by 2 as
we as we promised in the function signature okay so that's future int
this is the name of the function so nothing magical about that and then it
takes a parameter that says integer a in the function body itself we're saying
okay we're returning a future but we're delaying its return by the duration of
three seconds so duration as you can see is a class here if you go in it
actually is a constitution okay and then there is a class on top probably
somewhere uh let's see
constitution in blah blah blah constitution duration operator i believe
this is i mean the duration dart it's probably just a class duration
somewhere if you look at here class duration so
so we're saying that we're creating a duration as a first parameter to the
delayed function of the future so we're saying that we're delaying this future's
return value by three seconds and then it says okay i'm going to wait three
seconds but then i'm after i waited three seconds i'm going to call this
function and this is kind of like a shorthand for
creating a an inline function you could also do it like this you say okay my
function that i'm providing to this function so it's like you're passing a
function to the future delay function and then in here you could just say okay
i return a multiplied by two and then a semicolon so this is probably a little
bit easier to read so um
now that we have that um we could actually use this function in
our test um in our test function so
when you then um i mean now that actually we we've now
talked a little bit a bit about future and in order to use a
future then you need to know something about
async and awaiting dart now
async and await are very related to each other but quite
different in their meaning and um
i just want to now explain actually first async
async is a key word in dart that marks a function as asynchronous in that
remember synchronous is something that returns immediately and asynchronous is
something that does not return immediately takes some time however to
mark a function async in here it means that this function internally
can execute commands that do not return immediately okay
so ac marking a function as async it
it it means that this function internally calls other functions that do
asynchronous work so let's now say final um result is
heavy future and we say 10 okay
now that we've done that let me just print the result and you'd be surprised
to actually see the result when we do that and you'll see that it
is not what you think it's not going to be 20 okay
so i'm gonna get rid of this caption so that you can see the the result and i'm
gonna clear the results in the console and command s
and you'll see that what got printed to the screen is actually the future is not
is not what you think it's not the value 20 which should be a
multiplied by 2 which should be 20. so what happened here is that when you call
a function that returns a future you're actually getting the future back you're
not getting its data back so how do you get that data back well by
prefixing the function with the keyword await
so as its name indicates this keyword is just going to wait for
the result of this function to be calculated and then it's gonna go to the
next line okay so
these two are very related to each other and you'll see that if i remove async
then i will get an error saying that well you said this function
called test is a synchronous function it just returns void
basically means it doesn't return anything and it asynchronously does its
work and doesn't have to wait for anything so
but then inside the function you're saying wait which means yeah i have to
wait some time for something and that's not okay so
what you need to do then is you mark your functions with async if internally
in that function you're using a weight all right
and the weight itself then is used for
waiting for the result of the future okay so if you remove this async and
then you remove this await everything will just work but it's just
synchronously getting the future of the heavy future that multiplies by two and
printing it so it's not doing any asynchronous work in here you can see
it's just getting that instance so now that we're calling that let's command s
and you'll see it's waiting three seconds and then printed the
result 20 to the screen okay so
that for us was async and in weight and we're going to use async and in a way
and await quite a lot in this course so it would be really good if you could
have with this information that i gave you if you could just have a little bit
of a read about future like documentation
on the web so if you just search future
dart um and maybe async await and read a little bit about them because
they're so important in doing asynchronous work in dart that we just
can't jump over them okay
all right um so now we've talked about future
uh and we've talked about async and awaits
so i'm just gonna mark them as
done in my notes um the next topic to talk about
it would be streams
so as you saw here a future in dart is a class that controls the computation of
an asynchronous value in order to be returned in some point in the future
however quite often in
in your client's work or even server work you need to do work that is
asynchronous however it is continuous work for instance if you if like i have
the time uh displayed on top of my screen on the right hand corner
that is a stream of strings
it is a it is a stream because it doesn't have an end ready it it's a
continuous pipe of information every minute that
little ticker up on top right it's gonna increase and
it's gonna go to zero six fifty zero six fifty 651 so
it is continuously calculating the current time and like sending it down at
this pipe now in asynchronous programming and in
reactive programming which you may also get into if you're
following with this course or if you're following some other course you may
actually be interested in learning about learning more about streams
and reactive streams a stream is just a pipe of data
um that either
it either completes or it never completes
actually it completes successfully or it never completes or it errors out and
dies okay so um a stream of time up there you can see
it's not 0 6 50 in the morning and it is a stream of data that never completes
because time is just just continuously going forward okay
so when we talk about streams we just mean a pipe of data a future
that sends data down this pipe that
never ends as you saw in the case of a future a
future ends it calculates its data and it returns and it says i'm done
but a stream in dart is a future that just continues working
okay so it calculates some data in the future and it also sends it down the
stream and it says oh well i'm not done here's another data here's another data
okay so
let's have a look at this uh stream and see how we can work with streams okay
so let's go and create a stream of um let's say a string
and then we say get name okay now in here
you your job is to create a string so if you say return hello
see that hello is not compatible with the return type that you promised it's
going to be a string um so you it this is very similar to how
we worked with the future of integer you couldn't return an
integer in that future but you have to create a future of integer and inside
the function return the actual integer which was the
computation if i go back you will see that
code here right the future delayed and inside this
function you're actually doing the computation all right
so how do we create a stream and you could
just say stream and then you could say
okay periodic for instance or a value okay if you say we return a stream of
value and then you could say foo
is accepted what this means is that you have a pipe
of data but the only value that it contains is a
foo is the value of food that's it all right
so let's now go into this test function and try to consume this uh stream if you
just said final value is gets me
and you just print this value and then i'm going to clear the logs
here and say command s you'll see that just like future it just says instance
of controller stream okay so it is not the actual value inside the string so
the question is how do you wait for values
inside a stream you could just say okay await
it says okay you've actually we could read this a weight
applied to stream string which is not a future so
dart is understanding that okay you're awaiting on a stream but
this is this is not just like a future that you're gonna wait for there's
nothing to await like it's not a single value is a stream so
the syntax to do that is await
four okay so this is a syntax
for awaiting for values inside a stream then you could say wait for final value
in its name okay
and then you could just print the value so this is a little bit of a strange
syntax but if you read it in like in english it makes perfect sense you're
waiting for values in get's name if you just ignore the final in here
okay but read it in english from left to
right await for values in get name that's it
and then at the end i'm going to say print stream
finished working
here the console command s and you'll see it immediately said foo
and then stream finished working i'm gonna clear it command s
foo stream finish working okay so this is an interesting concept but
it's still not a stream really i mean we're packaging the full string inside
the stream but it's only one value we could have done
that with a future so let's take advantage of streams actual
functionality of sending down data in its pipe
continuously so what we could do in here say stream
periodic it means periodically produce values and in here you can see the first
parameter is a duration so let's say constant duration
of seconds every second okay and then there is a second parameter in here
that you'll have to provide if i move my mouse over periodic you'll see that the
second parameter is this string function int okay so it means that give me a
function that accepts an integer and then it returns a string all right
and it understands that it needs to return a string because you're saying
that your stream is a string if you change this to an int and then went here
um to the documentation and the documentation will actually or the
method signature will change to say that uh your you should support you're
supposed to take an integer in this function that you provide to me and then
you need to return an integer okay so that string i just wanted to show you
that that string that was shown in the function signature there it's because we
promised to return a string in our function okay so
let's go in here basically the function signature said
that you need to accept an integer so i'm just going to say value
and then let's go in here i'm just going to say return foo
so we basically conform to that function signature we
said we take some value and you see the value is an integer
and then we're returning a string okay so now we can consume that so if i clear
this log and i say command s you see that every second the value of foo is
going to get printed to the screen and that's
actually i need to remove this caption i can see you can't see it
you see that 10 times 11 times 12 13
14. so all right
um i'm sorry about that the caption was blocking the screen i wasn't aware of
that um or actually i was aware of that but i forgot that that was the case in
in this as i was talking so you can see that every second the
stream is sending a value all right now that's that's basically the gist of
using streams you will
i'm wondering actually if we're gonna use the streams in this course i believe
at some point we are i need to probably look at the um
look at my notes yes i can see that we're actually using
streams in this course so don't worry about
if you don't fully understand streams at the moment because we're gonna talk
about streams and um
because we're gonna actually talk about streams and stream controllers later in
this in this
course so just know for now that a stream is like
a future but it continuously or periodically can return
values and then you can wait for those values using the await for
syntax and dart okay
okay um
now the next topic to
talk about in this chapter is generators so
generators are very very interesting in dart
some other languages also support generators and
but not not all modern languages do that so
a generator in dart is a function that returns
i don't want to say iterable but it returns a list of things
but it internally calculates that data in a
very simple way that's the best explanation i can come
up with to be honest with you let's have a look here
i think the best way to do that is actually write a function that does uh
creates a generator okay um i'm gonna clear this um
and then we have a test function here let's mark lacing okay
um let's now go create a generator and
let's say we want to
create a function that returns the values one two three
um so
a way to do that is would be to say i want a list of integers okay and my
function or get one two three like this
and you could say return one two three like that okay so that's completely
valid another way of doing that is to use
something called iterable and iterables i mean you need to
understand what iterables actually are and they're kind of like lazy
collections and when you get used to doing more software engineering you will
understand more what why we use lazy collections
but for now just know that an iterable is a prepared and packaged up list of
things but it is not
it is not completely calculated when it first begins
it's kind of like it's kind of like how a restaurant works
in a typical night a restaurant might have for instance 50 customers
and when that shift begins during the night
not all food is ready i mean it can't possibly be like when cut the first
customer comes in we can say that the food for the 50th customer is already
ready in the kitchen that's how a restaurant works it it
listens to orders of its customers and then it generates the food based on the
orders that's how an iterable works okay however a list in dart is an already
packaged list it means that it's as if like you go to a supermarket and then
you buy ready ready to go
food that's already packaged 30 packs of that that is a list that is 30 ready
readily packaged food items and then you take away that's how list works but an
iterable is more like it's
it's a list of like things that gets calculated on the go
on the fly all right so
um just know that for now so we just said
either well and as you can see dart understood that okay a list is also an
eye trouble so i don't have to worry about that so it didn't give you an
error so let's go and actually instead of
doing one two three let's go and mark our
um function as uh a generator and you do that with
either sync or async okay so and this would be a stream like
now the difference between sync with a an asterisk an async with an
asterisk is a sync function is an
it is a generator function that returns a list of things but it calculates that
list of things asynchronously and as you can guess the
async equivalent of the sync asterisk it does the exact same thing but it returns
a stream and which means it's asynchronously
calculating its result okay so when you mark a function as sync you
don't then go and return like this because you can see that you
can see that it says you're creating a generator function so you have to kind
of calculate your results now you can't just return a bunch of things to me okay
so to do that you would use a keyword in
dart called yield now yield is
a very interesting keyword that you would use only in generator functions as
far as i know and in here you're telling dart that
okay the first value that i'm outputting in my iterable is the value of one so
if in here we went and said um
i know or say we say four value in
gets one two three and then you could just say print value
you can see it only prints the value of 1. i'm actually going to get rid of this
caption you can see the output it only prints the value of 1 just
because we yielded the value of 1. okay so you could just send then say yield
one yield two and yield three then you'd see the values one two three
so in this function internally then you
could do a lot of other important things maybe some synchronous uh some other
synchronous calculations and every time you have a value to output
then you would basically um
you would do a yield and you could also print the entire return value
yes you don't have to do a four loop so you could just say print it and then
it would say one two three okay but if you do a for loop then you're
actually taking advantage of that lazy um
capabilities of an eye turbo so you could break out the loop at loop at any
time you could just say print value
if value is two
then you could break okay so let's clear the logs and command s
you'll see only the value of one and two gets printed and then as soon as you're
at the value of two then you're breaking and that means that this yield
was basically never calculated so that's that's like the beauty of
generator functions
so you could also create asynchronous generator functions as i mentioned and
that means that you're kind of like creating a stream of iterables
to be honest with you asynchronous generators i've i've maybe used them
once or twice uh in in the many years i've used dart
so i don't think you're going to use them a
lot but just know that they're there and you could use them by prefixing your eye
treble with a stream saying that basically you're returning a
stream of eye troubles and then suffixing your function with async just
like that all right so and then here it says okay you said
that you're returning a stream of ideal integers but you're turning only one
value in here then you would just say okay one two
okay um but then you would say yeah then you
have the ability to do whatever you want here like return an actual eye variable
okay so i'm not going to talk about asynchronous generators to be honest
with you in this course because they're kind of like outside the scope
so just know that they exist and you can use them
okay i'm going to mark in my notes that we've talked about generators so
the next topic to talk about are generics
and i'm going to bring up a caption here so generics in
programming languages that do support it are
there so that you avoid writing the same code over and over again okay
so let's say that you i mean this is a very
typical example i know it's a little bit cliche
but i think it's cliche for a reason and
that's because it's such a good example um
let's say you have a class
that stores a pair of data let's just say class
pair okay and then in here you could say okay what
pair of data do i want to store okay i want to store
value one as a string and i want to also store value two as a string and then you
create the constructor for it okay all right that's that's great it's a
pair of strings but how do you then pair an integer like two integers then
you would say okay i have to have another pair class and
this one is an integer but then you have this problem because
pair is already defined as a class up there on line seven
so you cannot reuse that you cannot have the same name then you would say okay
pair of integers
and then here you would say pair of strings
and you make sure that the constructor name is also
correct now
i mean you may have also i mean in this point at this point we don't have logic
at all in these two classes you may have actually quite a lot of logic in your
classes but as i mentioned i think during one of
these chapters i think it was chapter one or two program one of the main
characteristics of software engineers is that we all dislike
um writing the same piece of code over and over again so
we try to as much as possible avoid
um repeating ourselves so
that's where generics can come in so what you could do is instead of doing
this pair of pair of let me bring this here let's go and
create a class that is generic and you would say pair
and then a format for creating a generic class is to write after the name of the
class oh just to a less than and greater than sign okay and then open your square
brackets now
in here then you define your generic
names like the data types with usually with single characters let's say that
what you want is a pair of any data type let's call the first data type a
and the second data type b because there's two values so let's call this
one a and this one b okay you would just write them as we just say we say a and b
okay so then in here you would say final
a value one so you're telling the compiler
that okay whatever pair i'm creating the first data type that i accept is a
and that should be placed here and then we say okay then the b is the
second one and then we create a constructor for
this okay so how you would use this then is you
would say final and is pair then you would say foo and bar okay
and then this is just like a simple it's very similar than to pair of
strings that we wrote up there you see it worked as well but now in this case
dart is smart enough to understand that names is a pair of string and string
meaning that the two values that you pass to this pair generic class were
actually then placed for you magically inside the a and b templates
that you provided up here okay so if in if in this case then you said
okay i have foo and then i have the value of 20
then dart smart enough to understand that oh now it's a pair of string and
integer so
that's how you would use uh generics basically so i mean there are so much to
talk about about generics and how you can
uh basically utilize them in order to create
very simple classes so that they're so that they're reusing as much
capability or as much code as possible without duplicating that code so
and talking about generics to be honest with you it could be it's its own entire
course we could go on and on four five six hours i could talk about generics so
just know that generics are created like this you say class pair and then you
would say your generic data types which then in
case then in turn get placed inside the
definitions inside the class itself so okay
um
all right now that we've talked about generics um i believe that we could kind
of like wrap up this um chapter where we talked a little bit
more about advanced topics in dart extensions futures
async awaits streams the weight for stream generators and
generics okay now i'm actually really happy that we
went through chapter number seven which is this chapter because up until this
point we've kind of been like preparing ourselves for our launch
it's it's now time that we put everything
that we've learned into practice and actually start building our project
so i'm actually getting goosebumps because it's such an important part of
this course that we've actually gone through the basics we've talked about
dart we've talked about like some of the basics of setting up the simulator etc
etc that it's with great pleasure that i can say okay we've gone through that now
and all you need to do right now is just to practice and what better way to
practice than to put what you've learned um into
application by writing
the flutter project that we've been aiming
to do from the beginning so without further ado let's then
prepare for the next chapter which is chapter eight and in chapter eight we're
gonna talk about uh project setup and then we're actually
gonna add some dependencies to our project which we're gonna use
later okay so let's aim for that and i'll see you in
the next chapter hello and welcome to chapter number
eight of the slatter course in this chapter we're going to talk
about our basic project setup in the previous chapters
up until this point to be honest with you we've been just working with dart
and kind of like um laying the foundation for learning
the programming language that actually um
uh it fuels flutter so it's a programming language that you're gonna
need to be quite comfortable with in order to be able to write your flutter
applications so you're gonna learn more and more about dart as we go on in this
course but it is very very good if you can
look at the intro chapter and then just kind of like follow along on the
chapters up until this point so that you get the general idea of what dart is all
about and then how you can use it at a very shallow level i mean i know
there's lots of material that i put out on that but
we really didn't like go so deep in every topic so i just wanted to give you
like a flavor and taste of the different available options in dart
so if you haven't watched those chapters
please just go ahead and skim skim over them even if you're comfortable already
with dart so
in this chapter we're going to talk about the project setup and this is the
like one of the absolute most important parts of setting up
um an application for flutter so if you're
if you're thinking of maybe skipping um over this chapter that's also okay if
you know what you're doing but if this is the first time that you're setting up
a flutter project that then i think it's really good if you can
follow along with this chapter so i'm going to go now into um
let's do some setup here so what am i going to do i'm going to bring my face
to the bottom right here so you can see the entirety of the screen
and then i'm going to bring up the caption for the next item that we're
going to talk about and in here well we have a um
as you can see there is a command that you can issue in the terminal to create
a new flosser project so every flosser project has different
properties it has for instance a name which is the entire like the name of the
entire project um and also one of
the main properties of flutter project is
identifier now the identifier wouldn't be so
important had it not been that flutter can actually deploy to ios and android
and an identifier for an ios app and an android app is
actually what defines that application as unique
as on the app store where ios ios users and ipad os users can download
applications and on the um play store where android users can
download android apps so these identifiers are as
i mentioned in one of the previous chapters are kind of like reverse domain
identifiers so it's kind of like if your website is
foobar.com and your application is called baz
then your reverse domain identifier for your application will become dot
foobar.bass so it's kind of like
you take your domain name and reverse it so if foobar.com becomes com.fubar and
then you put dots after that and then you put your actual application name
so these identifiers need to be unique and by that i mean like
if a if a developer on the ios app store or google play
store is already gone and registered the reverse um basically that item
identifier.com.fubar.bass for any of their applications so they
said okay here's my application called image gallery but it has a completely
random identifier of com.foobar.pass
then you as a new developer even if you want to do the same funky uh deployment
to the app store you can't register that name anymore because because it is
already taken so
think of the identifier of your project as
what is gonna carry on from the start of where you create your project all the
way through to the app stores okay so
it is quite important that you actually choose it wisely because if you don't do
that wisely from the absolute start unfortunately you will have to do some
filling around in the future to go and update that yourself so
um so i would i would really suggest and
recommend here that you take a little bit of um time to think about what that
identifier is going to be what you prefer that identifier to be
and what you're comfortable with and what for instance if you have a domain
name as a developer for the app store and for google play store
so if you have a domain name already registered on your name i suggest
strongly then that you use that and if you have domain names personally and
domain names selected as like a
and for your company then you need to now know whether you're going to release
this application under your name personally or if you're going to release
it on your company's name so these all play a role but
without further ado let's just go and create our project here and
um i to be honest with you i personally
haven't really thought about whether i want to release this application as a
private person or if i want to create it under my company and i think
since my developer account is at apple and at google is under
my company's name which is pixelity ab in sweden then i'm actually going to use
that company's domain name which is pixelity.se
because s is like the swedish domain name just as code.uk is the
um british one for instance so i think i will do that so let's go to
and open a new terminal let's go to terminal um
i don't see my screen right now but i'm just going to bring up a new terminal
window here
and bring it up so that you can also see it um
and i'm gonna increase the size of the text so it is clear what i'm typing okay
so let me go ahead and create a project so i'm gonna go to my development um
folder where i have all my projects and i'm gonna go to projects
flutter okay and then as you can see is flutter
create and then and then dash dash org as an
organization and i'm going to see say se dot pixelity
now as i said my domain name is called pixelity.sc but your org needs to be the
reverse of that okay so remember reverse identifier so reverse domain identifier
so then if your for instance organization
is hello dot com then here you would have
to write com dot hello alright so i'm gonna say s epixody but you
shouldn't do this so if you're following along with this course please just
choose an identifier for your domain that it makes sense to you and if you
don't have a domain if you if you're not bothered by all of that if you're not
going to release your application to the app store you don't even have to care
about this just put anything in here you could just say
come um making stuff up
if that's what you want so it's not a big deal to be honest with you so just
go ahead and pick an identifier so i'm going to say s epixody because
that's my reverse domain name and then in here you have to write your
app application name so
um what should we call this application to
be honest with you i i mean i personally haven't really
made up my mind what this application should be called maybe we should call it
uh my personal
notes my personal notes or my notes
something like that or
private notes okay
all the private notes
or notes list i don't know not my notes that would work
sd pixel in my notes yeah why not and
let's just call it my notes then all right
so let's go ahead and do that flutter
create and i can see i mean actually i'm very
grateful that we got that little notification on top so let this do its
work and um
it did its work and it's done and it called something and it created a folder
you can see called my notes and on top of this window if you saw
then there was a little message printed a new version of flutter is available to
update to the latest version just run flatter upgrade so that was not a part
of this course i didn't mean it for this to happen but i can't control it either
because flutter is a tool that is being developed by google it's an open source
tool when there is a new version when you run any of these flutter commands
and it's going to check um with the version repository to see is
there any new version available and if there is then it's going to give me this
flutter upgrade message here so
um as i mentioned in the introduction of the course
i've planned this course quite a lot but i haven't i can't plan it 100 so things
will happen that i hadn't planned for and then we just have to roll with the
punches and i'm actually glad that this thing happened right here so you can see
how to upgrade flutter as well so as you can see it's very easy just copy
just say flutter upgrade okay so i'm going to go at the bottom of the
terminal i'm just going to say flutter upgrade
right so this is going to actually take some time depending on how big the
upgrade is because flutter is divided into
different kind of engines as you know flutter can output um
binaries or applications for ios it can output it for android it can do it for
mac os it can do it for um
windows and basically desktop searches and mac
windows linux and then you will have web as well so there's
quite a lot of things involved in flutter as you can see in here it's like
downloading everything necessary in order for you to be able to create
android applications so so after that is done you see it goes to
the ios tool so it's downloading but it's also i believe after it's done
downloading stuff it also needs to make sure that it can
build those tool sets so this is a process that might take some
time and in order to avoid us having to wait
for that entire process as you can see it's now going to web sdk
and blah blah so we don't have to necessarily wait for
this so i'm just going to create a new oh it actually finished so that was
quite fast all right so it it finishes work we don't have to do anything
special here um so that's how you upgrade flutter so
just run this command as suggested by the flutter tools itself flat upgrade
and then you're good to go okay so
we've done that step now so we've set up our project i'm just gonna move to my
notes here and i'm gonna make sure that that topic
is ticked and for the next item what we're gonna
do here is we're gonna talk about um we're gonna basically have a quick look
around the the environment set up by flutter when
you run photo create because the flow to create doesn't just like create an empty
director it actually creates the skeleton or the scaffold of your
flosser project but pretty much everything necessary for you to be able
to run that project okay so in this in this application i mean in
this in this step of chapter 8 we're not actually going to run the application on
any device that's for chapter 9 and for chapter 10.
but what we are going to do is to have a quick look around the
project structure so let me go to my notes here and what i'm going to do is
i'm going to use this code visual studio code
extension which is provided in the path so i can just say code dot which opens
up visual studio code in the current folder okay
so then once that is done i'm going to
bring a visual studio code here i'm just going to take a little bit of care to
ensure that you can see the important parts of the screen
okay and i'm going to increase the size quite dramatically so it's visible for
you as well it is very big on my screen but i think it's like
a nice size on the on the actual output video
alright so as you can see here is the folder created by flutter create
and there are quite a lot of bits and pieces in here
and i'm just going to tell you
a bit about a few of these folders and what they they represent so
one thing that you need to understand about flutter is that it actually is not
like um it's not really like react native
uh if you're familiar with that flutter on ios for instance it for those who
have done ios development uh flutter it outputs a native binary on your on your
phone a native um
fat binary basically for your uh ios application and it just puts one
view on the screen and then it graphically renders all its contents
using metal okay so if you're not an ios developer that probably doesn't make so
much sense to you but this part that i'm going to mention now
should make sense for everybody but when you create a flutter application
and the flutter create command basically spits out different parts that may be
necessary for your application to run on different platforms
one of those platforms one of the key platforms that flutter runs on is ioso
that is the folder that contains the native bits and pieces necessary for
photos to be able to run in an ios simulator or on an ios device
such as an iphone or an ipad okay so this is like as you can see it's the
project or the workspace and sorry and the workspace because for those of you
who are ios developers you will know that
there's a thing called cocoapods and flutter internally actually uses
cocoapods for ios if you're not an ios developer just know that
every ios or android or web application
can bring with itself dependencies and a dependency is a way for your application
to bring in code from other people in order to be able to achieve special
functionalities so there are various tools available for
ios developers android developers web developers to be able to bring in
dependencies for web for instance if you're writing a node application you
will just use npm which is a node package manager if you're using swift
you will probably just bring in for instance spm i think um swift package
manager or cocoapods and there's another a third one
um which i've kind of forgotten the name of um
which i may remember later if you're using android you're probably familiar
with gradle and that you can like use for
bringing in external dependencies so
so if
this is a platform of android and this is a platform of ios and here's web and
here's um desktop for instance
flutter sits on top of these so it can control all the um
all the small bits and pieces for these platforms to be able to be packed
packaged inside one flutter application which sits on on top here
and all these different platforms down here
excuse me they can have their own dependency management so the dependency
managements kind of sit under one layer under so
flutter then talks with these dependency managers and says okay you need to
install this dependency for me to be able to work
so the reason i mention all of that is
that is the reason you can see a workspace here and an xcode project and
that's because flutter internally is using a dependency manager
system called cocoapods which in turn creates a
workspace that
links together the main project and all its dependencies
if you're not an ios developer if you're not interested in all of this just know
that this ios folder is just so that your application run can
run on an ios device um
so that's that the next part which is important is the
test folder which we're actually going to use in this course
the test folder is where you create your tests
if you're not familiar with software development from before if you don't
have a background software engineering testing is
the ability for programmers in order to be able to make certain assertions about
their code and in order in order to make sure that they can automatically run a
series of tests against their own code to make sure that everything is
functioning as the programmer intended that to if you are if you if you are
coming from software engineering background that know that we're gonna
put our integration tests we're gonna put our
widget tests and unit tests inside this test folder okay so i hope that covered
everybody that's that may be watching this course
then you also have a folder called android and this is as you would expect
it is putting all the necessary files and folders that is required for your
android project to be hosting your flutter application so
just know that flutter kind of is a series of tools is like a mobile
kind it's like a beautiful sdk that gets injected into these native
applications and natively also renders its content so
um and just like we had a host ios
application here you will also have an android folder which contains all the
bits and pieces required for your application to be run natively
on android
phones and on android tablets so
this is as you can if you're an android developer you're probably like already
familiar with this like you have your app and build great gradle inside the
app folder so there's nothing like fancy going on here it's a simple android
application which you can actually uh if you have android studio installed
on your computer if you want to you can open that folder and actually have a
look around and even run that application as a native and android app
on your phone okay
so that is our android folder and as you
would guess then we have a web folder because
i think i mentioned this before but flutter supports uh deployment of flash
applications to the web as well so you can actually create web applications
with flutter it's nothing that we're going to discuss in this course
particularly but if you're interested in writing web applications with flutter
you can also google that so have a look at that if you're
interested in web applications because though web applications in flutter are
relatively new but foster has actually come really far with with that so people
are creating all sorts of websites with flutter already
sorry about that okay um then we have a little file here
called analysis options and um as you can see it says this file
configures the analyzer so um
if you are not coming from a software engineering background then you may not
know what analysis actually means but think of analysis as
a way for a flutter to be able to have a look at the code that you write
and and correct you
where it sees fit so where it sees that oh you've
made a mistake in writing something that could be written in a better way then it
consults this analysis options yaml file and then it says okay what are the rules
that i have to adhere to like do you want me to be very strict about certain
rules or do you want me to be like less strict about other rules or do you want
me to completely ignore certain mistakes that you're making so
the analysis options yaml file as it is pronounced
it allows you to basically define the roles that make
sense for your project in this course we're not going to talk
about so much analysis options to be honest with you but just know that it's
there so let me bring up the uh
the project structure here again um and the next thing that we need to
have a look at which is very very important is this file pop spec dot yaml
now um this is a file that i mean one of the things that you you'll need
to know about flutter and the basic structure that it creates for you is
that there are tons of documentations and documentations are like so so well
done in my opinion in in the flutter world where i personally come from like
the back-end developer development background like i'm doing django or
where i'm doing ios development sometimes documentation can for instance
on the ios native world be very kind of lacking
so flutter has gone like well above the
line of what is required from a developer's perspective in terms of
documentation and they provide a lot of documentation
and if you're not coming from a software development background the documentation
is pretty much like information provided by the developers
who created the tool for you in order to help you get better at that tool okay as
you can see here there's a file created for you pop special and you can see
there's lots of gray lines here prefixed with this
hashtag if you remove them you'll see that they
become normal sentences but if you put them back they become something called a
documentation and a documentation if you're not from software engineering
background it means just piece of text provided as an information block to you
which is not code anymore so the program is not going to
turn this into any sort of sort of a code it's just going to ignore that this
is just for you to learn okay so let's go back to this pop specky ammo
and talk about what it actually is pop spec yaml is such an important part of
flutter that i think that you need to actually
ignore i mean don't ignore the comments go and spend some time and read the
comments just to understand what they mean
so um what i'm going to talk about here is
a little bit about what this pop spike yaml actually is it is if you're for
instance from coming from a web background and if you've worked with
node.js then we will have some sort of a config
json file or if you're coming from django you'll have settings.pi file if
you're coming from native ios world what would be the equivalent of the config
it kind of will be kind of like your info plus file um
so i mean it is your it is kind of like a
control panel of what your project should actually be
looking like its icons the version number its name all your dependencies so
these things will be all placed inside inside this file and
when you change this file if you're already running your application then
flutter are automatically understands changes to this file and
then reconfigures itself if it can on the fly
with your new configurations if it can't then you may have to restart your
application like if you make drastic changes for instance if you bring in a
completely new dependency into your project
then the project cannot be like re-run immediately it needs to actually
recompile and link against that dependency it's just like humanly
impossible or computerly impossible for it to do so
um so let's have a little look around in
this pop specky ammo file as you can see there's a tag here called name and it's
and it's a value it's my notes and if you remember
from the terminal if i bring back the terminal
bring up the text a little bit uh this is what we created right this is
the project this is how we created the project so
we said flutter creates an organization of seda pixelity and then my notes all
right that is what the my notes is for this is
your project name my notes all right and this is a little just a little
description of what this application is all about now
you may be curious about what word is actually went
s e se.pixelity or whatever you created your
project organization under now you can see i search for it i said
command f in visual studio code on in mac or control f in linux and
windows and visual studio code and i don't know actually what the shortcut
for that fine is in uh android studio i just now heard studios
a little bit peculiar about its uh key mappings so it may not be command f on
mac or controller for linux and windows so i search here now for sepixology and
you can see that there are no results so this particular thing that i stressed so
much in the beginning that is very important you choose wisely
is not actually something that flutter itself needs as i mentioned it is
something that the different platforms that you'll deploy to need so if i now
actually say command shift f in visual studio code which searches in the entire
project say se.pixolity you will see that it is found in different places
inside this project for ios for instance you can see here is in the project pbx
approach and for android as well in our build
gradle so you'll see the application id became se pixelity my nodes
and for ios if you look around here as well you'll see that it is s e pixel in
my notes okay so
that was just side note um so the other thing that you'll need to
know about the pop spec yaml is this version number here and this is the
if you're not from a software development background um if you haven't
done software development before versioning is a way for you to tell
various places that you publish your application on for such as ios app store
or google play store what
if you have something new in your application
so for instance if you and this is this is how software is actually actually
labeled like a software has different properties
what you're deploying what you're developing here is a fluster application
but from the point of a store such as the app store it's it's just a package
of stuff with some properties like its name
identifier and its version now this version is very important because it is
a number usually three digits or i know that google play store
actually supports also four digits separated by a dot
and these these numbers actually mean something
special they if you begin from the left and then you
go to the middle and then to the right the left number is something called a
major number the middle number is called a minor
number and the right one and then most the rightmost number is usually called
the build number in normal software development the
process is kind of like this that you begin with an idea you say okay my
idea is to create a notes application that's that's the first idea that's idea
number one then you put one as the major number then you begin by zero and zero
okay so that's how a version number is kind of like birth
so you say one zero zero that's version one usually called okay
then you release that application you say okay i'm fine with that version one
and then you're in the kitchen cooking some food and then you say okay um it
would be great if i could put like um if i could add
the ability for users to be able to delete their notes
it's not a huge functionality it's just a little bit um improvement on what i
already have in the store then you will go and say okay is that a
major idea or a minor idea hmm it's not a major idea a major idea
would be like a total rewrite of the application adding massive number of
features fixing massive number of bugs etc so it's not a major idea then you go
to the minor idea and that minor idea corresponds to this minor version here
so you say okay the previous one was zero this one is how big of a difference
hmm it's just a small future so let's just say one
it was a huge like uh minor idea
not major enough to be a major idea but minor
but quite a big minor idea then you would probably like
from zero to maybe two or three it's not so popular to do that usually
would go chronologically in that order like one two three four but you're also
welcome to jump versions um
in special cases so let's say then you say okay i fixed that
and i'll now make it build and send it to
apple and google just remember that your previous build
was build zero now
depending on how your project is structured like you may decide that okay
every build that i make i'm going to actually increase this build number so
the previous one was zero now it's gonna be one then it's going to be two three
four five six blocks so every time you make build and send it out to your
consumers even if they're a group of testers or
people who are your only consumers may actually just be
people who are downloading your application directly from the app store
or google play store or from the web they may be interacting
with your application as well then you may say okay every time i make
a new bill and send it out that's when i actually increase this build number
or depending on your project setup you may
come with into an agreement with your teammates to say okay we don't increase
the bills chronologically but every time we change the major or the minor we
actually reset the build back to zero and then we go up chronologically so
um i i don't want to go to be honest with
you too much into detail about the version but if you're
interested in software development and i think if you're watching this course
that kind of means that you're interested in software development
you'll need to know about this so just know that version is your way of
labeling your software and its features and what's new in it
with numbers okay so just remember major
uh minor build all right but you don't have to play with this so
much to be honest with you so i think in this entire course we're actually not
gonna play with it so all right
uh the next bit of information in the pop special is the environment as you
can see there it says sdk now when you see sdk just think of
software development kit and this sdk is referring to the flutter
sdk so it means that if you share your source code with some
other developer who's sitting maybe on the other side of the planet
if they get your source code and they want to for instance be able to test
this application on a simulator or an emulator on a real device then they are
required to have flutter sdk version this
or less than this all right so you can actually get your flutter version by i
believe if you run flutter dash dash version
it will tell you that i'm plotter 281 and that as you can see here it says
yeah the sdk required in order to run this application is two
one five zero more than or equal to that at least at least two one five zero okay
so that's your sdk the flutter sdk the other part that you'll need to know
about is this section in the pops wiki ammo and that that is called the
dependencies and this is what we're going to talk about actually
um right now
um and dependencies as i mentioned before
uh are ways for you as a software developer to bring in code that other
people have written in order to make your application application function
better or function in a completely new way for instance
um you need to kind of be careful with dependencies just because
depending on what dependencies or libraries you bring into your project it
can actually make your life better or worse
dependencies are um
basically when you bring it in a dependency they're usually code written
by somebody else or other people that may be working on a library so
when you're if you're not coming from software development background then you
will need to know this and i'm just going to warn you from from now so that
you've heard it at least from somebody dependencies when you're picking
dependencies just be a little bit careful in that
they may it may be that they initially make your
suffer better but
since dependencies are code written by other people
and other people's priorities change their lives may change so that they
don't have time enough enough time to continue working on those dependencies
so i have personally run into the issue
that uh we brought in a dependency into a project and then after a while we just
realized that oh the developer isn't uh
actively working on this and maybe even the developer made that library um
deprecated and deprecated is the world that a word that you'll get to know when
you work more with software development and deprecated kind of means that the
library is not supported anymore the library is not
is not actively being worked on anymore and the developers are encouraging you
to move away from them so
when you bring in dependencies what i'd like you to do is just to have a look at
who is behind the dependency and prioritize your picking and cherry
picking based on a few factors
if the divi if the if the dependency is written by a single
person um be a little bit careful about that
just because single persons priorities may change and they may not
be able to like continuously work on a
even if if it's an open source project they may not be able to continuously
work on that um if independence is written by an
organization especially an organization that you have a lot of
faith in then prioritize it a little bit higher
um at least that's my opinion
if a dependency is written by a bunch of independent people
under an organization prioritize that also higher than a single person who has
a who has a library under their private
name okay that doesn't necessarily always mean
that a dependency created by an organization is actually better quality
it just means that the chances of it being deprecated are a little bit less
than uh
chances of the same library being deprecated had it been written by a
single person under their private name so these may actually to be honest with
you sound a little bit high level at the moment
and you may think okay why do i have to need all
this it's just that it is very easy for newcomers to flutter to get
dependent on dependencies in that it's so easy to bring in a dependency and
just work with it that people forget that oh
this is actually code written by a single person sitting in there in their
room just like me sitting here and telling you not to listen to people who
are sitting in their rooms but i believe it is very important to
try to steer your thoughts towards a little bit more
constructive dependencies that are good for your project in the long run but if
you're writing an application i just want to release it and don't care about
it anymore after you've released it maybe
maybe it's okay to bring in a dependency from just a
that that dependency that you don't even care about but i would even challenge
that idea of releasing an application which you may not care about after the
first release but because that's usually not a good idea
okay a lot of talk about dependencies but i think that had to be said
so we're talking about dependency i'm just gonna bring in the captions so
um now here you can also see there is a
dependency dependency here by default brought into you by flutter itself
called cupertino icons and cupertino icons is a dependency that
i believe that the flutter team itself is actually behind
so you may be thinking okay what are these
dependencies like where do they come from they actually come from normal
people and companies so i'm going to bring up a
um website here for you and it is called pop.dev i'll bring it
up so that you can actually see it here and um
you can see that in this website popped up there you can search for dependencies
so i'm actually going to copy this cupertino icons from here
and i'm going to paste it right there um kupertino icon just enter and i'm
gonna press on it and you'll see that it's published by the flutter team
themselves okay so
pop.dev is the website where you will search for dependencies so you just
search for a package and then it will bring up results here for you so
um this is how you'll search for dependencies okay
um and
now that we talked about that let's also talk about something called dev
dependencies they have dependencies are
dependencies that will bring into your project
which are useful only under development so
if you're familiar with software engineering the normal dependencies will
get linked to your project and then you will they will be shipped with your
application whereas dev dependencies there are only dependencies that
you under the development time will use in
order to make your software better and as you can see here one of the
dependencies for instance is flutter test
or flutter lens in this case as well excuse me
okay so there are lots and lots of things to talk about here and as you can
see here in the future actually we'll work with this that you can bring in
assets and images and bringing them into your project okay
so this is a quick look around at the pub
spec yaml and i'm going to let this be here
i'm just going to tick in my notes here that pops back yaml we've talked about
it now to the important part
we actually in our application we're going to need some dependencies in order
to be able to continue working with the application now
we haven't talked so much about firebase before but just know that firebase is
a tool that allows you to kind of go serverless but also have a
server now serverless is just a fun funky word that is being used nowadays
to describe a server written by somebody else so a server that you don't
personally have to write if you don't come from a software development
background for instance you're a product owner or a designer
a server is where your data sits in the cloud kind of
so
you as a developer sitting in front of your computer right now you're writing a
flutter application and your flash application is going to be installed on
ios and android devices and that is the client the client is the consumer of the
data sent by the server okay so the server is where the logic sits on a
computer in the cloud okay and firebase is a computer in the cloud just think of
think of that that is written by google so you control it with simple commands
on your computer but it controls your data so your client your flutter
application can connect to it and grab the data and read the data and
manipulate the data on the client side so
now in order to talk to firebase we actually need some um
dependencies and firebase um will i'll bring up my safari window here
now let's have a look at firebase core i'm going to search for it
click on it firebase core as you can see it's written by the publisher is
firebase.google.com and just remember that flutter is
actually a tool created by google as well so
i personally think that anything related to firebase is completely okay to bring
in into your flutter application has a dependency all right
so um i'm going to go here and then say
we need four dependencies for this particular project okay so
if you're in visual studio code you can bring um
the terminal up uh i actually forgot the command for bringing the terminal i
think on my mac is control backtick but i believe you can also always bring
up terminal advice going to terminal and new terminal okay now i can see there
are two terminal windows here okay now i'm going to get rid of the explorer on
the left hand side so you can see that the data a little bit better here
there are four dependencies that we need to bring into our project all right and
i want you to follow along with this exactly as i'm doing
previously what we had to do in order to i mean previously in the previous
versions of flutter if you wanted to bring in a dependency then you'd have to
go and say you go to your in your pop spec and then
add your dependencies manually with special versions and then
you have to go to those dependencies top dev websites to see the current version
all but with the latest versions of flutter
you don't have to do that all you have to do is just to say flutter pop add
and i'm going to do that right now
so that's how you bring in a dependency all right
the first dependency that we need is firebase core so just enter this command
it'll take some time perhaps
okay then say the same command but say
firebase off i'm gonna have a look at my notes
basically here to make sure that i'm entering the correct dependencies
and i'm not going to talk so much right now about what these dependencies
actually are because that is going to take a lot of
time as well so let's just bring the dependencies in there are four
dependencies so the next dependency that we have to bring in is cloud
firestore
and
let's go to the next one and we say that
cloud firestore is the third dependency and then we say firebase analytics
so that is the fourth dependency so
we've brought in four dependencies at the moment if you look here
there is a firebase core which is like the
the kernel the main important parts parts of firebase which again is what
we're going to use as our server where all the nodes for all our users are
going to sit the next one is firebase auth
auth is the short form let me see where did it go um here firebase off that is
for authentication and
um i haven't yet shown how that our application is actually going to look
like but auth is for authentication is where our users will
be able to register uh log into our application and log out
and also get email confirmations to send to their emails in order to be able to
verify the account so auth is for authentication and that's
what we're gonna use it for in order to make sure that people who
are interacting with our application they're actually logged in okay
the next part is cloud firestore and this dependency is used for when we
actually store a logged in users notes in the firebase backend
all right it's just funky names to be honest with
you they're just names decided by developers just like me and you so
and the next part is firebase analytics and that is for
if you use firebase analytics when you basically set up your firebase backend
you will get some free analytics in for instance oh which
screen did the user go to which button did they press and you can have a look
at these analytics when you then look at your firebase console which we're gonna
talk about later i mean i know all of these are quiet um
maybe a high level if you're not if you're not familiar with firebase you
may be like what the hell did we just do and that is okay you don't have to know
all of this just know that we are these four dependencies are stuff we need in
order to make our application function all right so now that we've added these
dependencies you can actually go back to your popspakiano file and kind of have a
look here at the dependencies that we added and
you can see all of them were added here automatically for you with their latest
versions okay so previously in previous versions of flutter we had to do this
manually but now you can just say flutter pop ad and it will add the
dependencies for you directly to pop special all right
so great a lot of things we discussed here
it almost took 50 minutes to go through all of these basics but i believe
actually basics should take more time to explain than the more advanced stuff
because the more advanced you get the less
explanation you need so that is why all these basic things basically take time
to explain [Music]
okay i'm just going to take in my notes that
we've talked about all of these
topics and i think this is actually a wrap for
chapter number eight so chapter number eight we talked about um
how to set up our project we've actually set up our project now we've set up our
dependencies had a look around uh the default flutter template and we also
talked about pop special so that's great stuff in chapter number
nine we're gonna talk about my favorite which is the ios app setup and in this
chapter actually we're gonna go through a lot of things profiles certificates
we're gonna talk about app ids a lot a lot a lot i can see here in the
list so i'm really excited actually for chapter number nine
so go grab a cup of coffee or a cup of tea
and i'll see you in the next chapter hello and welcome to chapter nine of
this course in this chapter we're going to talk
about the setup of our ios app and as i mentioned it i think it was in um the
introduction uh chapter in the absolute first
actually it's not a chapter it's just introduction to this whole course
um we talked a little bit about what we're planning to do with this
application that we're developing here and um two of the things that we're
going to do is to actually release the app in the app store and in the play
store now if you're not planning to actually do that you could
potentially skip over this chapter um
but i still believe that if you're planning on becoming a flutter developer
you need to know how these things work because
being a flustered developer depending on what kind of flutter developer that you
actually want to become um with me assuming that you want to
become an actual flutter developer where you can for instance work on different
applications and release them personally or you can work in like a team con
concept uh and in the context of a team where you
work with other developers inside a company for instance in order to work on
their applications and release them than in the app stores so
if you're if you fall into any of those categories that you actually want to
release your application then i strongly believe that you should know how to do
that yourself so although you may be a part of a part of
a team of a huge organization where the release process is its own like process
that you basically hand over your source code to them and then they basically
build it and repair it and release it but if you want to become like a
full-fledged flutter developer or a mobile developer for that matter you'd
need to know how to actually release your
applications okay so in this chapter we're going to talk
about releasing your app or actually we're
going to talk about preparing your application for releasing in
app store later so what you need to know
is how do you set up your flutter application so that you can actually
build it later and release it in the ios app
store okay and if i bring up the next caption here
you'll see that in order for you to be able to
build your application and then deploy it in the app store you need an ios
developer account and i talked about this previously um
that how what a developer account is and that
you'd have to apply for it i think it was in chapter one we talked about this
but if you've jumped over that chapter you'd need to know that you have to
apply for a developer account at apple and once granted that developer account
then you're going to be able to get access to a portal portal called the
app store connect app store connect is your portal for
managing your applications and uploading to the app store
downloading some debug information etc which i'm not going to go into so much
detail right now and it also has a side note as a developer you will get access
something called i think the developer portal or something like that i think
it's called i believe so i think we just call it
developer portal or developer developer site
so you'll get access to that and you'll be able to manage things such as
certificates and profiles okay so which we're going to talk about soon
actually so let's say that you have your developer
account and if you don't have your developer account then please just go
and search online for register developer account or just watch the first chapter
i have to look at my notes actually here and see if that's what we talked about
in chapter one actually yeah i can see here chapter one
was titled developer accounts and in that chapter we talked about how to
register for an ios developer again in depth so please go and watch
chapter one if you haven't done that and if you are planning to actually release
your application in the ios app store
so sorry about that
so now you know that you need the developer account and it costs a little
bit of money i think it's about 99 so in sweden it's about 990 swedish crowns
something like that or 1000 swedish crowns almost
so um now that we've talked about the
developer account let's talk about the certificates and profiles because this
is the thing that trips up a lot of mobile developers when they come to ios
development um i mean i've been doing ios
development since late 2000 2007 when
there was pretty much no um ios sdk as such it was like just a set
of tools and very little library support because originally ios apps by steve
jobs definition were supposed to be web applications and then
apple just transitioned to disbelief that yeah we actually have to have
native applications so they released some tools and xcode was there so you
could build some simple applications with ios opengl es what's there so you
can build some games as well but
how it started was that apple wanted to make sure that the
applications that are developed can only be distributed through the app store so
they said that okay if i give vandal for instance a
developer account he shouldn't be able to create his own app store because they
it's just a i'm not going into the details of what
why they're doing that there's a whole topic and what we could discuss like a
few days we could talk about that whether it's a monopoly or not i don't
know so i'm not going to go into the detail about that but what you need to
know that is there is an app store the um
basically just called app store but you could call ios app store mac apps or
whatever you want and apple has control over that so it's
apple who sits there and like controls the
measures that apps that are published on the app store they're of a good quality
for instance okay so apple themselves have a certificate now a certificate is
like a piece of paper uh just imagine a piece of paper certificate that they
hold onto and they said okay whatever we publish on the app store
um it comes from us okay so every app on
the ios app store comes actually from apple i don't mean
that the apple has written the app i mean that apple has signed the app using
their certified that piece of paper okay so
and then when the app gets downloaded to your iphone your iphone actually checks
is this a is this a trusted application where does
it come from so ios as an operating system it can
contain and you can install many different types of applications that
come from many different types of sources
such as the ios app store or you could actually
download application that comes directly from a specific developer
now all these applications need to be signed
they need to be signed with a certificate that is just to identify
where they come from so certificate is a piece of paper that you as a developer
hold and every application excuse me every application that you
develop will be signed using that certificate okay so that certificate is
your identity as a developer and it gets kind of
carried around in with your application to the destination so if you develop
this notes application that we're doing in this course and you sign it with your
certificate then your application is going to have that certificate signature
inside it so when i send it to apple and then apple is like aha that's this
developer who created this app okay and then when apple then
says okay your application's fine you can't release it to the app store then
apple re-signs your application with their own certificate
that is just to make sure that your application after it's been signed with
apple certificate can be distributed into the ios app store and downloaded by
millions of users around the world so it's just sir just know that certificate
is your identity as a developer okay [Music]
now now that we talked about certificates let's talk about profiles
because that also is a tripping point for some developers
um especially if they don't come from like a native ios development background
which i do um
profiles you see a certificate identifies you
in short profiles identify your app so that's like the
very short way of saying it so you as a developer might have
10 20 30 applications that you're developing or you have developed
each of these applications will have their own identity
and that identity at the end is tied to you as a developer so you say here's my
certificate here's who i am
but when you then create an application then that application also needs to
identify itself it will be like here i am i am an application signed with this
profile using this certificate so just know that a profile is kind of like
an identity for your application and different flavors of that
application and a certificate is an identity of you
as the person who developed that application all right
so and if you notice i just said different
flavors of your application and by that i mean that if you're not
coming from a development background um if you're for instance coming from a
design background and you have a figma file or visio file that you're designing
your wi-frames and whatever if you're coming from a product owner ownership
background than your probably may have like um
working with jira or excel sheets or whatever wherever you put your
requirements you may not be familiar with different flavors of an application
but if you've worked a little bit close with an app
team then you'll know that there are different flavors of every application
and those flavors are usually i mean they're
usually two flavors one is a development flavor and the
other one is a production flavor a development flavor is the application
you see if you sit with developers with software engineers that are working on
your application on a daily basis they're coding they're
fixing things they're fixing bugs adding new features and then they will provide
the product to you as a software uh as a product owner for instance or a designer
and you will download that flavor on your application and be like okay this
this looks fine great now
all of a sudden you press a button and that button crashes the application so
the application just disappears oh it crashed
well at that point if the developers were doing their job correctly then they
had had to put some crash analytics into the application
that as soon as the application crashes or
something bad happens to the application of that flavor of the application that
you installed on your
iphone or android phone or tablet or whatever and they will get
something called a crash report a crash report is as its name indicates
it's just a report where the crash information is completely visible and
they probably even know which button you tapped at what time and what was the
information that your app was carrying at the point
that it crashed so it helps them debug and fix that problem
now these flavors of the application that you install on your phone on a
daily basis were working mobile developers are usually called debug
applications and a debug application it's just a way of saying that the
developers who created it it created the application have the opportunity then to
fix any bugs that may arise with more information than they would usually have
had they released this application to the store for millions of
others to download so that is a flavor it's a debug flavor or
is a development flavor okay and it just means that it's a daily it's kind of
like a updating regularly application that only
very close circle of people close to the project can download so that's a flavor
okay another flavor of an application that
gets released by developers could be the production
flavor and the product production flavor is
the same as the debug flavor but a little bit like
some stuff maybe removed from it some sensitive information that may be logged
otherwise maybe removed from it it's just like a stripped-down version
for security purposes not stripped-down version of like features or anything
it's just they make it tighter they make it so
that it is a little bit more secure like some extra stuff may be removed from it
extra stuff that otherwise developers only may need so
when it then gets packaged into this beautiful little uh
yeah beautiful little package basically then it will also be a new flavor called
the production flavor so now you have two flavors one is like
for a close circle people sitting next to the product
in the same product room or now that everyone's working
remotely maybe people are sitting at home etc and that is like the product
team closely developers testers product owners designers uxers everyone that is
the closed circle they get the development builds usually
and then when you get to sending your application to apple for
instance or to google for review then you would
get the production flavor okay the reason i'm talking about flavors is that
these different flavors on ios at least are basically
assigned with their own specific profiles so then you'd have a
development profile and you would have a production profile and these prof
profiles dictate to your application what it what it can and it can't do
for instance one of the capabilities of a development profile in the ios world
is that your application can actually be installed on a telephone hooked with a
cable or even without a cable and debugged remotely so
this is one of the cool things you can do with ios in that you can actually
like if i'm a developer sitting here i can
get the designer's telephone and say oh yeah you want the application like do
you want to actually see what i'm working on yeah she or he would say
you would connect your their phone to your
computer and enable something called remote debugging
and then you would disconnect it and then give the phone back to them and
whenever they want the application running live on their phone as you're
developing it you can actually run the application with your xcode
live under uh iphone or ipad so
that is its own flavor and the profile which is the development profile
dictates to that application that you can be debugged but if you then want to
sign your application with a production profile and send it to apple
that profile dictates that this application is not allowed to be
debugged and when you
create your application and send it to apple you need to make sure of two
things among many other things but
certificate and profile wise you need to make sure of two things
the application is signed with your production certificate and the
application is signed also with the production profile which is hooked to
the production certificate so first the certificate should be there using the
certificate you create the profile with the profile you sign your application
and then you send this application to apple apple then looks oh everything is
is in order the profile to use was a
a production profile and the certificate linked to the profile was also correct a
production certificate identifying you as a developer
so that was almost 16 minutes of
information about profiles and certificates for ios but i think they're
so paramount in i mean it's so important to
understand that you shouldn't really jump over
these concepts as if you're if you want to become a mobile developer it's so
important so
now enough with concepts now let's talk a little bit
about um
the developer account and here i actually have a link which i'm going to
open in a separate window and then i'm going to bring it to the
foreground so you can actually see
so here is the developer account as you can see on apple's website and i'm gonna
bring my face a little bit to the right bottom right so zoom into the window
here and this is actually on developer
then you would go into accounts okay so after you've registered an account
then you will be able to go in here and sign in with your account and i'm going
to sign in with my um companies apple id
there we go and then it says okay we sent you a verification code and i have
my apple watch here so i'm i'm just gonna
say i didn't get a code and text me the code all right
so in a short while i should be able to get
a verification code here and it is important that you don't show
this verification code to other people it's just you shouldn't do that so i'm
gonna remove the screen from where you can see it and i'm gonna enter the code
that was sent to me it is six digits and it is uh just basically digits and
bring the phone i bring the browser up now and i say trust this browser okay
[Music] so
here you will see that um license agreement has been updated okay so we
should be able to review that later so i'm gonna increase the
space that this screen is taking at the moment so you can see it in its entirety
and you can see that now that you you've logged into this account you should be
able to see things such as overview membership people's
certificates ids and profiles okay so and then what i talked about earlier
which is your app store connect okay so um
and what happens here basically is
that in the membership people's certificates
ids and profiles is where you will manage your certificates and all your
profiles as i mentioned before so
um here it is very important that you
basically set up a good ground for your uh certificates create the dev
certificate the the production survey and then you
create your profiles after that which we're gonna talk actually about in this
um in this chapter
so here are the missing pieces for us in
order to be able to carry on
so we need as i mentioned before certificates profiles and app ids app id
is something that i didn't mention before so i think it's just important
that i mention what an app id is an app id is
additional to the profile that you create an app id is an identifier that
apple and you use in order to know which application you are
talking with both you yourself and also
if you for instance in the in the future are going to enable
features such as push notifications now if you're not familiar with what
push notifications are they're basically remote notifications remote information
that you can send from a cloud somewhere on the internet
to a user's phone so when they get their phone they will see oh here is a message
from this application you can think of it as remote messages
just as if someone sent you an sms or an imessage
or for instance if you're using whatsapp or telegram someone writing a message in
a chat and then you're getting a notification on your phone that is
called a push notification so an app id is used mainly in order to
be able in order for you as a developer to be
able to specify different capabilities of your application for instance that it
can receive push notifications that it can
for instance store secure information on the phone etc etc so
so when i previously mentioned that you need a certificate and profile in order
to sign your application you also need an app id in order to identify your
application and its capabilities okay so we're going to talk about that soon
actually
so now
what we need to do here before we actually get started creating a
certificate uh is to
talk about the keychain now if you're if you're if you have a
developer account here and you are planning on releasing your application i
kind of can basically assume that you have
a macintosh so that you have registered for an account
and that you want to be able to sign your application with a certificate and
profile however you may be in a group of people
who doesn't have a who doesn't have a macintosh and xcode
etc but you still want to be able to release your application to the app
store so you may want to for instance create your certificate profiles an app
id and then later send that information to some sort of a cloud hosting service
for for them to sign your application and then send it back to you something
like that i have never done that myself but you may be in that group and uh
for the sake of being inclusive i think it's important to talk about that
um now let's talk about what i've put up here
as the caption and that is like the certificates in the keychain
you see every certificate gets created by you as a
developer sending a request to apple now
this request is you basically creating a digital
signature on your computer which
your computer holds onto then your request you will send it to
apple apple says oh you're asking for a certificate okay here's the certificate
and then you download that certificate and then when you double click on the
certificate it gets installed and hooked to your original request okay so here's
the certificate and here's the private key so
the private key is just a piece of information that your computer stores
digitally on only your computer so that later the downloaded certificate can
actually be hooked to it creating a chain okay so
your application when it gets signed with your certificate that you then
download from apple it actually contains some information
about the certificate and the private key and then you send the application
that was signed using these two pieces of information to apple so
there's a lot of information i know but i think it's important for every mobile
developer who wants to release something for ios appstore to
know this um now this
private key and the certificate they both get stored inside a program on your
computer called keychain if you have macintosh
and i can bring up keychain actually now let me see which i have three
screens here so i don't know which one is gonna get open on
so i will bring up keychain here um
and i will show you how it looks like so
here is an example of keychain and you can see here there's a distribution
certificate and a development certificate okay
and these certificates i didn't create them i downloaded them but the things
under them this is the chain i was talking about this is the key that i
created okay so when you request a certificate from
apple you actually create this thing on your computer and you upload this thing
to apple for them to create a certificate hooked to that kind of not
you don't actually upload exactly this but something that is related to this
okay so
for us in order to be able to continue i think it's important that i actually
delete these existing certificates from my computer
so i'm just going to go like this and i'm going to be like
delete two items all right and delete them just like that
okay so now they're gone now what we need to do is
um
here let me put up the captions so you can see
so that was the certificates and now we also need to talk about um
we also need to talk about actually deleting the profiles now this is an
interesting part if you already have like profiles installed on your computer
you may not want to do this but i'm just going to show you this step so that we
start with a clean slate okay so you're not supposed to do this if you exactly
know what you're doing with your certificates but if if this is the first
time you're doing this and there may already be some certificates for you on
your computer for some reason then this is the way to actually get rid of them
so i'm gonna open up finder um
let me open up finder here and i'm gonna bring it up here
and what we need to do is to go into a folder called um
i believe it's called library and then mobile
device and then something called provision
profiles okay and you can see here um and i will show
you this path again so it's my user library mobile device and then provision
profiles okay so after i've gone into that folder i'm
going to delete these profiles that are here okay
so you don't have to do this if you don't want to and you know exactly what
you're doing but i'm just doing it to show you that profiles are always stored
in that location for your user okay and what you can also do which i really
like is to if you say add columns here and kind of like drag it into your
favorites so you don't have to type that path every time so let's just put it
here okay so that every time i want to install the profile i can just click
here and put my profile there all right
all right um
now that we've done that the next step as the caption shows here is to delete
our existing certificates and profiles from apple's
development account so let's go to certificates ids and profiles here on
the left hand side and you'll see here i have quite a lot of things stored right
here okay you see distribution development development blah blah
so what we can do here is to go ahead and delete these certificates on the
left hand side you see it's a certificate so there are quite a few of
them so what i'm going to do is just to tap
on this one and just say revoke revoke tap on the next one and just revoke them
one by one so and again if you're new to ios development and you've just gotten
your development account you don't even have any certificates so this screen is
going to be empty for you so revoke revoke so your screen is gonna look like
this all right so now that we don't have certificates
i'm also going to go into profiles and delete these profiles so if i just go in
here and kind of like say all my profiles and then just delete this is
going to be fine as well so sort of problem all right so now i've deleted
all my profiles and certificates
and that was the goal of this part of the chapter
9 i believe so yeah i've now deleted the existing
development and production certs and
then that is done with the profiles as well they're also gone
so what we need to do now is to create something called a development
certificate and just to recap a development certificate is
a certificate that will allow you as a developer to run and test your
application while you're developing it on real
iphone or ipad all right so it's it's not necessary for releasing
the application but i personally after many years of experience developing
mobile applications i've come to the conclusion that i prefer actually
running my application testing my applications are real devices as i
develop because you also have emulators and you also have simulators that
simulate and emulate the capabilities of iphone and
android phones or tablets but i've come to the conclusion that it's actually for
me at least better to test my application real phones or tablets
so in order to be able to do that and if you have for instance an iphone
connected to your computer um and you want to test your flag
application on that iphone then the first thing you need to do is to create
a development certificate so you need to identify yourself as a developer to
apple so let's go to the certificate section and then just say create a
certificate and then choose apple development actually sorry ios app
development this is interesting it says
yeah so it says apple that's very interesting so you can basically use
something called apple development but we're not going to do that we're just
going to say ios app development at the moment okay
so let's do that just choose ios app
development and just press continue and here it says create a new certificate
and create a new certificate is it's waiting for you to tell it that you're
asking for a development certificate and you need to choose a file now this is
the magic part you need to now go back to
keychain so let me see if i can bring up keychain again
and in here just go to keychain access menu
and then say a certificate assistant and then say
request a certificate from a certificate authority okay
so i'm gonna press that and i'm gonna put my company's email here
and the common name i'm just gonna leave it as my name all right
and then i'm just going to say save to disk
all right so um
that's what we're doing now then i'm gonna say continue and it says
okay i'm gonna write a file on your desktop or wherever you want with that
request so save it somewhere that you know where it is actually saved so i'm
gonna save that and then say done all right now you see
that certificate request in itself didn't create a certificate it's just a
certificate request but what it did is that it created a private key
and you can actually go to your keys here and you'll see that there was a
if i say kind private key so one of these keys is the one that was just
created right now okay i don't exactly know which one because
it doesn't have a date but it's just one of these so every request for creating a
certificate it creates with itself a private key
okay so keep that in mind let's go back to my certificates
now that that file has been saved on your desktop just say choose file and
then go to your desktop and pick that certificate request okay
and it's you see here certificate request search sign request
and just say continue and then it says okay it expires in a
year and you need to keep that in mind because development certificates do
always expire in a year and you need to by basically renew them okay
so but for now you don't have to worry about that because we're not going to
take a year to develop this application so let's just say download and it got
downloaded to my downloads folder so i'm gonna bring up my downloads folder
uh and actually just
gonna show you here like this
so here is
the file that got downloaded you see it's a cert file all right now this
certification in itself it doesn't contain your private key remember the
private key is in the keychain so what you need to do is just you need to
double click on this all right so double clicking on it you see it will
then create a certificate in your keychain under my certificates and login
keychain that is linked with your private key you see so this is what you
downloaded from apple this is what you created on your computer by requesting a
certificate and when you double click on the downloaded certificate these two get
hooked together okay so that's it that that is what you have
to do to create a development certificate and the key related to it
all right now let's go to the production
certificate and we need to kind of do the same thing same process
in order to create our production certificate so let's go back to all
certificates and i'm just going to say plus certificate and
i'm gonna say ios distribution app store and ad hoc okay so choose that option
please and sorry i'm just gonna not also in my
notes here that we talked about the dev certificate
so let's go ahead and press continue here and you'll have to do the exact
same process as you did for the development certificate and create a new
certificate request so let's do the same thing just basically
kind of copy and paste the same process go to keychain access
certificate assistant request a certificate from a certificate authority
and just be careful a little bit with this because i've understood from what
i've what i've seen is that depending on what you've chosen here this menu
actually changes so
it could be that you kind of need to make sure in your keychain that you're
not selecting anything so just make sure that nothing is
selected and then go to um sorry then go to
certificate assistant and request a certificate for certificate authority
put your company's or your developer accounts
email there i'm just gonna pick solid a b
and then save to disk and then say continue
and then save it to desktop and since there is a file already there with the
same name from the previous step it's going to say are you sure you want to
replace it yes replace it and it got saved then i'm going to go
here and then choose the same exact file but it's
actually is a new file which got rewritten
and then say continue and you'll see now there is a download
so i'm going to download that and if i go
to my downloads folder um here i'll bring it up so you can see as
well um
let's see i'm going to bring it here you will see
that there is a new file called ios distribution that is your production
certificate okay so double click on that keychain it's open again and you'll see
now you have two certificates here iphone distribution and then iphone
developer so these are your certificates and keep
hold of them kind of like try to save them and if even if you don't save them
it's okay because they're now placed here so you can always export them okay
but it's also good practice just to keep hold of them
great now
sorry about that now we've created a developer and a dis
and a production or distribution certificate
let's talk about the next step and that is required for us to be able to release
or test our application on on phones so
let's go back here and to identifiers and in here is where you create your
application identifiers and you can see that they're actually tied to a specific
organization and identifier which we talked about
in which chapter was it that we talked about i think it was actually in chapter
eight yes if you have if you don't know what
an identifier is please go back to chapter number eight where i discussed
that so let's
press the plus button here and say that you want to create a new
app id okay press continue and then you will choose app here not an app clip
and then you will be presented with this screen here so i'm gonna
explain to you what all this is so in here the description um we're just
gonna print some information here that describes our application and to be
honest with you i don't remember what we actually called our application when we
created in the previous i can see it was called
my notes so i'm just going to say my notes
flutter application sample or flutter app all right
here the bundle identifier is very important that you actually specify it
correctly as we created it in our in chapter 8. so i'm going to bring up
the my notes application here i'm going to increase the font size so you can see
um if you remember where we created the application
with this command you see we said se.pixelity and then my notes meaning
that the application identifier from this point on is going to be
se.pixelity.mynotes okay with a dot in between all right so if i search for
that in our project let's say sepixolity.mynotes
you will see there are some results here you see so depending on how you created
your floater application depending on what organization you specified this
identifier may be different for you but since my identifier in this case is s
epixody my notes i'm just gonna copy that
and i'm going to bring it here make sure explicit is selected and just paste that
bundle id in there okay so yeah it's chosen
now if you remember what i said before an app identifier is not just the
identifier the bundle id itself but it's also like a list of capabilities that
your application can have now if you for instance want to have push notifications
you will also need to enable that in here now push notification is not not
something that we're going to do in this course so you don't have to do that but
all you need to do here after you've entered your app id prefix sorry your
app bundle an identifier and a description just press continue
and you can see that says okay are you sure everything's fine yeah explicit
yeah great and then i say register now that identifier got created all
right so
um you don't really have to do anything
with that identifier right now it's just that you have now registered that
identifier so no one else can basically take that app from you
so i'm gonna
actually
tick these items in my notes so that we know we've talked about it all right
now the next step is to prepare your
uh your application so that it can actually be installed and debugged or
tested on real phone now you can't see my entire setup but here i
have an iphone 12 pro which is just right here it's a little bit dirty
screen but that doesn't matter it's just my test telephone
and this phone
is connected as you can see with a cable to my computer and it is available for
my computer to see so i'm just going to unlock this phone right now with my
passcode and if i then bring up my
finder so here
you can see that it is available here right here okay
so it's my telephone and it has a special identifier and if you
want to get your device identifier which is what we need to do here as you can
see in order to debug on a real device we need a uid to register for our
profile so
when you i mean this is a kind of like a big thing to talk about because it takes
a lot of time but what i'm going to say here is that when you created that
development pro and development certificate the next step is for you to
basically register your device with apple so that apple knows on which
devices you actually want to test your application all right
and those devices they're stored in here in under the devices um tab
and there are ways to get your device identifier such as going to finder as i
just showed here and just tapping on your
device now i'm kind of going to do it off screen so you don't see the entirety
of what is here so
let me see if there's any way for you to actually get your device identifier yes
and it is i can actually see here there's a way to get that um
so what i'm going to do is i'm going to actually bring finder up here so you see
what happens i just tap on my phone now you need to register your device on
identifier under this devices tab before you create your profile okay
i'm not going to do that because my phone is already registered but you need
to do this on your own and the way to do that is to connect your phone or your
tablet which you want to test your flutter application on to your computer
then go into finder and tap on your phone and
then just click on this section now i'm not going to do that here and the reason
behind that is that every device says identifier really identifies that
device so you could go and register my device under your account
so and it's just not a good idea to show
your device identifier to others so i'm not i'm not going to be able to do that
unfortunately in this course but the steps you have to take is to click
here on this label and it will show you a
section called uuid copy that uuid and go into devices
section of the certificate identifiers and profile section of apple developer
account and add that uuid with a name to your account
okay so i'm just gonna assume you've done that and if you need some time to
go ahead and do that please pause this video and do that so
the key is just to get the identifier from here okay there's a way also get
your identifier your device identifier from xcode um and that works exactly the
same you just have to open xcode then go to um i believe go into menu and then
pick devices and from there you pick your device and you'll see it's
identifier right there so that was a lot of talk let's say that
you've already done that so what we need to do now is to go and
create a development profile all right so i'm just going to tick these items in
my notes as well so this is the exciting part now we're
going to go to the profile section and create a new development profile so
click on generate a profile and i'm going to say ios app development and
then say continue then it says okay choose an app id you
see now your profile is going to be linked with your app so
do this drop down here and you can see i'm just going to say my notes and this
is the app that i created and for you this id maybe a little bit
different the description maybe a little different but just choose the
um app id that you created in the previous
steps so i'm going to choose that i'm just going to say continue
now it's going to say okay which certificate is this profile connected to
do you remember i said that a profile is linked to a certificate this is what
that actually means so granted that you've created your
development certificate in as i talked about in this chapter just select your
certificate so and then say continue now
here it asks is that which devices do you want this um
profile which which device do you want your application which is signed with
this profile certainly to be able to run on now these all these devices come from
the devices section i've registered many devices so
um even some of my co-workers devices
which allow us to basically debug an application on their devices as well so
granted that you've done that
if you go back here then you will see those um
see those devices in this list right so i'm just going to say select
all just make sure my application can be run on all those devices that i've
registered okay then say continue and then you will give
it a name so i'm going to give it a name of my notes
dival dev profile
or just my notes dev okay i'm just going to say generate
and you will get some information about when it expires etc also expires in a
year so and then you'll have to say download
and we're going to do the exact same thing now for a distribution profile a
distribution profile is the kind of like the same dev profile but you cannot
debug your application with it all you can pretty much do with it is to sign
your application with that profile and send it to apple so that you can deploy
your application in the app store okay so press plus profile and in this and
this time go to distribution and say app store you see distribution subsection
and app store so press the continue button
then go here and then choose your application
so that was the development profile sorry now we have to go to production so
i'm going to bring the window a little bit up so that you can see it in its
entirety so then i'm gonna choose my notes
all right and then i'm just gonna press the
continue button here
um i'm gonna take it in my notes so we've
talked about the dev profile okay so now that you've done that uh
choose your assertive again you see it says okay now you're creating a
certificate a profile for a distribution then it should be hooked with some sort
of distribution certificate and since ios distribution certificate is the only
one that we created if you remember i deleted all my other certificates
so that's the only one left here just pick that and press continue
now give it a name i'm going to say my notes
prod production
and then i'm just gonna say generate it says
okay there you go and you can download it all right
now that you've done that you need to bring up your
downloads folder where your profiles got downloaded um
now you see these are the two profiles i got downloaded except with their
extension of mobile provision provision you need to install these somehow on
your computer so that you can sign your applications or your ios application
with this with these so what you need to do now is to copy
these two files i'm going to copy them like this and command c
and then bring them into your provision profiles folder i'm just going to
cut and paste them there okay so they're not in the downloads folder anymore so
there they are there are other ways of installing these
profiles some people rather drag it into xcode some people double click on them
and those are all fine but there's a little bit of a problem by doing those
methods compared with the method i showed you here if you double click
these profiles mac os knows how how to install them but
mac os just messes up their naming so they will be installed on their very
random names so if you come back to your provisioning profiles folder they may be
under some sort of a cryptic name that you don't recognize anymore so in this
way they basically keep their original name which
is very descriptive of what they actually are okay
okay that was that so now we've created a um dev profile and a prod profile
exciting stuff so what we need to do now is actually work we can say that we're
done with this screen here so i'm going to close that
and what i'm going to do here then is to what we need to talk about now is to set
up our project in xcode so that xcode understands that
our application needs to be signed with the correct profiles and certificates so
what i need you to do is to go to the ios folder in your flutter project and
just right click on it and say reveal in finder okay
after you do reveal in finder double click on the workspace in order to open
your flutter xcode workspace in xcode
and what you'll need to do now is to basically
make sure that your signing of your ios application is done correctly so choose
this icon on top left in your um i think it's project explorer or something
project navigator then on the targets
choose your targets and then go to signing and capabilities and just remove
automatic signing okay for this course we're not going to use
automatic signing i'm just going to take it
here in my notes that i've talked about removing automatic signing
so the next step is for us to be able to
tell xcode that for debug purposes in order for us to be able to run our
application on a real phone and debug that
application which profile and which certificate it needs to use
so what i'm going to do here is to go into this section here as you can see
debug on under signing and capabilities and then i can see that actually it is
going to it's already using the automatic signing
for debug and i'm going to remove that as well okay
so what you need what you need to do here is actually pick the right profile
here and it says my notes dev and my notes
profile sorry prod and you can see it says ineligible
and um that is because we don't have a
development team yet and alex and i'll explain that soon but for now just go to
your provisioning profile and say for debug purposes we're gonna use the
mynotes dev um
and then go to your release and then say i'm gonna use my notes prod okay and
here's a little error here you see it says producing profile my notes pro
doesn't include signing certificate apple development blah blah blah okay
that's that's fine don't worry about that
so what we need to do now is to actually
tell it um so i'm going to actually pick here
profound search setup release profile insert okay
so what you need to do here is to go to your build settings and make sure
that your development team
here is actually selected you see pixelity is for me and then for you it
may be something else so um now what i'm gonna do i mean
sometimes uh and i can see signing certificate here is actually not really
selected sometimes it can be that xcode kind of goes crazy when we play with
certificates and signings so i'm going to close xcode
i'm going to do the same thing here go to
revealingfinder finder open up in another window here so
i'm going to open up the workspace again
okay i can see we're still getting the problem provisioning profile minus that
doesn't include signing certificate apple development and let's open up our
keychain again and have a look a little bit here
and i can see unfortunately there is a profile you can see previously we had
two profiles and it is very unfortunate because um
so in here you can see this this development
certificate was created by us you see they're very tightly close to each other
these two we created but this is something that xcode has created and
that is because xcode tries to do automatic signing as you saw it was
saying automatically manage signing so by doing that it created a certificate
for me on my behalf which i don't want so the error that we're seeing here is
that xcode is now saying that this this
profile that you have here is not linked to this thing
which xcode created itself no one asked it to do that i didn't ask xcode to do
that so when you're working with is a woman just know that xco tries to do a
lot of magic for you and if you want to actually
do things manually it may get in the way
so what i'm going to do here is i'm going to delete this
development certificate because i didn't ask for it okay
so i'm going to say i believe actually that's the right one
yeah so i'm going to say delete delete and now you can see that error went away
simply because xcode was like ooh now i understand which one you're talking
about and then the provision profile of the
prod also is hooked
correctly so
now what i'm gonna do is as you can see here
i've opened the project here and then i have my actual iphone selected here to
be able to make sure that your application can actually run on this
phone now after all of this hard work is just to press the play button here
so i want to do that and i want to let it do its thing and if everything works
correctly um it's going to basically then um allow
us to run the application all right so now it says
now and this is a dialogue that you're probably also going to get
what's happening here is that it's trying to sign the application and all
its libraries using that profile
development profile and since that development profile is
linked to a development certificate in the keychain and that keychain is
password protected you see the login keychain it says i can't access that
certificate give me the password for the login keychain so i'm going to type that
and then i'm going to say always allow so let's do it let it do its thing
and this may depending on the machine that you're running this uh process on
it may take some time i can see it's saying now building so um
okay then i got an actual failure here it says cloud firestore wasn't found
and this is very interesting um actually i mean i didn't plan for this
to happen but it did happen i'm kind of glad that it happened
this happens usually when you um
when you add new dependencies to your projects such as these big dependencies
but they're not really linked to your project yet so the way to fix that is
i'm gonna let xcode be here okay i'm gonna close
this i'm gonna bring a terminal uh what i'm
going to say here is flutter clean i clean
ios or clear ios i think clean
so this is basically going to clean up how the ios project was set up and all
those dependencies all right now i'm going to close actually xcode as well
then what i'm going to say is to say flutter pop get
and flutter pop get what it does is that it sets up all our dependencies from the
beginning and just to make sure i'm going to go into the ios
folder and i'm going to say pod install
and could not be compatible version okay pod
[Music] install
dash dash update repo uh
hot install uh let's see if we can do an update repo
i'm just gonna do that uh without like explaining it right now so much and see
if that fixes our problem i'm going to bring up a new safari window and say
pod install update repo let's see what the command was but because i've
forgotten that
what update we have yeah um let's pawn install
i believe there is a variant of
repo update it's called okay pot install repo update let's see if this fixes our
problem and if cisco could not find compatible
version for podcloud firestore from blah blah
specs satisfying from dependencies were found but they require higher minimum
deployment target and that's very interesting
so what is happening here is
you see the deployment target that we have for our application um what it
means is that when we created the project with flutter
flutter said that what it does internally is says
this flutter application should be run on these ios versions and these android
versions and what we're seeing here is that
what we're seeing here is that we are using cloud firestore and cloud
firestore as a dependency is expecting our application to have a minimum
deployment version it means that cloud firestore cannot be used in applications
that for instance are trying to run on ios 7 for instance okay so what we need
to do here in your um flutter project just say command p in visual studio code
and open up a file called um pod file all right
you go in there and let's see
here we have some stuff set up let's go in here and just say platform ios and
what we're going to do is just to say platform ios 13
just just now i mean 13 it's really good because right now is ios 15 is available
so you could just say you're supporting 15 14 and 13. so i'm going to do that
and then i'm going to run pod install again
and this time i can see that things are going a lot better and it's installing
all our dependencies without a problem so
um what you need to know now what i did here was something that you probably
would need to do if you're comfortable with ios development so you need to fix
these problems by hand but before i explain what i actually did
you need to know about something called pod
and i explained this in the previous chapters about when we started in
chapter 8 when we talked about dependencies
flutter can in can create ios applications ios
applications dependencies are basically using uh cocoa pods
so cocoapods is a dependency management system for ios applications
and you need to just know that
you need to in order to be able to do the trick that i just did you need to
install cocoapods and there is a good website for that i mean you can i'll
bring up my and i say install cocoapods and then i go here and you just say
cocoapods and then there is a command that you need to issue in your computer
in order to install cocoapods okay so um after you've installed cocoapods
then you can go into your ios project and like
ask it to reinstall your dependencies so the key here though was for me to
uncomment this platform line in the pod file where my dependencies are managed
so i'm just going to say now i'm supporting ios 13 at the minimum
all right and then i manually ask the io the project to be recreated the ios
project to be recreated using pod install repo update
so after you've done that your dependencies
are generated and then i'm going to right click on ios again
and i'm going to say oh i can say open in xcode that's interesting will that
work i don't dare to be honest with you do that
revealing finder and then i'm going to do that and open a project so
i'm going to go now do command do i do command b maybe not let's just
run it directly so
so i'm gonna then bring up xcode and press
run again and let's see if it can then find
those dependencies that it couldn't find previously okay
so we're gonna
let it do its thing and it may take some time as you can see
because there's lots of dependencies we dragged in
and all i think there were firebase off we had firebase core we had cloud
firestore and also firebase analytics so these dependencies
themselves can bring with them a lot of other dependencies so
um it is important that that then to know that
as i mentioned in the previous chapter in chapter eight bringing dependencies
is not just all
butterflies and balloons in the sky it is actually a serious process you need
to consider what's bringing in a dependency means to you and your team
and your application so in this case we've only brought
dependencies that were officially done by google and google is behind flutter
so i think then the
you can basically trust anything that has to do with firebase at least so
if it's released by the google team that work on firebase of course
um so we're gonna let it do its thing i'm gonna just tap here and i can see
that it's building quite a lot of files
if everything goes according to our plan
then the result is going to be that
application run on this phone so um
it would be very exciting actually to see if this will
work as we intend to and as i mentioned depending on the
computer that you're using this process may take
in the beginning at least quite a lot of time
so if you have a powerful computer it may take less time and if you have a
little bit less powerful computer it may take some more time
and um now that we're waiting i should also
probably mention that this process of waiting is only initially
something you need to do once the build has been done once it
kind of like its artifacts will be cached inside your computer
so that you don't have to rebuild the entire project from the beginning okay
so um
i'm gonna let it do its thing and uh while we're waiting actually we
could talk a little bit about quicktime which is a caption i brought here
if you're like me and you like to like debug your applications on real phones
then you may want to see or show that your your phone's screen
and on your computer so for instance if
you're sharing your computer as a screen with a co-worker and he or she wants to
also see your application running on your phone you will need to use
something called a quicktime network quicktime
so we're going to talk about that now but before we do that let me just show
you that here is now our flutter application
run on this telephone so
there we go our app is now running
now that we've done that all of this is done you don't need xcode anymore so i'm
just going to press stop here and what i'm going to do i'm actually going to
run our application from visual studio code or flutter application on that
iphone all right so command shift b or control shift b depending on which
platform you're using and say select device
i'm going to choose my iphone 12 pro then i'm going to go to run and say run
without debugging you don't have any extensions oh not
this file open up your main darp file okay
and then say run run without debugging and you'll see it says launching
so this is going to actually consult xcode and say that hey xcode here's the
flutter application run it on this telephone
so
and to be honest with you i actually didn't like this that it's using
automatic signing it what may have happened is that when
we did flutter clea clean you may have messed up our
profiles to be honest with you and this is not a good sign it could be
that when i did flutter clean it actually messed up the profile
so i'm going to open up xcode again and bring up our application again and let's
have a look at our profiles and i can see debug no it's fine it's
not automatic signing so you don't have to worry about this
message that was printed to the screen by uh by flutter so i don't think this
something that we need to worry about so now that you've set that up then you
could actually run your application directly from
visual studio code or android studio depending on which environment you're
running your flutter applications or debugging your
applications from okay now let's say that that is done um
then what you need to do if you want to mirror your application
screen on your computer then you can bring up something called quicktime
player on your macintosh and then go to file and then say movie recording now
this is probably going to hijack my no it didn't hijack anything then i'm
going to go to iphone 12 pro and see if it can mirror
that phone for me
uh
is it not able to do that is it because i'm recording my screen or something i'm
gonna actually [Music]
wait for this debug process to continue
let us do its thing first i think i'm probably trying to do too many things at
the same time so uh
[Applause] i proxy i don't really know what i proxy
is so
um connecting to the vm service taking
longer than except expected and that could be because my macintosh is
actually blocking something that flopper needs so i'm going to go to privacy here
which is security and privacy and just let iproxy to run
allow anyway so that may help flutter then get its
process working
yeah that could be it because maybe my macintosh just blocked that eye proxy so
i'm gonna stop this process and i'm just going to say run run without debugging
again let's see if it can do its work this time
launching and this time since it's actually built the application
previously it shouldn't take long this time before it can run the app
so it has already built the app once so it shouldn't really take as long this
time
so i can now see it says installing and
launching
so let's see if we can get that to work
xcode build done in eight seconds and to be honest with you this is taking
longer than i expected it shouldn't take this long to run the application and i
can see nothing was blocked this time mac os cannot verify the developer of
iproxy and i'm just going to say open i think there is something wrong with
the latest versions of mac os and how it tries to for instance verify
various tools that flutter is using internally but
everything went fine at the end i could actually launch the application from
visual studio code and now it's running inside my iphone
now i'm gonna stop this so now the app as soon as i say stop the app is going
to stop working there what i'm going to do then is to go to
quicktime and see if we can get quicktime to
actually mirror this iphone i'm going to unplug it
the phone and then plug it again and see
if it understands that it has to mirror the phone
i can see my quicktime is also giving me some trouble
and it crashed
i mean this is live uh recording of this session so you can see all the problems
a developer will have to fix and this is me
so let's go to um and see if we can get it to
let's see if i can get it to
recognize this phone
and to be honest with you i mean i'm actually doing this on a separate screen
so you don't have to see my face so much but i can see that my macintosh for some
reason is not recognizing this telephone so i cannot record it basically on this
um uh on this screen right now
but if you're doing this at home it's probably gonna work for you so uh
connect your phone with a cable to your computer and then go to quicktime player
and then with quicktime player say new movie recording and from movie recording
just from the drop down choose your choose your um
phone and you'll be able to mirror your screen so
um now that that is done i mean we actually
got to a lot of hurdles that i hadn't planned for we saw the iproxy thing
happening here grateful that it happened
we saw the error with the pod installation which is the dependency of
our project because there was no minimum version set up for our flutter project
we fixed that we saw a problem with the profile not being picked up
automatically because xcode had created the certificate automatically we fixed
that so
i mean i could for instance now go and filter these out
from the video and kind of like when i actually output the final course for you
then everything will just work perfectly so
you don't have to see any of that hiccup
but i don't want to do that to be honest with you because i think it's so
important for you to see what issues
you will get as you develop your thoughts or applications it is important
i don't want to polish this um i don't want to polish this uh course so much
that you think everything is perfect from the absolute beginning and if
you're and if you're making mistakes then something is wrong with the way
you're developing things but these things happen you need to understand why
they happen then you need to learn how to fix them so
with that said uh
i think then we're good to go uh for ios we've explained
everything we needed to explain uh everything worked except for the
quicktime thing and i think that is because
um i'm actually i have a lot of software open here i am playing stop playing in
stuff recording stuff so it may be because of that is a little bit confused
and who knows maybe my computer needs to restart so
um so with that said let's prepare
ourselves for the next chapter and that is
to do the exact same thing with it for ios hopefully with less explanation now
that we've gone through the basics for android so
uh grab a cup of tea cup coffee whatever you want and i'll see you in the next
chapter hello and welcome to chapter 10 of this
flutter course in this chapter we're going to look at
setting up our android phone
or any android device that you may have at hand in order for us to be able to
run our flutter code on it and now in chapter nine we looked at how we can run
the application and basically run our flash application
on an ios device and we set up the provisioning profiles we set up the
certificates what else the app id
at app store can on um apple's developer website
i mean there is a lot of work to do and you know that chapter took about an hour
to explain everything but when it then comes to
the android side things are a lot easier um
so i thought in this chapter we're gonna
have a look at how we can have an android phone for instance in my
case here i have a oneplus pro 7 pro that is connected with a usb cable to my
computer so there's nothing special about it it's just an android phone and
um i prefer to actually as i mentioned in
the previous chapter in chapter 9 that i prefer personally when i'm developing
applications to developing floss applications to run my
applications on a real phone or a real device as i'm testing now
um you may not know this if you're coming from like a design background or
a background that's not really related to mobile development in previously but
um if you're developing applications for
only ios then you have something called an ios simulator
um an io simulator is a program that runs on your macintosh that comes with
xcode and the ios sdk that allows you to simulate how ios internally works and it
allows you to install your applications from xcode directly or from from flutter
directly into the simulator and simulate basically how your application will be
perceived by your actual users if you're developing applications for
android then there is something called an android emulator now an emulator is
quite different from a simulator in that an emulator as its name indicates it
actually tries to emulate everything about the operating system and the
device so for instance an android emulator for an old device for instance
that you may get a hold of a device that's five six years old
it will actually work slower than an android emulator for a very
modern device but had you done the same thing for an
ios simulator and simulated an ios device that's five years old
it would still perform at today's like at your computer's uh
speed because it is simulating ios it's not actually emulating it the way it
really works on a phone so when it comes to android you have this
possibility to run your application on an emulator which is a lot closer to the
actual device that your user will be using
so it is not the exact perfect copy in most cases so it's not gonna be like
working exactly as a real physical phone but it's a lot closer to the actual
physical device that an ios simulator is so
given that background i still prefer to run my flutter applications on a real
phone and in this chapter
if you're interested in that if you're if you have an android phone and you
want to for instance deploy your flutter application on an android phone and test
it while you're programming it then this chapter is for you
now i also have to say that um
mean [Music]
you don't you don't have to do this but for the
entire entirety of this course i'm actually going to be
as we're developing the application the notes application i'm personally going
to be using my android phone
so that um so as we basically do hot reloads and
then we write some code and we want to test it i'm not going to show any
emulator i'm not going to show any simulator i'm actually going to show my
real android phone working now i'm not going to show it with just
like i'm not going to install the application
here and just show you like this because this is not going to work it's not a
good way of showing things to uh to someone watching this course so what
we're gonna do is as the first
task in this uh chapter we are going to install an application on our um
computer called scrcpy okay
now scrcp cpy is a is an open source project
um that is on github with
many thousand stars and it is not like a dependency it's not something
that you're going to build into your flutter application but it's actually
utility you're going to install on your computer okay so
your computer will will then be able to mirror your android
phone or your android tablet on your computer's screen so
and this scr cpy is absolutely beautiful it's one of my absolute favorite
utilities to have when doing mobile development
and the reason behind that is that unlike the
um solution that i showed in the previous
chapter which is quicktime quicktime player where you mirror your ios
telephone on your computer but you cannot interact with that mirrored image
you still have to bring up your telephone and interact with the
telephone and see the interactions either on the phone itself or on your
screen unlike that scrcpy allows you to actually interact with your phone or
your tablet or your android phone or tablet
from your computer screen so you can actually take your mouse and then go to
that screen and tap on a button and it will actually tap on that button on your
android telephone so it is magical it's beautiful it's open
source and free so if you have an android tablet or an android phone and
you're following along with this course i highly recommend that we install